<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Tiger &#8211; neverendingbooks</title>
	<atom:link href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tag/tiger/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Dec 2007 20:15:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>NeB on Leopard and iPhone</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/neb-on-leopard-and-iphone/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/neb-on-leopard-and-iphone/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Dec 2007 20:15:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Leopard]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[markdown]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[OSX]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tiger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wordpress]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=49</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If you have an iPhone or iPod Touch and point your Safari browser to this blog you can now view it in optimised format, thanks&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/iphone.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;"> If you have an iPhone or iPod Touch and point your Safari browser to <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/">this blog</a> you can now view it in optimised format, thanks to the <a href="http://iwphone.contentrobot.com/">iWPhone WordPress Plugin and Theme</a>. I&#8217;ve only changed the CSS slightly to have the same greeny look-and-feel of the current <a href="http://www.deanjrobinson.com/wordpress/redoable">redoable theme</a>.</p>
<p>Upgrading a WordPress-blog running under Tiger (Mac OS 10.4) to <a href="http://www.apple.com/macosx/">Leopard</a> produces a few anxiety moments. All of the standard tools (Apache, PHP and MySQL) seem no longer to work as before. For those of you who do not want to waste too much time over it, I&#8217;ll walk through the process.</p>
<p>After upgrading to Leopard you want to check whether your blog is still alive, so you fire up Safari and will be greeted by the message that Safari cannot find your server. Sure enough you forgot to start the WebServer in SystemPreferences/Sharing/Web Sharing. Having fixed this you will see the default Apache-screen because Leopard put these default-files in your webserver-root directory (/Library/WebServer/Documents). In case you installed your blog under a user account you will get a message that you enter forbidden territory, see below for the solution to that problem. Having removed all those index.html files (making sure NOT to delete the index.php of your blog) a more serious problem presents itself : you see the text-version of index.php meaning that PHP isnt working. You check the /etc/httpd/httpd.conf file and it still contains all the changes you made to it to get PHP running under Tiger, so what is going on?</p>
<p>Googling for something like &#8216;enabling PHP under Leopard&#8217; you&#8217;ll discover that the configuration file used by the webserver is in a different location. It now resides at /private/etc/apache2/httpd.conf. You will have to remove the hash sign (#) at the beginning of line 114 so that it reads</p>
<p class="code">LoadModule php5_module    libexec/apache2/libphp5.so
</p>
<p>Next, you have to create a php.ini file and change one line. The first thing is settled by the following Terminal-commands</p>
<p class="code">
cd /private/etc<br />
sudo cp php.ini.default php.ini
</p>
<p>and in the php.ini you have to modify line 305 so that it becomes (removing the latter part of the line)</p>
<p class="code">error_reporting = E_ALL
</p>
<p>Restarting the webserver enables PHP. If you need more details check out the article <a href="http://foundationphp.com/tutorials/php_leopard.php">Enabling PHP and Apache in Leopard</a>. However, you are not quite done yet. Your blog will now show the WordPress-page that something is wrong with your mysql-database. However, mysql seems to be running fine as you can check from the Terminal so PHP cannot find it.</p>
<p>To remedy this, you have to add the locations (after the = sign) in the follwing two lines of the php.ini file</p>
<p class="code">mysql.default_socket = /private/tmp/mysql.sock <br />
mysqli.default_socket = /private/tmp/mysql.sock</p>
<p>Restarting the webserver should resolve the problem. But then your blog can still choke on old PHP-code in one of the plugins you use. In my case I was using an ancient version of the <a href="http://michelf.com/projects/php-markdown/">PHP-Markdown plugin</a> but after replacing it with the newest version NeB looked just like I left it with Tiger&#8230;</p>
<p>A final point : webpages stored in personal Sites-folders cannot be served by Apache2 and will produce a message that you have not enough privileges to view the page. To resolve this, type the following command from the Terminal</p>
<p class="code">sudo cp /private/etc/httpd/users/*.conf  /private/etc/Apache2/users</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/neb-on-leopard-and-iphone/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>NeverEndingBooks-general</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/neverendingbooks-general/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/neverendingbooks-general/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2007 13:17:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arxiv]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blogging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GMD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[google]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LaTeX]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[latexrender]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Riemann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[teaching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tiger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wordpress]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/?p=8</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here a list of pdf-files of NeverEndingBooks-posts on general topics, in reverse chronological order. Bloomsday end Group think 2 Down with determinants Group think MathML&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here a list of pdf-files of NeverEndingBooks-posts on general topics, in reverse chronological order.</p>
<p><span id="more-12054"></span></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/323.pdf">Bloomsday end</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/322.pdf">Group think 2</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/321.pdf">Down with determinants</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/317.pdf">Group think</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/310.pdf">MathML versus LatexRender</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/303.pdf">Stalking the Riemann hypothesis</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/238.pdf">MathML and work ahead</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/234.pdf">The secret life of numbers</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/220.pdf">CCDantas on blogging</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/211.pdf">Doing the Perelman</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/206.pdf">The n-category cafe</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/190.pdf">Writing with gloves on</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/179.pdf">Why mathematicians cannot write</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/178.pdf">The music of the primes</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/173.pdf">arXiv trackback wars</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/146.pdf">citeUlike</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/143.pdf">The efficient academic</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/20.pdf">2005 lists : math novels</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/16.pdf">Teaching mathematics</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/14.pdf">Two TA Tales</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/10.pdf">The Oxford murders</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/9.pdf">Mappalujo</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/3.pdf">LatexRender Plugin for WordPress under Tiger</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/57.pdf">GMD</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/268.pdf">Google scholar</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/249.pdf">Simonne Stevens (1926-2004)</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/32.pdf">Quiver pictures in WordPress</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/136.pdf">Groen moet!</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/132.pdf">Artistic (and other) frustrations</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/94.pdf">The cpu 2 generation</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/neverendingbooks-general/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>hold on to those PPC macs</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/hold-on-to-those-ppc-macs/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/hold-on-to-those-ppc-macs/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 May 2006 08:53:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LaTeX]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PPC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tiger]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=307</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On my return from O a brand new 15inch MacBook Pro lie waiting in my office. By that evening I had wrecked the system to&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/macbookpro.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;" />   On my<br />
return from <a href="http://www.mfo.de/">O</a> a brand new 15inch <a href="http://www.apple.com/macbookpro/">MacBook Pro</a> lie waiting in<br />
my office. By that evening I had wrecked the system to the extend that I<br />
could no longer login and had to reinstall from scratch&#8230; I was<br />
about to trow it away but tried it out for a few more days and<br />
eventually began to understand it a bit. In short : the new Intel Macs<br />
promise to be really good hardware, unfortunately some essential<br />
software lags behind, so if you want a stress-free Mac-life&#8230; hold<br />
on to your PPC mac a few months longer. If you are impatient and want to<br />
learn some of the pitfalls, read on&#8230;    I&#8217;m ashamed to admit this<br />
but the first thing I did on my new machine was to create a WindowsXP<br />
partition&#8230; <a href="http://www.apple.com/macosx/bootcamp/">BootCamp</a> does what it<br />
promises to do and is extremely easy to use once you can start it. The<br />
installation guide does tell that you jave to update your systems<br />
software and firmware, but that&#8217;s what you do anyway after a new<br />
install, right? Wrong! You update the software but _not_ the<br />
firmware and it took me some time to come to this simple conclusion. How<br />
to check whether your firmware is up to date? Go under the apple to<br />
&#8216;About this Mac&#8217;, click on &#8216;More Info&#8217; and look at your<br />
&#8216;  Boot ROM Version:&#8217; if it says MBP11.0055.B03 you&#8217;re ok, if not<br />
you have to install the <a href="http://www.apple.com/support/downloads/macbookprosmcfirmwareupdate.html">newest firmware</a> which is a slightly terrifying experience<br />
with soundsignals included, but works fine. Once this is done, you can<br />
start BootCamp and have a Windows partition in no time. At a certain<br />
moment you have to decide on possible partition-formats for the Windows<br />
part, I choose the &#8216;Fat&#8217; option to be able to swap files across<br />
the partitions.    Next, what does a mathematician wants from a<br />
computer? To run LaTeX! I&#8217;ve installed LaTeX on more Macs than I<br />
remember so I continued on automatic pilot, getting Gerben Wierda&#8217;s <a href="http://ii2.sourceforge.net/">i-Installer</a>, startd it up and<br />
&#8230; my machine froze! Nothing, not even a &#8216;Force Quit&#8217;, was<br />
possible any more. Today, there is a clear warning message as the<br />
i-Installer page (i don&#8217;t recall seeing it there last week, but then it<br />
is a recent problem. Things broke down on May 11th when I was still in<br />
O)   </p>
<blockquote><p> WARNING: i-Installer on Mac OS X 10.4.6 may trigger<br />
the Mac OS X 10.4.6 bug that partially freezes your system.  May 2006:<br />
i-Installer did work perfectly on Mac OS X 10.4.3, the version of Tiger<br />
that was shipped with the Developer Transition Kit. When the first intel<br />
machines were sold by Apple, these contained 10.4.4 and on that system,<br />
i-Installer experiences troubles because of problems deep inside Apple&#8217;s<br />
Frameworks. The only way I could solve this was to make i-Installer a<br />
PowerPC-only application again and ask for Apple&#8217;s help to determine<br />
where the problem was. So far, this has been s slow process without any<br />
noticeable results. The PowerPC-only version worked fine until Apple<br />
released 10.4.6 and especially the latest upgrades (Security Upgrade<br />
2006-003 and maybe QuickTime). As I am writing this (May 21) a<br />
completely updated Mac OS X 10.4.6 on intel will partially freeze in<br />
various circumstances, triggered by various applications (MatLab,<br />
i-Installer, etc.). Sadly, the just released MacBook (successor of the<br />
iBook) is shipping with this broken version of the OS. Hence, there is<br />
now no i-Installer that reliably works on intel machines with recent OS<br />
versions and even worse, i-Installer may trigger a nasty bug in recent<br />
Mac OS X intel versions.  </p></blockquote>
<p>   Scary isn&#8217;t it? You have a<br />
brand new expensive machine but cannot typeset a single paper&#8230;<br />
Fortunately, the <a href="http://www.uoregon.edu/~koch/texshop/obtaining.html">TeXShop<br />
page</a> not only mentions the problem, but also a workaround</p>
<blockquote><p> On May 11, 2006, Apple provided security updates for Mac OS<br />
X. These updates broke i-Installer on Intel (it continues to work on<br />
PowerPC). If you have an Intel Mac and you have installed this update,<br />
you must use the MacTeX install package until this problem is fixed.<br />
Once TeX is installed, it works fine. </p></blockquote>
<p>   The first<br />
assertion is true : installing the <a href="http://www.tug.org/~koch/">MacTeX package</a> gives you a working<br />
TeX-installation, with TeXShop, Excalibur, BibTeX and i-Installer coming<br />
for free. But don&#8217;t think the i-Installer problem has been solved, I<br />
tried it out and voila another ice-age&#8230;    So far so good but<br />
sometimes we like to compute things, don&#8217;t we? Like some commutative<br />
algebra or algebraic geometry things via <a href="http://www.singular.uni-kl.de/">Singular</a>? I remembered to<br />
install this via the <a href="http://fink.sourceforge.net/">Fink<br />
project</a> but already their news-items are not very promissing</p>
<blockquote><p> A preliminary version of Fink for the Intel architecture is<br />
now ready. No binary packages are available, and things are still rough<br />
around the edges, but it should be usable if you are patient!  To<br />
install it, you need to install the XCode compiler and SDK packages (at<br />
minimum). Then you need to get the file fink-0.24.14.tar.gz from the<br />
Sourceforge file release page for Fink, expand the file, and run the<br />
command ./bootstrap.sh . At the end of the bootstrap process, run fink<br />
selfupdate and you&#8217;ll get the currently available packages.  At last<br />
check, there were about 1750 packages in the &#8220;stable&#8221; tree,<br />
but about 150 of those did not build. When things are truly stable,<br />
another annoucement will be made here. </p></blockquote>
<p>   The normal<br />
FinkCommander didn&#8217;t work either but then I found a version which does<br />
at <a href="http://homepage.mac.com/charleslo/">Charles K. C. Lo&#8217;s<br />
Homepage</a>. I verified it by having the fink-TeTeX package installed<br />
(which works!) and then I wanted to do a Singular-install&#8230; Things<br />
seemed to start off well (once you change the freferences to install<br />
also unstable packages) but then the installation procedure halted with<br />
the message   </p>
<blockquote><p> Failed: phase compiling: singular-3.0.1-1013<br />
failed  Before reporting any errors, please run &#8220;fink<br />
selfupdate&#8221; and try again.  If you continue to have issues, please<br />
check to see if the FAQ on fink&#8217;s website solves the problem.  If not,<br />
ask on the fink-users or fink-beginners mailing lists.  As a last<br />
resort, you can try e-mailing the maintainer directly:          Michael<br />
Brickenstein bricken at mathematik.uni-kl.de  <strong>Note that many<br />
fink package maintainers do not (yet) have access to OS X on Intel<br />
hardware, so you may have better luck on the mailing lists.</strong>
</p></blockquote>
<p>   So, maybe I should just donate my MacBook Pro to the<br />
Fink-project? A similar problem with installing Maxima&#8230; I didn&#8217;t<br />
even try out GAP via Fink but went for a niversal Unix-installation for<br />
GAP and this WORKED! even with all packages and tables and the whole I<br />
dont know what. Thank you, GAPpers, perhaps all algebraists on Intel<br />
Macs should shift to GroupTheory?    But hey! My Intel-Mac does have a<br />
WindowsXP partition&#8230; So, I did a binary Windows install of<br />
Singular and Maxima and both work without problems. Still, it is a<br />
strange situation. Fortunately, I did resolve these issues but that will<br />
have to wait until tomorrow&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/hold-on-to-those-ppc-macs/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>latexrender plugin for wordpress under tiger</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/latexrender-plugin-for-wordpress-under-tiger/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/latexrender-plugin-for-wordpress-under-tiger/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2005 15:26:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LaTeX]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[latexrender]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[markdown]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tiger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wordpress]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=165</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Promises and pie-crusts are made to be broken, a wiser man once said. Still, promises have a much longer life-span and sometimes their real content&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p> Promises and pie-crusts are made to be broken, a <a href="http://www.incompetech.com/authors/swift/">wiser man</a> once<br />
  said. Still, promises have a much longer life-span and sometimes their<br />
  real content becomes redundant over time.</p>
<p>A year ago, I<br />
  promised<br />
  to document how I got the <a href="http://sixthform.info/steve/wordpress/index.php?cat=2"><br />
  LaTeXRender Plugin for WordPress</a> working under OS X. The procedure<br />
  consisted of some trial-and-error operations, installing non-standard<br />
  versions of software and hardcoding certain directories throughout<br />
  certain files&#8230;</p>
<p>Not something I was looking forward<br />
  to when I decided to upgrade this <a href="http://www.wordpress.org/">WordPress</a> blog but,<br />
  surprisingly, things went pretty smoothly this time (Mac-technology<br />
  has improved a lot). So, please don&#8217;t worry too much about <a href="http://sixthform.info/steve/wordpress/index.php?p=23">this<br />
  post</a> and follow the (late) instructions below.</p>
<p>First<br />
  things first : I will assume you have the &#8216;generic&#8217; LaTeX<br />
  running under Tiger (10.4),that is, use the <a href="http://www.rna.nl/ii.html">i-Installer</a> to download BOTH<br />
  LaTeX and Imagemagick! Further, in order to get WordPress up and<br />
  running, have <a href="http://dev.mysql.com/downloads/mysql/4.0.html">the standard<br />
  MySQL 4.0 package</a> installed for 10.3 (<strong>not</strong> version<br />
  4.1&#8230;) and don&#8217;t use the generic Mac-PHP version, but<br />
  instead download <a href="http://www.entropy.ch/software/macosx/php/">Marc<br />
  Liyanage&#8217;s PHP5 package</a> which has plenty of additional<br />
  packages installed (notably, GDlib and MCRYPT which comes in handy if<br />
  you want to fight spam-comments using <a href="http://www.blueeye.us/wordpress/?p=5">BotCheck</a>).</p>
<p> \r<br />
  \n</p>
<p>Download <a href="http://sixthform.info/steve/wordpress/index.php">wp-<br />
  latexrender.zip</a> and follow the instructions given to the letter<br />
  (there is one undocumented extra directory you have to fill in at the<br />
  start of the <strong>latexrender-plugin.php</strong> file). There is<br />
  just one additional thing to do. Find in the<br />
  <strong>class.latexrender.php</strong> file the line starting<br />
  with</p>
<pre>// convert dvi file to postscript using
  dvips</pre>
<p>  and include the following lines just before it<br />
  :  </p>
<pre>// begin of workaround // extending the PATH
  environmental variable Soldpath =
  getenv(“PATH”); Swhere_imagemagick_is =
  “/usr/local/bin”; if (Soldpath) { Swhere_imagemagick_is .=
  “:Soldpath”;} putenv(“PATH=Swhere_imagemagick_is”); //
  end of workaround </pre>
<p>activate the plugin and it<br />
  should work! Still, there are three things you may want to change. In<br />
  the <strong>latex.php</strong> file uncomment the indicated lines as<br />
  you will be using htmlArea to input your posts. In addition, if you<br />
  have the MarkDown-plugin enabled, it is best to append additional<br />
  lines such as</p>
<pre> Slatex_formula =
  str_replace(“_”,”_”,Slatex_formula);     Slatex_formula
  =
  str_replace(“_”,”_”,Slatex_formula); </pre>
<p>(<br />
  between the first &#8221; &#8221; should be the beginning and end<br />
  em-tag respectively) or underscores will be interpreted as em-tags.<br />
  If you run into additional similar problems, the procedure is to<br />
  comment-out the line</p>
<pre>
  unlink(Sthis->_tmp_dir.”/”.Sthis->_tmp_filename.”.tex”);
  </pre>
<p>  near the end of  class.latexrender.php  , look in the<br />
  tmp directory for the TeX-file, detect the problem and add similar<br />
  lines to the ones above to solve it.  Another useful thing to do<br />
  is to add TeX-packages in the class.latexrender.php file. My own<br />
  version has the following predefined symbols and loaded<br />
  packages  </p>
<pre> function wrap_formula(Slatex_formula) {
  Sstring  =
  “\\documentclass[“.Sthis->_font_size.”pt]{“.Sthis->_latexclass
  .”}\\n”;  Sstring .=
  “\\usepackage[latin1]{inputenc}\\n”;  Sstring .=
  “\\usepackage{amsmath}\\n”;  Sstring .=
  “\\usepackage{amsfonts}\\n”;  Sstring .=
  “\\usepackage{amssymb}\\n”;  Sstring .=
  “\\usepackage{xy}\\n”;  Sstring .=
  “\\xyoption{all}\\n”;  Sstring .=
  “\\\\newcommand{\\vtx}[1]{*+[o][F-]{Scriptscriptstyle
  #1}}\\n”;  Sstring .= “\\\\newcommand{\\mathbb{C}c}{\\Bbbk}\\n”;
  Sstring .= “\\\\newcommand{\\mathbb{C}}{\\mathbb{C}}\\n”;  Sstring .=
  “\\\\newcommand{\\mathbb{Q}}{\\mathbb{Q}}\\n”;  Sstring .=
  “\\\\newcommand{\\mathbb{Z}}{\\mathbb{Z}}\\n”;  Sstring .=
  “\\\\newcommand{\\mathbb{N}}{\\mathbb{N}}\\n”;  Sstring .=
  “\\\\newcommand{\\mathbf}[1]{{\\\\text{\\em \\usefont{OT1}{cmtt}{m}{n}
  #1}}}\\n”;  Sstring .= “\\pagestyle{empty}\\n”;  Sstring
  .= “\\begin{document}\\n”;  Sstring .=
  “S”.Slatex_formula.”S\\n”;  Sstring .=
  “\\end{document}\\n”;          return Sstring;     }
  </pre>
<p>   which, among other things, allow all commenters to add<br />
  quiver-pictures using xymatrix and vtx to depict vertices. Oh yes, you<br />
  can allow comments to include LaTeX-code by uncommenting the<br />
  line   </p>
<pre>  // add_filter(‘comment_text’,
  ‘addlatex’); </pre>
<p>in the latexrender-plugin.php<br />
  file (but before you do make sure you have spam under control, such as<br />
  with BotCheck mentioned above). That&#8217;s all for now. If you want<br />
  to use TeX in a comment, make sure to put the code between tags [ tex<br />
  ] and [ /tex ] (omitting the extra spaces). If you want me to add<br />
  other LaTeX-packages, leave a comment.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/latexrender-plugin-for-wordpress-under-tiger/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>tiger tracks</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tiger-tracks/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tiger-tracks/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2005 08:17:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tiger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tracks]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=288</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I got Tracks working under Tiger by trial and error starting with a suggestion from Jan who found a fix here. From this I stumbled&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I got<br />
Tracks working under Tiger by trial and error starting with a suggestion<br />
from Jan who found a fix <a href="http://www.macosxhints.com/article.php?story=20050526080438129#comments">here</a>. From this I stumbled on for an hour or so on my iMac<br />
untill near the very end I found that the tracks-page <a href="http://dev.rousette.org.uk/wiki/Tracks/Install/Mac">itself</a> now<br />
has a Tiger-section. So, let&#8217;s try to do it all over again from fresh on<br />
my regular machine (a little iBook).  </p>
<p>Start with <a href="http://wiki.rubyonrails.com/rails/show/HowtoInstallOnOSXTiger"><br />
this page</a> and read it all the way to the comments. There is a<br />
comment by Jamie on installing Rails and MySQL on a fresh Tiger which<br />
looks like the thing I want followed immediately by another post by Jose<br />
Marinez on <a href="http://jmarinez.typepad.com/blog/2005/06/installing_ruby.html"><br />
Installing Ruby on Rails on Tiger</a> which I decided to follow by the<br />
letter (with one noticeable exception!). So first I downloaded the <a href="http://users.tpg.com.au/aarnold/Ruby%20on%20Rails.zip">Rails<br />
installer on Tiger</a>. Next, an install of the Standard version  of<br />
MySQL. I used <a href="http://dev.mysql.com/downloads/mysql/4.0.html">version 4.0 for OS<br />
X 10.3 !!!! NOT 4.1 !!!!</a>. I installed MySQL and the StartUpItem.<br />
Next, I opened Terminal and typed the following commands</p>
<p>&#8211; cd<br />
/usr/local/mysql<br /> &#8211; sudo chown -R mysql data/<br /> &#8211; sudo echo<br
/> &#8211; sudo ./bin/mysqld_safe &#038;  </p>
<p>and verified it by performing a<br />
simple test</p>
<p>/usr/local/mysql/bin/mysql test</p>
<p>Next, I<br />
secured everything by having a root-password</p>
<p>/usr/local/mysql/bin/mysqladmin -u root password<br />
<strong>__</strong>*</p>
<p>Then I remembered that I&#8217;d better<br />
not have to type the whole path so I did a</p>
<p>echo &#8216;export<br />
PATH=/usr/local/mysql/bin:$PATH&#8217; >> ~/.bash_profile</p>
<p>Also, I want<br />
to admin MySQL via <a href="http://www.phpmyadmin.net/home_page/index.php">phpmyadmin</a> so I<br />
installed it. Then I enabled my webserver to use PHP using <a href="http://phpmac.com/articles.php?view=225">this post</a> though I<br />
did use vi rather than pico! Next, i did a check whether everything<br />
worked fine by typing in safari</p>
<p>http://localhost/~lieven/phpmyadmin/index.php</p>
<p>Followed by<br />
a</p>
<p>sudo gem install mysql –<br />
–with-mysql-dir=/usr/local/mysql</p>
<p>Now, it is time to get the <a href="http://www.rousette.org.uk/projects/downloads/">Tracks-package</a><br />
and to follow <a href="http://dev.rousette.org.uk/file/trunk/tracks/doc/README.txt?rev=72
">these instructions</a> And, it works! Here is the proof :</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/tigertracks.jpg" /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tiger-tracks/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>balm or poison</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/balm-or-poison/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/balm-or-poison/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2005 06:20:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tiger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tracks]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=274</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Don&#8217;t try to follow the previous post unless you want to end up in a neverending (sic!) series of re-installs, unrecognized harddisks at start-up and&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Don&#8217;t try<br />
to follow the previous post unless you want to end up in a neverending<br />
(sic!) series of re-installs, unrecognized harddisks at start-up and a<br />
few kernel-panics!  </p>
<p>At this moment I know of NO safe way to use <a href="http://www.bombich.com/software/ccc.html">Carbon Copy Cloner</a><br />
to make a bootable clone of my HD. Here is the only way I managed to<br />
make a bootable copy :</p>
<p>&#8211; before you start, click on the<br />
target-partition of the external HD and use _File/Get Info_ and<br />
uncheck under _Ownership &#038; Permissions_ the box _Ignore<br />
ownership on this volume_<br /> &#8211; this might be enough for you but I<br />
had to use DiskUtility to _Erase_ the externet HD-partition.<br
/> &#8211; then follow the previous post (that is do _sudo open_ on CCC<br />
and then proceed as usual <strong>BUT</strong> make sure in your<br />
prefernces only the box _Make Bootable_ is checked and certainly<br />
no syncing-options!)   </p>
<p>A bit too drastic for me. Its a bit like<br />
: make a DMG of your MacintoshHD and do a restore on an empty external<br />
partition. It seems that Tiger and Panther have very different<br />
DNA-samples bringing a lot of excellent free- and shareware developers<br />
near a nervous breakdown. Have the Apple-people ever heard of something<br />
like _backwards compatibility_? Anyway, I&#8217;m not going to try<br />
making another backup again until Mike Bombich has released a<br />
Tiger-version of CCC!</p>
<p>Also, don&#8217;t try to follow the suggestions<br />
of my <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php?p=65">Tracks<br />
post</a>. It certainly is not enough to get tracks running under Tiger<br />
(and probably also not under Panther as at the time I did a strange mix<br />
of following this path and doing some manual installs using the <a href="http://hivelogic.com/archives/2005/03/18/ruby_install/">Hivelogic<br />
page</a>. This time, I got strange errors coming from the Ruby-MySQL<br />
dialogue. I&#8217;m not going to try installing MySQL, PHP and Tracks before<br />
someone like <a href="http://www.entropy.ch/software/macosx/mysql/">Marc<br />
Lyanage</a> tells that it is safe to use the Panther-packages under<br />
Tiger!</p>
<p>So, for the moment I&#8217;m just going to use my minimal<br />
system (Tiger+Xcode Tools+TeX (following the instructions from <a href="http://www.uoregon.edu/~koch/texshop/obtaining.html">this page</a><br />
)+some excellent free and shareware like <a href="http://www.devon-technologies.com/products/devonthink/overview.php">DevonThink</a>  , <a href="http://www.kainjow.com/pod2go/">Pod2Go</a><br />
, <a href="http://flyingmeat.com/voodoopad/">VoodooPad</a> , <a href="http://www.codingmonkeys.de/subethaedit/">SubEthaEdit</a> ,<br />
<a href="http://quicksilver.blacktree.com/">QuickSilver</a> , <a href="http://www.panic.com/transmit/index.html">Transmit</a> and  <a href="http://ranchero.com/netnewswire/">NetNewsWire</a>  ) until the<br />
experts have tamed Tiger. Meanwhile, I&#8217;ll just confine myself to the<br />
_Dashboard-Kintergarten_ !</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/balm-or-poison/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>tiger days 1</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tiger-days-1/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tiger-days-1/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2005 07:24:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LaTeX]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[latexrender]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tiger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tracks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wordpress]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=290</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It should be really day 2 but yesterday evening I was a bit overoptimistic and tried to get MySQL, Ruby, Rails &#38; Tracks installed and&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It<br />
should be really day 2 but yesterday evening I was a bit overoptimistic<br />
and tried to get MySQL, Ruby, Rails &amp; Tracks installed and in the<br />
process totally wrecked my Ruby-system (and probably a few things more).<br />
Besides, I found out that the _Carbon Copy Cloner_ work-around<br />
doesn\&#8217;t really work (that is, one canNOT boot from the cloned copy)<br />
etc. etc. In short, a lot of frustration. So today, I started all over<br />
again (using the install notes below to guide me and so I could reduce<br />
the total time to about 2 hrs). But, as this was the easy bit (still to<br />
come : MySQL, PHP, WordPress+LatexRender, Ruby&amp;Tracks etc.) and I<br />
don\&#8217;t want to redo everything again when I do something horribly wrong<br />
I changed my overall tactics. I\&#8217;ll keep identical copies on my iBook<br />
and on my iMac and do the next batch of installs on just one machine and<br />
check whether everything works before syncing it to the other. If<br />
something gets messed up I resync to the state of the previous day. Just<br />
one question left : what program to use for the backup/restore now that<br />
CCC seems to be broken? Fortunately, there is still <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/psyncx/">PsyncX</a> which still<br />
seems to work fine (at least today&#8230;). Below, for what it is worth,<br />
yesterday\&#8217;s log of events :  </p>
<p>Okay, I checked that I can still<br />
TeX papers and connect to the printer on the iMac (after Archive/Install<br />
to Tiger). Most other things have broken down, such as my <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php?p=271">mind on tracks</a><br />
and my MySQL-database, but I\&#8217;m quite hopeful I can rebuild them all.<br />
So, time for a drastic _Erase/Install_ on my iBook.   </p>
<p><strong>12:04</strong> : One final safety check. Connect the external<br />
HD, select the _Carbon Copy Cloned_ partition as StartUp Disk and<br />
do a Restart to verify that it can be cloned back should everything go<br />
terribly wrong. Seems to work nicely, so change again from StartUp disk,<br />
restart and disconnect the external HD.  </p>
<p><strong>12:16</strong><br />
: Printed the <a href="http://www.macdevcenter.com/lpt/a/5825">macdevcenter install<br />
tips</a> and made a fresh pot of coffee. Took the unread part of the<br />
newspaper with me, connected Jan\&#8217;s iPod, made it the new StartUp disk<br />
and did another Restart.  </p>
<p><strong>12:24</strong> : Selected<br />
\&#8217;English\&#8217; as the main language. Selected _DiskUtility_ from the<br />
_Utilities_ menu (before you have to select a Disk destination).<br />
Selected the HD, clicked _Erase_ and choose _Erase Free<br />
Space_ first, then choose the SecurityOption to \&#8217;zero out data\&#8217;.<br />
(Both steps require a lot of extra time but what is the point of doing<br />
an Erase if you don\&#8217;t erase properly? Btw. the macdev-article does not<br />
agree with me on this point.) Meanwhile, had some coffee and a<br />
read&#8230;  </p>
<p><strong>13:23</strong> : Did quit DiskUtility<br />
which brought me back to the Installer. Selected the HD and clicked on<br />
_Options_ to select Erase&amp;Install and clicked Continue. Then<br />
clicked on _Custom Install_ to choose which Packages to Install.<br />
Did choose _all_ Printer Drivers but in _Language<br />
Translations_ only selected : French, German and Dutch. Didn\&#8217;t<br />
select X11! Clicked : _Install_ and had yet another cup of<br />
coffee&#8230;  </p>
<p><strong>13:45</strong> : Restarted! Got me into<br />
the SetupAssistant. Didn\&#8217;t choose to transfer info from another Mac. It<br />
selected our wireless network immediately, and asked me for my .Mac<br />
account info. Did create my main account and finished at<br />
<strong>13:53</strong> Only had to stop iTunes from wanting to put<br />
PodSoftware onto the connected iPod&#8230; Checked for SoftwareUpdate<br />
but there was none. Am connected to internet but had to add my other<br />
mail-account. Done and received email at <strong>14:05</strong> Found<br />
our Printer but did gray out two-sided printing (have to remember later<br />
how I did set this up&#8230;).  </p>
<p><strong>14:12</strong> : Time<br />
to add the _Xcode Tools_ : opened the folder on the iPod and<br />
clicked on _XcodeTools.mpkg_ . Followed he default installation.<br />
Finished and deconnected the iPod at <strong>14:24</strong> Took a break<br />
to decide how to continue. (21.97Gb available) Update today : do a<br />
custom install using also cross-development!  </p>
<p><strong>14:37</strong> : Okay, first things first : get myself a<br />
working TeX-system starting from <a href="http://www.uoregon.edu/~koch/texshop/obtaining.html">this page</a><br />
to get the latest version of TeXShop and the i-Installer and place both<br />
in the Applications folder and in the Dock. Placed the _To Your<br />
Library_ folder of TeXShop in my ~/Library (containing the texmf<br />
etc. path for pdfsync). Then followed <a href="http://www.uoregon.edu/~koch/texshop/installing.html">this<br />
page</a> and the i-Installer to install the packages in the right order<br />
:  </p>
<ul>
<li>FreeType 2   </li>
<li>libwmf   </li>
<li>Ghostscript<br />
8   </li>
<li>ImageMagick   </li>
<li>FontForge   </li>
<li>TeX (did a<br />
Full install with 2005 Devel.)   </li>
</ul>
<p>Had a brief look<br />
through the other packages and maybe I\&#8217;ll install _Latex to RTF_<br />
and _RTF 2 Latex_ later. Created a _DMG_ folder and put<br />
the downloaded disk images into it. Created a_PAPERS_ folder and<br />
transferred the last version of the paper with Stijn to check TeX but<br />
clearly it couldn\&#8217;t find the _diagrams.sty_ file (I know I have<br />
to quit using this, but I\&#8217;ll better get it over for backward<br />
compatibility; put it into ~/Library/texmf/tex/latex/. Ran TeX again<br />
without problems this time and checked the nice source-PDF syncing<br />
(apple-click to jump). Finished : <strong>15:37</strong>  </p>
<p><strong>15:56</strong> : As long as administration sends me<br />
_Word_ documents and expects me to read them, I have no choice<br />
but to install _Office X_ . The upshot was that while searching<br />
for the OfficeCD I found also the HP LaserJet 1320 CD and installed the<br />
driver so now I can print 2-sided (using Printer Setup Utility) . Done :<br />
<strong>16:15</strong>  </p>
<p><strong>16:45</strong> : Used the<br />
_.mac System Preference_ to get syncing started with my iDisk to<br />
get adresses, calendars and passwords etc. on my iBook. Also filled in<br />
the Sharing Preferences. Now that I have the passwords at hand, it is<br />
time to get the latest versions of some of the shareware I own (and copy<br />
their disk image to the DMG folder)  </p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.devon-technologies.com/products/devonthink/overview.php">DevonThink</a>   </li>
<li><a
href="http://www.devon-technologies.com/products/devonagent/overview.php">DenonAgent</a>   </li>
<li>Pod2Go : the <a href="http://www.kainjow.com/pod2go/">site</a> seems to be down at the<br />
moment but fortunately, I have a disk image of it which will have to do<br />
for now (note to self : check later whether the site is permanently<br />
dead&#8230;) Update today : it is up and running again&#8230;  </li>
</ul>
<p>and while I\&#8217;m at it I may as well get my wallet out and<br />
purchase the full version of _Lite_ versions I like and use a lot<br />
:  </p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://flyingmeat.com/voodoopad/">VoodooPad</a>   </li>
<li><a href="http://ranchero.com/netnewswire/">NetNewsWire</a>   </li>
<li><a href="http://www.panic.com/transmit/index.html">Transmit</a>   </li>
</ul>
<p>Fortunately, there is also a lot of excellent freeware that I<br />
want to use   </p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://quicksilver.blacktree.com/">QuickSilver</a>   </li>
<li><a href="http://www.bombich.com/software/ccc.html">Carbon Copy Cloner</a><br />
Update today : skip and use PsyncX instead.   </li>
<li><a href="http://cocoamysql.sourceforge.net/">CocoaMySQL</a>   </li>
<li><a href="http://www.codingmonkeys.de/subethaedit/">SubEthaEdit</a>   </li>
</ul>
<p>One of the following days : MySQL, PHP and perhaps Tracks but<br />
first I desperately need to do some maths to kick off from all this<br />
nonsense&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tiger-days-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>tiger balm</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tiger-balm/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tiger-balm/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2005 19:32:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[google]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tiger]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=273</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I still havent received my Tiger-package but got a bit panicky because it is released as a DVD and at least one of our recent&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I still<br />
havent received my Tiger-package but got a bit panicky because it is<br />
released as a DVD and at least one of our recent iMacs (the older ones<br />
do not even have build in firewire, let alone enough RAM) cannot read<br />
DVDs. That&#8217;s not a major problem as one can always send the DVD back and<br />
ask for CDs instead (and wait even longer) or you can follow <a href="http://www.oreillynet.com/pub/wlg/6976">this trick</a> (using<br />
Firewire target disk mode). <a href="http://www.math.ua.ac.be/~adri/">Jan</a> suggested another<br />
approach : make the DVD into a _dmg image_, connect an iPod,<br />
erase with DiskUtility its hard disk and use the _Restore_ option<br />
of DiskUtility to copy the dmg onto it. Then choose the iPod as StartUp<br />
Disk and restart and everything works nicely.  </p>
<p>As he went through the<br />
trouble of setting up his iPod, I merely borrowed it and did an<br />
Archive/Install of Tiger on the redundant iMac.All went well and<br />
afterwards you can hardly see the difference with Panther except in the<br />
top right corner where there is the _SpotLight_ icon (a feature I<br />
do like and will use often) and in the lower left corner the<br />
_Dashboard_ icon (a feature which still has to convince me).</p>
<p>Anyway, I wanted to check out as quickly as possible a comment (also<br />
from jan)<br />
that there is a new _Tiger only_ version of <a href="http://www.uoregon.edu/~koch/texshop/texshop.html">TexShop</a> out<br />
which syncs nicely between the PDF-file and the source. As it requires<br />
some extra packages using <a href="http://www.rna.nl/ii.html">i-Installer</a> I took the opportunity<br />
to update my TeX-system. </p>
<p>As they predict bad weather for the<br />
rest of the weekend I thought &#8220;well, why not just begin the<br />
Panther/Tiger switch on my _iBook_ using the iPod trick as well&#8221;.<br />
But first I wanted to backup the latest Tiger+TeX version using<br />
_Carbon Copy Cloner_. Over the last year this has become such a<br />
routine operation (backing up to a slick _Porsche_ designed 250Gb<br />
HD) that I was quite surprised that the computer halted after typing in<br />
the super-user password. Forcing CCC to quit and restarting didn&#8217;t solve<br />
the problem so it was time to do a Google on &#8220;Carbon Copy Cloner Tiger&#8221;<br />
to find out that other (quicker) people had already experienced the<br />
same.</p>
<p>As making a bootable backup is crucial for me I had to<br />
find a way round this and fortunately found the <a href="http://forums.bombich.com/viewtopic.php?t=5264">Tiger balm</a><br />
post. Here&#8217;s the hack :</p>
<p>&#8211; go to the Applications folder<br /> &#8211;<br />
open Terminal and type   <strong>sudo open</strong><br /> &#8211; drag CCC to<br />
the Terminal-window<br /> &#8211; type return and provide superuser<br />
password<br /> &#8211; open CCC and fill in Source and Target disks as<br />
usual<br /> &#8211; it works!  </p>
<p><a href="http://www.bombich.com/software/ccc.html">Rumours</a> are that<br />
Mike Bombich will rewrite CCC shortly to fix this problem. Let&#8217;s just<br />
hope that I don&#8217;t find too many other applications behaving unexpectedly<br />
(in the 2 hours I&#8217;m onto Tiger I also found _Remote Desktop_ not<br />
to work at all but then it&#8217;s an old 1.2 version so maybe Apple took this<br />
chance to force people to upgrade (and pay heavily) as they seem to do<br />
with hardware (someone should come up with a way to get the first<br />
generation iMacs onto Tiger!)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tiger-balm/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>nostalgia</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/nostalgia/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/nostalgia/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2005 18:29:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arxiv]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Connes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[differential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[non-commutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tiger]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=272</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Unlike the cooler people out there, I haven&#8217;t received my _pre-ordered_ copy (via AppleStore) of Tiger yet. Partly my own fault because I couldn&#8217;t resist&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Unlike the<br />
<a href="http://www.rousette.org.uk/blog/archives/2005/05/04/shiny-tiger-things/">cooler people</a> out there, I haven&#8217;t received my<br />
_pre-ordered_ copy (via AppleStore) of <a href="http://www.apple.com/macosx/">Tiger</a> yet. Partly my own fault<br />
because I couldn&#8217;t resist the temptation to bundle up with a<br />
personalized <a href="http://www.apple.com/ipodphoto/">iPod Photo</a>!<br />
The good news is that it buys me more time to follow the <a href="http://www.macdevcenter.com/pub/a/mac/2005/04/26/tiger.html"><br />
housecleaning tips</a>. First, my idea was to make a <a href="http://www.bombich.com/software/ccc.html">CarbonCopyClooner</a>&#8211;<br />
image of my iBook and put it on the _iMac_ upstairs which I<br />
rarely use these days, do a <a href="http://www.macdevcenter.com/pub/a/mac/2005/04/29/tiger.html">clean<br />
Tiger install</a> on the iBook and gradually copy over the essential<br />
programs and files I need (and only those!). But reading the<br />
macdev-article, I think it is better to keep my iBook running Panther<br />
and experiment with Tiger on the redundant iMac. (Btw. unless you want<br />
to have a copy of my Mac-installation there will be hardly a point<br />
checking this blog the next couple of weeks as I intend to write down<br />
all details of the Panther/Tiger switch here.)  </p>
<p>Last week-end I<br />
started a _Paper-rescue_ operation, that is, to find among the<br />
multiple copies of books/papers/courses, the ones that contain all the<br />
required material to re-TeX them and unfortunately my _archive_<br />
is in a bad state. There is hardly a source-file left of a paper prior<br />
to 1999 when I started putting all my papers on the <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/">arXiv</a>. </p>
<p>On the other hand, I do<br />
have saved most of my undergraduate courses. Most of them were still<br />
using postscript-crap like _epsfig_ etc. so I had to convert all<br />
the graphics to PDFs (merely using <a href="http://www.apple.com/macosx/features/pdf/">Preview</a> ) and<br />
modify the epsfig-command to _includegraphics_. So far, I<br />
converted all my undergraduate _differential geometry_ courses<br />
from 1998 to this year and made them available in a uniform<br />
screen-friendly viewing format at <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/toolkit/pdfdir.php?dir=%2FTheLibrary%2Fundergraduate%2F">TheLibrary/undergraduate</a>.</p>
<p>There are two<br />
ways to read the changes in these courses over the years. (1) as a shift<br />
from _differential_ geometry to more _algebraic_ geometry<br />
and (2) as a shift towards realism wrt.the level of our undegraduate<br />
students. In <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/toolkit/pdffile.php?pdf=%2FTheLibrary%2Fundergraduate%2Fdiff1998.pdf">1998</a> I was still thinking<br />
that I could teach them an easy way into Connes non-commutative standard<br />
model but didn&#8217;t go further than the Lie group sections (maybe one day<br />
I&#8217;ll rewrite this course as a graduate course when I ever get<br />
reinterested in the Connes&#8217; approach). In <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/toolkit/pdffile.php?pdf=%2FTheLibrary%2Fundergraduate%2Fdiff1999.pdf">1999</a> I had the illusion that<br />
it might be a good idea to introduce manifolds-by-examples coming from<br />
operads! In <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/toolkit/pdffile.php?pdf=%2FTheLibrary%2Fundergraduate%2Fdiff2000.pdf">2000</a> I gave in to the fact<br />
that most of the students which had to follow this course were applied<br />
mathematicians so perhaps it was a good idea to introduce them to<br />
dynamical systems (quod non!). The <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/toolkit/pdffile.php?pdf=%2FTheLibrary%2Fundergraduate%2Fdiff2001.pdf">2001</a> course is probably the<br />
most realistic one while still doing standard differential geometry. In<br />
<a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/toolkit/pdffile.php?pdf=%2FTheLibrary%2Fundergraduate%2Fdiff2002.pdf">2002</a> I used the conifold<br />
singularity and conifold transitions (deformations and blow-ups) as<br />
motivation but it was clear that the students did have difficulties with<br />
the blow-up part as they didn&#8217;t have enough experience in<br />
_algebraic_ geometry. So the <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/toolkit/pdffile.php?pdf=%2FTheLibrary%2Fundergraduate%2Fdiff2004.pdf">last two years</a> I&#8217;m giving an<br />
introduction to algebraic geometry culminating in blow-ups and some<br />
non-commutative geometry.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/nostalgia/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>GMD</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/gmd/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/gmd/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2005 19:08:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arxiv]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GMD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GTD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[non-commutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tiger]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=266</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I&#8217;m always extremely slow to pick up a trend (let alone a hype), in mathematics as well as in real life. It took me over&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m always<br />
extremely slow to pick up a trend (let alone a hype), in mathematics as<br />
well as in real life. It took me over a year to know of the existence of<br />
_blogs_ and to realize that they were a much easier way to<br />
maintain a webpage than manually modifying HTML-pages. But, eventually I<br />
sometimes get there, usually with the help of the <a href="http://www.macdevcenter.com/">mac-dev-center</a>. So, once again,<br />
I read their <a href="http://www.macdevcenter.com/pub/a/mac/2005/03/08/productivity.html
">gettings things done with your mac</a> article long after it was<br />
posted and completely unaware of the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0142000280/104-3738293-1714365">Getting Things Done</a> (or GTD) hype.  </p>
<p>At first, it just<br />
sounds as one of those boring managament-nonsense-peptalk things (and<br />
probably that is precisely what it generically is). Or what do you think<br />
about the following resume from <a href="http://www.43folders.com/2004/09/getting_started.html">Getting<br />
started with &#8216;Getting things done&#8217;</a> :</p>
<ol>
<li>identify all the<br />
stuff in your life that isnÕt in the right place (close all open<br />
loops)</li>
<li>get rid of the stuff that isnÕt yours or you donÕt<br />
need right now</li>
<li>create a right place that you trust and that<br />
supports your working style and values</li>
<li>put your stuff in the<br />
right place, consistently</li>
<li>do your stuff in a way that honors<br />
your time, your energy, and the context of any given moment</li>
<li>iterate and refactor mercilessly</li>
</ol>
<p>But in fact there is<br />
also some interesting material around at the <a href="http://www.43folders.com/">43 folders</a> website which bring this<br />
management-talk closer to home such as the <a href="http://www.43folders.com/2004/09/how_does_a_nerd.html">How does a<br />
nerd hack GTD?</a> post.</p>
<p>Also of interest are his findings after<br />
a year working with the GTD setup. These are contained in three posts :<br />
<a href="http://www.43folders.com/2004/12/a_year_of_getti.html">A Year<br />
of Getting Things Done: Part 1, The Good Stuff</a>, followed by <a href="http://www.43folders.com/2004/12/a_year_of_getti_1.html">A Year of<br />
Getting Things Done: Part 2, The Stuff I Wish I Were Better At</a> to<br />
end with <a href="http://www.43folders.com/2004/12/a_year_of_getti_2.html">A Year of<br />
Getting Things Done: Part 3, The Future of GTD?</a>. If these three<br />
postings don&#8217;t get you intrigued, nothing else will.</p>
<p>So, is<br />
there something like _GMD : Getting Mathematics Done_? Clearly, I<br />
don&#8217;t mean getting theorems proved, that&#8217;s a thing of a few seconds of<br />
inspiration and months to fill in the gaps. But, perhaps all this GTD<br />
and the software mentioned can be of some help to manage the<br />
everyday-workflow of mathematicians, such as checking the arXiv and the<br />
web, maintaining an email-, pdf- and BiBTeX-database, drafting papers,<br />
books and courses etc. </p>
<p>In the next few weeks I&#8217;ll try out some<br />
of the tricks. Probably another way to state this is the question &#8220;which<br />
Apps will survive Tiger?&#8221; Now that it is official that <a href="http://www.apple.com/macosx/overview/">Tiger</a> (that is, Mac<br />
10.4 to non-apple eaters) will be released by the end of the month it is<br />
time to rethink which of the tools I really like to keep and which is<br />
just useless garbage I picked up along the road. For example, around<br />
this time last year I had a <a href="http://www.perl.com/">Perl<br />
phase</a> and bought half a meter or so of O&#8217;Reilly Perl-books. And yes<br />
I did write a few simple scripts, some useful such as my own <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/arxiv.shtml">arXiv RSS-feeds</a>,<br />
some not so useful as a web-spider I wrote to check on changes in the<br />
list of hamepages of people working in non-commutative algebra and<br />
geometry. A year later I realize I&#8217;ll never become a <a href="http://www.perlmonks.org/">Perl Monk</a>. So from now on I want to<br />
make my computer-life as useful and easy as possible, relying on wizards<br />
to provide me with cool software to use and help me enjoy mathematics<br />
even more. I&#8217;ll keep you posted how my GMD-adventure goes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/gmd/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
