<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Douroux &#8211; neverendingbooks</title>
	<atom:link href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tag/douroux/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 14:29:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.4</generator>
	<item>
		<title>We sit in our ivory towers and think</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/we-sit-in-our-ivory-towers-and-think/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/we-sit-in-our-ivory-towers-and-think/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 14:29:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[rants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Douroux]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Grothendieck]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roberts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Woodhouse]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=8583</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I&#8217;m on vacation, and re-reading two &#8216;metabiographies&#8217;: Philippe Douroux : Alexandre Grothendieck : Sur les traces du dernier génie des mathématiques and Siobhan Roberts :&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m on vacation, and re-reading two &#8216;metabiographies&#8217;:</p>
<p>Philippe Douroux : <a ref="https://www.amazon.com/Alexandre-Grothendieck-traces-dernier-math%C3%A9matiques/dp/2370730854">Alexandre Grothendieck : Sur les traces du dernier génie des mathématiques</a></p>
<p>and</p>
<p>Siobhan Roberts : <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Genius-At-Play-Curious-Horton-ebook/dp/B00UX2UR44">Genius At Play: The Curious Mind of John Horton Conway</a></p>
<p>
<img decoding="async" src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/41o1VELFHwL._SX336_BO1,204,203,200_.jpg" width=50% align=left ><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://media.bloomsbury.com/rep/bj/9781620405956.jpg" width=50% align=right ><br />
.</p>
<p />
<p />
<p>Siobhan Roberts&#8217; book is absolutely brilliant! I&#8217;m reading it for the n-th time, first on Kindle, then hardcopy, and now I&#8217;m just flicking through its pages, whenever I want to put a smile on my face.</p>
<p>So, here&#8217;s today&#8217;s gem of a Conway quote (on page 150):</p>
<blockquote><p>Pure mathematicians usually don&#8217;t found companies and deal with the world in an aggressive way. We sit in our ivory towers and think.</p></blockquote>
<p>(Conway complains his words were taken out of context, in an article<br />
featuring Stephen Wolfram.)</p>
<p>If only university administrations worldwide would accept the &#8216;sitting in an ivory tower and think&#8217;-bit as the job description, and evaluation criterium, for their pure mathematicians.</p>
<p>Sadly&#8230; they prefer managers to thinkers.</p>
<p>This reminds me of another brilliant text, perhaps not receiving the attention it deserves:</p>
<p>Daniel J. Woodhouse : <a href="https://www.mcsweeneys.net/articles/an-open-letter-to-the-mathematical-community">An open letter to the mathematical community</a>.</p>
<p>Woodhouse offers a reaction to the &#8216;neoliberal upper management and bloated administration&#8217; of universities:</p>
<blockquote><p>Within the sphere of pure mathematics — the oldest and most successful of humanity’s intellectual endeavors — I believe our best chance at preserving the integrity and dignity of our tradition is to return to our Pythagorean roots. <strong>We should become a cult.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p>How?</p>
<blockquote><p>
Let us seclude ourselves in mountain caves and daub mysterious equations in blood across rock-faces to ward off outsiders. Let us embrace our most impenetrable mathematical texts as sacred and requiring divinely distributed revelation.
</p></blockquote>
<p>Why?</p>
<blockquote><p>I am convinced that the current system has dulled our understanding of the value we offer through our instruction. Modern mathematical techniques are the foundation of modern science, medicine, and technology, and we should be the literal, rather than metaphorical, high priests of this temple. Only by withholding our insights will we be able to reassert the intrinsic worth of our knowledge.</p></blockquote>
<p>I hope these few paragraphs have wetted your appetite to read the manifesto in full, and then take action!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/we-sit-in-our-ivory-towers-and-think/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Grothendieck&#8217;s gribouillis (4)</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/grothendiecks-gribouillis-4/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/grothendiecks-gribouillis-4/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 07:30:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[france]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[BNP]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Douroux]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gillot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Grothendieck]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=8388</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Fortunately, there are a few certainties left in life: In spring, you might expect the next instalment of Connes&#8217; and Consani&#8217;s quest for Gabriel&#8217;s topos.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Fortunately, there are a few certainties left in life:</p>
<p>In spring, you might expect the next instalment of Connes&#8217; and Consani&#8217;s quest for <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/archangel-gabriel-will-make-you-a-topos">Gabriel&#8217;s topos</a>. Here&#8217;s the latest: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.03310">$\overline{\mathbf{Spec}(\mathbb{Z})}$ and the Gromov norm</a>.</p>
<p>Every half year or so, Mochizuki&#8217;s circle-of-friends tries to create some buzz announcing the next IUTeich-workshop. I&#8217;ll spare you the link, if you are still interested, follow <a href="https://twitter.com/math_jin">math_jin</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/iutabc_bot">IUTT_bot_math_jin</a> on Twitter.</p>
<p>And then, there&#8217;s the never-ending story of <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/?s=gribouillis">Grothendieck&#8217;s griboullis</a>, kept alive by the French journalist and author Philippe Douroux.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" width=100% src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/GrothGrib1.jpg"></p>
<p>Here are some recent links:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.lemonde.fr/sciences/article/2019/05/06/alexandre-grothendieck-une-mathematique-en-cathedrale-gothique_5459035_1650684.html">Alexandre Grothendieck : une mathématique en cathédrale gothique</a>, an article (in French) by Philippe Douroux in Le Monde, May 6th (behind paywall).</p>
<p><a href="https://www.franceinter.fr/emissions/l-edito-carre/l-edito-carre-15-mai-2019">L’histoire étonnante des archives du mathématicien Alexandre Grothendieck</a>, an article (in French) on France Inter by Mathieu Vidar, based on info from Philippe Douroux.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.franceinter.fr/emissions/la-tete-au-carre/la-tete-au-carre-10-juin-2019">Les archives mystérieuses de Alexandre Grothendieck</a>, a podcast of a broadcast on France Inter on June 10th. Interesting interview (in French) with Philippe Douroux and the French mathematician <a href="http://perso.ens-lyon.fr/ghys/home/">Etienne Ghys</a> (with a guest appearance by Luc Illusie).</p>
<p><a href="https://elpais.com/elpais/2019/05/11/album/1557598548_352132.html?id_externo_rsoc=FB_CM#foto_gal_2">El enigmático legado de un genio de las matemáticas</a>, an article (in Spanish) in El Pais, May 13th, with 8 photos of some of the Gribouillis. The two pictures in this post are taken from this article.</p>
<p>So, what&#8217;s the latest on the 70.000+ pages left by Grothendieck?</p>
<p>As far as i know, the Mormoiron part of the gribouillis is still at the University of Montpellier, and has been made available online at the <a href="https://grothendieck.umontpellier.fr/archives-grothendieck/">Grothendieck archives</a>.</p>
<p>The Lasserre part of the gribouillis is still in a cellar in Paris&#8217; Saint-Germain-des-Prés, belonging to <a href="http://www.alainbrieux.com/">Jean-Bernard Gillot</a>. The French national library cannot take possession of the notes before a financial agreement is reached with Grothendieck&#8217;s children (French law does not allow children to be disinherited).</p>
<p>And there&#8217;s a dispute about the price to be paid. The notes were estimated at 45.000 Euros, but some prefer to believe that they may be worth several millions of dollars.</p>
<p>It all depends on their mathematical content.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, pictures claimed to be of the Lasserre notes (such as the one above) are in fact from the Mormoiron/Montpellier notes, which do indeed contain interesting mathematics.</p>
<p>But, it is very unlikely that the Lasserre notes contain (math) surprises. Probably, most of them look like this one</p>
<p><img decoding="async" width=100% src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/GrothGrib2.jpg"></p>
<p>endless lists of people deported by the Nazis to extermination camps in WW2.</p>
<p>Or, as Philippe Douroux is quoted in the El Pais piece: &#8220;I think it&#8217;s a treasure, maybe not a mathematical one, but a human one. It&#8217;s a descent into the hell of one the best organised brains in the world.&#8221;</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/GrothFilm"><br />
</center></p>
<p>The film made by Catherine Aira and Yves Le Pestipon &#8220;Alexandre Grothendieck: On the Paths of a Genius&#8221; (on the quest for G&#8217;s last hideout in the French Pyrenees) can now be watched on YouTube (with English subtitles)</p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zJnboQ_5-8c" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/grothendiecks-gribouillis-4/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
