<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Wolfe &#8211; neverendingbooks</title>
	<atom:link href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tag/wolfe/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 09:59:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>a SNORTgo endgame</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/a-snortgo-endgame/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/a-snortgo-endgame/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 09:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[games]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Col]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Norton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Siegel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Snort]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wolfe]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=7603</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[SNORT, invented by Simon NORTon is a map-coloring game, similar to COL. Only, this time, neighbours may not be coloured differently. SNORTgo, similar to COLgo,&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Col_(game)#Snort">SNORT</a>, invented by Simon NORTon is a map-coloring game, similar to COL. Only, this time, neighbours may not be coloured differently.</p>
<p>SNORTgo, similar to <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/a-colgo-endgame">COLgo</a>, is SNORT played with go-stones on a go-board. That is, adjacent stones must have the same colour.</p>
<p>SNORT is a &#8216;hot&#8217; game, meaning that each player is eager to move as most moves will improve your position. In COL players are reluctant to move, because a move limits your next moves.</p>
<p>For this reason, SNORT positions are much harder to evaluate, and one needs the full force of Conways&#8217;s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On_Numbers_and_Games">ONAG</a>.</p>
<p>Here&#8217;s a SNORTgo endgame. <strong>Who has a winning strategy?</strong>, and what is the first move in that strategy?</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/SnortGo1.png" width=100% ></p>
<p>The method to approach such an endgame is similar to that in <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/a-colgo-endgame">COLgo</a>. First we remove all dead spots from the board.</p>
<p>What remains, are a 4 spots available only to Right (white) and 5 spots available only to Left (bLack). Further, there a 3 &#8216;live&#8217; regions: the upper righthand corner and the two lower corners.</p>
<p>The value of these corners must be computed inductively.</p>
<p>Here&#8217;s the answer:</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/SnortGo3.png" width=100%></p>
<p>For example, Right&#8217;s best option in the left-most game (corresponding to the upper righthand corner of the endgame) is to put his stone on N12, resulting in a game in which neither player can move (the zero game).</p>
<p>On the other hand, Left can put a stone at either N11, N12 or N13 leaving a game in which she has two more moves, whereas Right han none (the $2$ game).</p>
<p>The other positions are computed similarly.</p>
<p>To get the value of the endgame we have to sum up all these values.</p>
<p>This can either be done using the addition rule given in ONAG, or by using programs in combinatorial game theory.</p>
<p>There&#8217;s <a href"http://cgsuite.sourceforge.net/">Combinatorial Game Suite</a>, developed by Aaron Siegel. But, for some reason I can no longer use it on macOS High Sierra.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the older program <a href="http://homepages.gac.edu/~wolfe/games/">David Wolfe&#8217;s toolkit</a> is still available, and runs on my MacBook.</p>
<p>The sum game evaluates to $\{ \{3|2 \}|-1 \}$, which is a &#8216;fuzzy&#8217; game, that is, its value is confused with $0$.</p>
<p>This means that the first player to move has a winning strategy in the endgame.</p>
<p>Can you spot the (unique) winning move for Right (white) and one (of two) winning move for Left (bLack)?</p>
<p><strong>Spoiler alert</strong> : solution in the comments.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/a-snortgo-endgame/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
