<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Lavisse &#8211; neverendingbooks</title>
	<atom:link href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tag/lavisse/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2023 13:00:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Weil photos used in Dema-lore</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/weil-photos-used-in-dema-lore/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/weil-photos-used-in-dema-lore/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2023 13:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[france]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tBC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dema]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dema-lore]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lavisse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[photos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tbc]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Trench]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[TwentyOnePilots]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[used]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Weil]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=11484</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On April 20th of 2018, twenty one pilots updated their store page to include a video with a hidden message at the end of it.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On April 20th of 2018, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twenty_One_Pilots">twenty one pilots</a> updated their store page to include a video with a hidden message at the end of it.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://images.genius.com/81b0c7216340b50cb464ca8b7db7ea71.811x401x1.png" width=100%></p>
<p>and with a bit of sleuthing it led to <a href="https://www.dmaorg.site/original/found/15398642_14/clancy.html">a page on the dmaorg.info site</a> containing:</p>
<ul>
<li>a <a href="https://www.dmaorg.site/original/found/15398642_14/img/6629097cc6e3/_ti_su_p.png">map of the City of Dema</a></li>
<li>a picture of <a href="https://www.dmaorg.site/original/found/15398642_14/img/61066cd46530/unnamed-(1).jpg">21 vultures</a> sitting on the rim of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower_of_Silence">tower of silence</a></li>
<li>a <a href="https://www.dmaorg.site/original/found/15398642_14/img/c72347067926/ba_dge.jpg">&#8216;failed perimeter escape&#8217; message</a></li>
<li>the first <a href="https://www.dmaorg.site/original/found/15398642_14/img/ff1e640a042d/cla_ncy-988-06MOON_18_-1.jpg">letter of someone named Clancy</a>, a citizen of Dema, starting with &#8220;The perplexities of the Dema horizon didn&#8217;t occur to me until my ninth year.&#8221;</li>
<li>the <a href="https://www.dmaorg.site/original/found/15398642_14/img/b5c55b910823/se__elf.jpg">blurred photo</a> on the left below:</li>
</ul>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/Se_elf.jpg" width=55%> <img decoding="async" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/af/Weil.jpg" width=40%><br />
</center></p>
<p>This was immediately identified as part of the photo on the right, which is on the <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andr%C3%A9_Weil">French Wikipedia page for Andre Weil</a>.</p>
<p>The photo is clipped in such a way one cannot be certain whether the child is a boy or girl, so a logical explanation is that this is supposed to be the nine year old Clancy, shielding his eyes from the violence (vialism) he just discovered in Dema.</p>
<p>The full picture suggests that Clancy&#8217;s struggles might mirror some in Andre Weil&#8217;s life.</p>
<p><a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andr%C3%A9_Weil">Andre Weil</a> was born May 6th, 1906, so &#8216;in his ninth year&#8217; World War 1 breaks out in 1914.</p>
<p><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/wheres-bourbakis-dema">Last time</a> we&#8217;ve seen that Bourbaki&#8217;s Dema = Ecole Normal Superieure in Paris during WW1, Vialism = militant patriotism sending ENS-graduates as trained reserve second lieutenants in the infantry to the trenches, and there getting killed &#8216;pour la patrie&#8217; and the glory of the ENS and its director <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernest_Lavisse">Ernest Lavisse</a>, &#8220;L&#8217;instituteur national&#8221;.</p>
<p>Here&#8217;s a G-translation of his letter to the young French, published September 23rd 1914:</p>
<blockquote><p>
Dear children of France, You will be old one day, and, like the old, you will like to remember times past. There will come evenings when your little children, seeing you dreaming, will say to you: Tell us, grandfather. And you will tell. It will be a few episodes of the war, a long march, an alert, a bayonet assault, a cavalry charge, the feat of a battery of 75, the strewn enemy dead on the plain, or else, in the streets of a city, the serried ranks of corpses left standing for lack of room to fall; and then the death of comrades, the terrible losses of your company and your regiment, your wounds received in Belgium, in Champagne, on the banks of the Rhine, beyond the Rhine; but the joy of victories, the poles knocked down on too narrow frontiers, triumphal entries.</p>
<p>On those evenings, after the amazed children have gone to sleep, you will open a drawer where you will have collected precious objects, a bullet extracted from a wound, a piece of shell, a cloth where your blood will have turned pale, a cross of honour, I hope, or a military medal, at the very least a medal from the 1914 war, on the ribbon of which the silver clasps will bear the names of immortal battles. And whatever your life, happy or unhappy, you will be able to say: I lived great days such as the history of men had not yet seen. And you will be right to be proud of your youth, because you are sublime young people!</p>
<p>I have read your letters; I have spoken with the wounded. Through you, I know what heroism is. I had heard a lot about it, being a historian by profession, but now I see it, I touch it, and how beautiful your heroism is, embellished with grace and smiling in the French way! Young soldiers if you were given one chevron per battle, your march would not be enough to accommodate them, because at the end of the war you would count more chevrons than years;</p>
<p>Young soldiers you are glorious old warriors.</p>
<p>Oh! Thanks thanks! Thank you for the beautiful end of life that you give to the elderly who, for forty-four years have suffered so much from the abasement of the fatherland.
</p></blockquote>
<p>The 44 years refers to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franco-Prussian_War">Franco-Prussian war of 1870</a> in which Bourbaki (the general) played a dramatic role.</p>
<p>The next cycle of militant patriotism occurred in the years leading up to the second world war. Here, Andre Weil&#8217;s experiences mirror those of Clancy. He tried several times to escape, first from military action (although he too was a reserve officer in the French army), then from France itself. He was captured in Finland, brought back to France to face trial and imprisonment, was released on the condition that he did active military duty, escaped with the French army to England, there demobilised he refused to join de Gaulle&#8217;s troops, left England on a boat to Marseille, from where he escaped to the US.</p>
<p>All this, and much more, you can read in his autobiography <a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-3-0348-8634-5">The Apprenticeship of a Mathematician</a>, especially Chapter VI, The War and I: A Comic Opera in Six Acts.</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/61dIRQ8r3YL._AC_UF1000,1000_QL80_.jpg" width=70%><br />
</center></p>
<p>(for TØP-ers, note the Bishop-red cover&#8230;)</p>
<p>Comic or not, the book tries to &#8216;explain&#8217; his actions in those years, but failed to convince the French from offering him a professorship at a French university after the war.</p>
<p>Perhaps it may be worth looking into a comparison between Weil&#8217;s autobiography and the collected <a href="https://genius.com/Twenty-one-pilots-dmaorginfo-transcriptions-annotated">Clancy letters</a>.</p>
<p>I guess that&#8217;s the best I can do to explain the use of that Weil photo by TØP. Surely they didn&#8217;t search any deeper as to where and when this picture was taken, or who the girl was next to Weil.</p>
<p>In case anyone might be interested, I&#8217;ll be happy to explain my own theory about this in another post.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m sure the full photograph ended up in the &#8216;Trench-bible&#8217;, given to the director of their clip-movies. The scenery is used at the end of the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UOUBW8bkjQ4&#038;t=282s">Jumpsuit video</a> when &#8216;Clancy&#8217; takes out a jumpsuit from the burning car and walks away along a road very similar to that in the photo.</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/WeilRoad.jpg" width=70%><br />
</center></p>
<p>The boy/girl shielding his/her eyes for the violence, should have been used at about minute one into the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eNcvblM8-_o&#038;t=55s">Outside video</a></p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/WeilShieldinEyes.jpg" width=70%><br />
</center></p>
<p>Now, there&#8217;s another Weil (or rather Bourbaki) photograph <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-bishops-or-banditos">we know did inspire Twenty One Pilots</a>, the classic picture at the Dieulefit/Beauvallon 1938 Bourbaki-congress</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/af/Bourbaki_congress1938.png/440px-Bourbaki_congress1938.png" width=70%><br />
</center></p>
<p>which was photoshopped in order to get Szolem Mandelbrojt in from the Chancay (quite similar to Clancy now that i type this) 1937 Bourbaki congress</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA2/chancay2.jpg" width=70%><br />
</center></p>
<p>Now, these were the only two Bourbaki-meetings <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simone_Weil">Simone Weil</a> (Andre&#8217;s sister) attended, and she features prominently in both pictures.</p>
<p>Probably this brother/sister thing struct a chord with Twenty One Pilots. But then, you quickly end up with this iconic picture of both of them, taken in the summer of 1922, just before Andre entered the Ecole Normale (he entered the ENS at age 16&#8230;)</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/DU4BfakW4AE-JdO.jpg" width=70%><br />
</center></p>
<p>I&#8217;d love to be send a copy of the &#8216;Trench bible&#8217; because I&#8217;m fairly certain also this photograph is in it. At the end of the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hMAPyGoqQVw&#038;t=234s">Nico and the niners-video</a> you see this boy and girl (who may be around age 9 and discover the truth about Dema)  finding a jumpsuit with the Bishops approaching</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/SimoneAndreWeil.jpg" width=70%><br />
</center></p>
<p>and they reappear a bit older at the end of the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eNcvblM8-_o&#038;t=389s">Outside-video</a>, with a burning Dema in the background.</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/SimoneAndreWeil2.jpg" width=70%><br />
</center></p>
<p><strong>In this series:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-and-top-east-is-up">Bourbaki and TØP : East is up</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-bishops-or-banditos">Bourbaki = Bishops or Banditos?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/wheres-bourbakis-dema">Where’s Bourbaki’s Dema?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/weil-photos-used-in-dema-lore">Weil photos used in Dema-lore</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/dema2trench-and-repeat">Dema2Trench, AND REpeat</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/top-photoshop-mysteries">TØP PhotoShop mysteries</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/9-bourbaki-founding-members-really">9 Bourbaki founding members, really?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-and-dema-two-remarks">Bourbaki and Dema, two remarks</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/clancy-and-nancago">Clancy and Nancago</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/weil-photos-used-in-dema-lore/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Where&#8217;s Bourbaki&#8217;s Dema?</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/wheres-bourbakis-dema/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/wheres-bourbakis-dema/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2023 15:17:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tBC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bourbaki]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bourbaki’s]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dema]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lavisse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tbc]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tØp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[where’s]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=11443</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In this series I&#8217;m trying to figure out why the Bourbaki-group was an inspiration for the storyline of Trench, the fifth studio album by American&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this series I&#8217;m trying to figure out why the Bourbaki-group was an inspiration for the storyline of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trench_(album)">Trench</a>, the fifth studio album by American musical duo <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twenty_One_Pilots">Twenty One Pilots</a> (or TØP).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://topmasterdoc.carrd.co/assets/images/image21.jpg?v=c02a4a30" width=100% ></p>
<p>Trench-lore centers around the city of Dema, ruled by nine Bishops enforcing Vialism (a fake religion asking people to take their own lives to glorify Dema).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://topmasterdoc.carrd.co/assets/images/image22.jpg?v=c02a4a30" width=100% ></p>
<p>It is an unfortunate coincidence that the city of Dema in the movie-clip of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hMAPyGoqQVw">Nico and the Niners</a> was inspired, and shot in Kyiv and Charkiv, Ukraine (the clip is from 2018).</p>
<blockquote class="reddit-embed-bq" style="height:500px" data-embed-height="500"><p>      <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/twentyonepilots/comments/9279qo/ive_just_found_out_that_dema_is_situated_in_my/">I&#8217;ve just found out that Dema is situated in my country&#8230; (NATN was made in Kyiv and Charkiv, Ukraine)</a><br /> by      <a href="https://www.reddit.com/user/Sasha0503">u/Sasha0503</a> in      <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/twentyonepilots/">twentyonepilots</a>    </p></blockquote>
<p><script async="" src="https://embed.reddit.com/widgets.js" charset="UTF-8"></script></p>
<p>Here&#8217;s the corresponding &#8216;beyond the movie&#8217;-clip, from which we learn (or rather are told) that the movie&#8217;s &#8216;city of Dema&#8217; was shot in &#8216;the former Ukranian high-school&#8217; of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josh_Dun">Josh Dun</a> (he even calls it his &#8216;Alma Mater&#8217;), all in quotes because I don&#8217;t buy any of it, but take it as a desperate hint to identify Dema.</p>
<p>In the Trench movie-clips, Josh Dun is always cast as a Bandito, and last time we saw that also the Bourbaki-gang is likely to be close to the Banditos. Dema is supposed to be the Alma Mater of (at least some of) the Banditos. Hold that thought.</p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/teIy4u1pqgs" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>As for the connection between the City of Dema and the Bourbaki-group, we only have one piece of solid information:</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/DemaBeforeBourbaki.jpg" width=100%></p>
<p>That the Bourbaki-group named themselves after Nico=Nicolas Bourbaki clearly resonates with Twenty Øne Pilots who got their name from the 1947 play <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_My_Sons">&#8216;All My Sons&#8217;</a> by American playwright Arthur Miller.</p>
<p>But the crucial info is: &#8220;The story of Dema happened before them&#8221;, so the story of Dema with the Bishops and Vialism happened before the Bourbaki-group. An extra piece of evidence that there is no way the Bourbaki-group are the nine Bishops of Dema.</p>
<p>So, what happened before the Bourbaki-group?</p>
<p>Mathematically, their direct predecessors were David Hilbert, Emil Artin, Emmy Noether and her boys, in short German mathematicians from the 1920&#8217;s and early 1930&#8217;s.</p>
<p>Several of the Bourbaki founding members studied in Germany (Weil in Gottingen in 1927, Chevalley in Hamburg in 1931 and Marburg in 1932, and Ehresmann in Gottingen in 1930).</p>
<p>They were inspired by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilbert%27s_program">Hilbert&#8217;s program</a> (<a href="https://plus.maths.org/content/we-must-know-we-will-know">We must know, we will know</a>), and set out to introduce the German style of writing and doing mathematics in France.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://mhedsson.files.wordpress.com/2018/03/group5869200031456766156.jpg" width=100%></p>
<p>So, a first candidate (also given the <a href="https://www.thespruce.com/what-is-bauhaus-architecture-4784133">Bauhaus-like architecture</a> of Dema) might be &#8216;German Mathematicians&#8217;, or in German, DEutscher MAthematiker = DEMA.</p>
<p>But one can hardly argue that there was a self-destructive attitude (like Vialism) present among that group, quite the opposite.</p>
<p>Still, one can ask why German mathematics was that strong in the 1920&#8217;s, compared to the French. France and Germany took different approaches with their intelligentsia during WW1: while Germany protected its young students and scientists, France instead committed them to the front, owing to the French culture of egalitarianism.</p>
<p>Remember that the album is called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trench_(album)">Trench</a>, and the dirtiest <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trench_warfare">trench-war</a> in all of human history was WW1. Hold that thought.</p>
<p>But, how does this help us in identifying Dema.</p>
<p>A few months before the release of Trench, a website was launched containing letters (from a character named Clancy) and some photos (including part of a photo of Andre Weil). That website&#8217;s URL still is <a href="http://dmaorg.info/">dmaorg.info</a>.</p>
<p>On the rear of the boat in the movie-clip <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FiXVRdotCEk">Saturday</a>, we see &#8216;030904 DMA ORG&#8217; (the 030904 is simplistic code for CID, believed to mean &#8216;Clancy Is Dead&#8217;).</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://preview.redd.it/rk4di7wol0a71.jpg?auto=webp&#038;s=38e6c5b1aee8daa2495b8b1f0547aa0efc1c03e2" width=100%></p>
<p>Compare this to the official email address of the <a href="https://www.bourbaki.fr/">&#8216;Association des collaborateurs de Nicolas Bourbaki&#8217;</a> which is: <strong>bourbaki@dma.ens.fr</strong>.</p>
<p>Here, &#8216;dma&#8217; stands for <a href="https://www.math.ens.psl.eu/en/welcome/">&#8216;Département de mathématiques et applications&#8217;</a>, one of the fifteen departments of the ENS, the <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%89cole_normale_sup%C3%A9rieure_(Paris)">Ecole Normal Superieure</a> in Paris, Rue d&#8217;Ulm.</p>
<p><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-bishops-or-banditos">Remember</a> the inspirational, photoshopped photo of the Bourbaki 1938 congress in Dieulefit/Deauvallon:</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/af/Bourbaki_congress1938.png/440px-Bourbaki_congress1938.png" width=45%> <img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/BeauvallonTop.png" width=45%><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/BeavallonDesktop.png" width=45%><br />
</center></p>
<p>All seven people in the original picture are &#8216;normaliens&#8217;, that is, their &#8216;Alma Mater&#8217; is the Ecole Normale Superieure&#8217;. All but Simone Weil graduated from the DEpartement de MAthematiques=DEMA, as DMA was called then.</p>
<p>Whence the hypothesis: <strong>Bourbaki&#8217;s Dema = ENS before and during WW1</strong></p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/bc/Cour_aux_Ernests_sous_la_neige.jpg/1280px-Cour_aux_Ernests_sous_la_neige.jpg" width=100%></p>
<p>It is a conglomerate of buildings and its central courtyard forms a kind of secular cloister around its basin. This space is called &#8220;la Cour aux Ernests&#8221; in reference to a former director, Ernest Bersot. He had placed red (!) fish (=the Ernests in ENS-slang) in the basin, which have become one of the symbols of the school.</p>
<p>More important to us is that the pond of the Ernests is reached by crossing the &#8220;aquarium&#8221;, where the ENS war memorial is located, commemorating the 239 (former) ENS-students killed in WW1 on a tatal of about 1400 of them drafted&#8230;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://2.bp.blogspot.com/--qFBZ0RWTo8/U4hVu8B-5AI/AAAAAAAAcf0/LfkMNvv6fXA/s1600/2+(Custom)+(Large).JPG" width=100%></p>
<p>From the Wikipedia-page on Nicolas Bourbaki:</p>
<p>&#8220;The deaths of ENS students resulted in a lost generation in the French mathematical community; the estimated proportion of ENS mathematics students (and French students generally) who died in the war ranges from one-quarter to one-half, depending on the intervals of time (c. 1900–1918, especially 1910–1916) and populations considered.&#8221;</p>
<p>A chilling, and very detailed account of the circumstances that lead to the deaths of about 50% of ENS-student from the period 1910-1913 can be found in the paper <a href="https://www.cairn.info/revue-pole-sud-2012-1-page-9.htm">Pourquoi les normaliens sont-ils morts en masse en 1914-1918 ? Une explication structurale</a> (Why the normaliens suffered mass-death in 1914-18, a structural explanation) by <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolas_Mariot">Nicolas (!) Mariot</a>. Here&#8217;s the abstract:</p>
<p>&#8220;The École Normale Supérieure d’Ulm is always mentioned when historians summarize the ravages of World War I in France: the institution embodies the commitment of intellectuals at the front. The article offers an interpretation of mortality rates of the School which allows to understand why it is primarily students during schooling (Classes 1910-1913) that are heavily affected. Rather than basing the interpretation on the single assumption of sacrifice, it puts forward arguments pertaining to the history of the school in the immediate pre-war, including the institution of military training after the reform service in 1905, competition with the École Polytechnique to retain the best scientific students, and finally the forced commitment of the ENS students in the infantry.&#8221;</p>
<p>Crucial in this is the role of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernest_Lavisse">Ernest Lavisse</a> who was the director of the ENS from 1903 till 1919.</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/1/19/Ernest_Lavisse%2C_1913.jpg/520px-Ernest_Lavisse%2C_1913.jpg" width=50%><br />
</center></p>
<p>Before, normaliens had to serve 12 months in the army, just like all other students. In 1905 the law changed, and under Lavisse&#8217;s influence ENS-students were given a heavy military training. From the paper:</p>
<p>&#8220;From now on, normalien students, like those of other major military schools, are subject to a two-year service: a first year before their actual entry into rue d&#8217;Ulm, which they had to perform in an infantry regiment; a second on leaving, which they can finish as a reserve second lieutenant, but always in the infantry, if they pass the tests. And there is more: because between these two years, the students also follow a fairly heavy military preparation, including theoretical and physical exercises, even on Sundays, organised by two officers seconded full-time for this mission within the walls of the School.&#8221;</p>
<p>He also instilled in the ENS-student a radical sense of patriotism, and was a fervent propagandist for <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Union_sacr%C3%A9e_(mouvement)">l&#8217;Union sacrée</a>. From the paper:</p>
<p>&#8220;Intellectual mobilisation crystallised in the figures of Lavisse and <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%89mile_Durkheim">Durkheim</a> via their famous Letters to all French people distributed in millions of copies across the country. In the fall of 1914, the two founded and took control, respectively as director and secretary of the Committee for Studies and Documents on the War, a propaganda organ for the country&#8217;s executives.</p>
<p>Alongside them, eight of the nine other members of the Committee are former students of the School who have become professors at the Sorbonne (<a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Andler">Charles Andler</a>, <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Seignobos">Charles Seignobos</a>, <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%89mile_Boutroux">Émile Boutroux</a>, <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernest_Denis">Ernest Denis</a>, <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gustave_Lanson">Gustave Lanson</a>) or at the Collège de France (<a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_B%C3%A9dier">Joseph Bédier</a>, <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henri_Bergson">Henri Bergson</a>, <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacques_Hadamard">Jacques Hadamard</a>), without even mentioning the role of editorial secretary held by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucien_Herr">Lucien Herr</a>, legendary counterpart of <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Dupuy_(ENS)">Paul Dupuy</a> at the Rue d&#8217;Ulm library.&#8221;</p>
<p>I would have liked that there were only nine members of the committee, but there were eleven of them&#8230;</p>
<p>Anyway, Lavisse and his eight professors created an extremely patriotic environment at the ENS during WW1, encouraging students to go to (the) Trench(es) and give their life for France and the glory of the Ecole. The ENS-monument is the equivalent of the Neon Gravestones in Dema-lore.</p>
<p>Did you spot it too? LAVIsse is almost a perfect anagram for VIALism.</p>
<p><a href="https://fr.wiktionary.org/wiki/se_non_%C3%A8_vero_%C3%A8_bene_trovato">Se non e vero&#8230;</a></p>
<p>Concluding, the best theory I can come up with in order to include the Bourbaki-group in Dema-lore is that their Dema is the ENS in WW1 and preceding years, and that Vialism is the regime installed by Lavisse and the other members from the committee.</p>
<p><strong>In this series:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-and-top-east-is-up">Bourbaki and TØP : East is up</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-bishops-or-banditos">Bourbaki = Bishops or Banditos?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/wheres-bourbakis-dema">Where’s Bourbaki’s Dema?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/weil-photos-used-in-dema-lore">Weil photos used in Dema-lore</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/dema2trench-and-repeat">Dema2Trench, AND REpeat</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/top-photoshop-mysteries">TØP PhotoShop mysteries</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/9-bourbaki-founding-members-really">9 Bourbaki founding members, really?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-and-dema-two-remarks">Bourbaki and Dema, two remarks</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/clancy-and-nancago">Clancy and Nancago</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/wheres-bourbakis-dema/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
