<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>warwalking &#8211; neverendingbooks</title>
	<atom:link href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tag/warwalking/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2008 20:14:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>iTouch as network sniffer</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/itouch-as-network-sniffer/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/itouch-as-network-sniffer/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2008 20:14:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[itouch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jailbreak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Leopard]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[warwalking]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/index.php/itouch-as-network-sniffer.html</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the iTouch warwalking post I was considering trying to gain access to closed networks for innocent purposes such as checking mail, rather than stealing&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/itouch-warwalking.html">iTouch warwalking post</a> I was considering trying to gain access to closed networks for innocent purposes such as checking mail, rather than stealing secret passwords from people allowing you free access to their wireless network, but still, I should have thought of the following possibility</p>
<p><object width="425" height="355"><param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/1koHEpoHL_g&#038;rel=1"></param><param name="wmode" value="transparent"></param><embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/1koHEpoHL_g&#038;rel=1" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" wmode="transparent" width="425" height="355"></embed></object></p>
<p>Here&#8217;s a walk-through :</p>
<ul>
<li>type the following command into your iTouch Terminal.app (assuming you&#8217;ve installed the BSD subsystem) :</li>
</ul>
<p class="alert">tcpdump -v -s 65535 -w log.txt</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>once you&#8217;ve collected enough packets, cancel the command (ctrl c), <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/first-things-first-jailbreak.html">AFPd</a> the file from the iTouch to your Mac and open it with <a href="http://www.finkconsulting.com/page7.php">Wireshark</a> (this is the most convenient way to install binaries under Leopard as well as an updated version of X11. For other platforms, or source code, <a href="http://www.wireshark.org/download.html">see here</a>)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>do whatever black magic you feel you have to perform using Wireshark (the new name for <a href="http://www.ethereal.com/">Ethereal</a>) or <a href="http://sectools.org/crackers.html">other password crackers</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/itouch-as-network-sniffer/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>iTouch warwalking</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/itouch-warwalking/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/itouch-warwalking/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2008 12:50:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[google]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[itouch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[OSX]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[warwalking]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=333</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Four years ago I had a brief fling with wardriving. It went only as far as getting Ethereal to crack the security of our house-network.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/itouchwar.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;" > Four years ago I had a brief fling with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wardriving">wardriving</a>. It went only as far as getting <a href="http://www.ethereal.com/">Ethereal</a> to crack the security of our house-network. I simply couldn&#8217;t picture myself walking around the neighborhood with my laptop under my arm&#8230; However, jogging around with an iPod will attract far  less attention.</p>
<p>Starting an iTouch in a network-rich environment you will be asked which network you want to connect to (see for example <a href="http://revver.com/video/416762/ipod-touch-wifi-network-drive-around/">this wardriving video</a>). However, if you need more information on the networks, there is a port of the OSX-tool <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IStumbler">iStumbler</a> for the iPhone/iTouch : <a href="http://code.google.com/p/iphone-wireless/">Stumbler</a> (available also from the Install.app under Network). This morning I flipped open my iTouch in a generic street near the University and was surrounded by 12 wireless networks, 6 of them wide open&#8230;</p>
<p>One may then ask : what about less innocent wardriving tools such as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kismet_%28software%29">Kismet</a> or Ethereal itself? The problem with porting those seems to be that no-one knows whether the iTouch wireless driver can be put into &#8216;promiscuous mode&#8217; (see for example <a href="http://www.hackint0sh.org/forum/showthread.php?t=9700">this thread</a>).</p>
<p>Once you have collected open networks at your favourite places or have passwords to closed networks, it would be nice if the iTouch would auto-detect these and connect to them without you having to remember the particular name or having to type in username/password combinations. Surprisingly, this is possible thanks to the people at <a href="http://devicescape.com/pub/">devicescape.com</a>. Create a free login, then get <strong>Devicescape Connect</strong> (available under Network) run it and write down the pincode you are given and follow the instructions to complete the installation. You can then edit your Wi-Fi list of desired hotspot or personal networks, together with all login-data. There is a nice <a href="http://db.tidbits.com/article/9182">TidBit article</a> describing devicescape in full detail.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/itouch-warwalking/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>the iTunes hack</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/the-itunes-hack/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/the-itunes-hack/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2004 15:19:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[warwalking]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=119</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If you are interested in getting thousands of mp3-files on your computer using only 128 Kb of ROM, read on! Yesterday I made my hands&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/imacs.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;" />   If you<br />
are interested in getting thousands of <i>mp3-files</i> on your computer<br />
using only 128 Kb of ROM, read on! Yesterday I made my hands dirty and<br />
with Jan&#8217;s help upgraded two <i></i> 6 Gb colored iMacs (a blue and a<br />
pink one) to potential servers for our home-network having a 80 Gb resp.<br />
a 120 Gb hard disk. If you do the installation yourself such an upgrade<br />
costs you roughly 1 Euro/Gigabyte which seems to me like a good<br />
investment. Clearly, you need to know how to do this and be less<br />
hardware-phobic than I am. Fortunately, the first problem is easily<br />
solved. There is plenty of good advice on the net : for the colored<br />
iMacs we used the <a href="http://www.macworld.com/2001/10/bc/howtoimac/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">upgrade an iMac</a>-page of MacWorld. For possible<br />
later use, there is also a page for replacing the hard disk in an <a href="http://caslis.com/mac/ibook/ibdrive.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">old iBook</a><br />
(which seems already more challenging) and in a <a href="http://www.xlr8yourmac.com/systems/iMac_g4/imacg4_takeapart.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">flat screen iMac</a> (which seems to be impossible<br />
without proper tools). Anyway, we followed the page and in no time<br />
replaced the hard disks (along the way we made all possible mistakes<br />
like not connecting the new hard disk and then being surprised that the<br />
Disk Utility cannot find it or not putting back the RAM-chips and<br />
panicking when the normal start-up chime was replaced by an aggressive<br />
beep). An unexpected pleasant surprise was that the blue iMac, which I<br />
thought to be dead, revived when we replaced the hard disk.</p>
<p> Back home, I dumped a good part of our CD-collection on the blue<br />
iMac (1440 songs, good for 4.3 days of music and taking up 7.11 Gb of<br />
the vast 120 Gb hard disk) to test the <b>iTunes Central hack</b><br />
explained by Alan Graham in his <a href="http://www.macdevcenter.com/lpt/a/3192" target="_blank" rel="noopener">six<br />
great tips for homemade dot mac servers</a>. Would I manage to get the<br />
entire collection on my old iBook which had only (after installing all<br />
this <i>WarWalking-software</i>) 800 Mb of free disk space? Here is what<br />
I did :</p>
<p> 1. On the iBook (or any machine you want to<br />
play this trick on) go to your <i>Home/Music/iTunes</i>-folder and drag<br />
the two files and one directory it contains to the <i>Trash</i>. Do the<br />
same for the two files <i>com.apple.iTunes.eq.plist</i> and<br />
<i>com.apple.iTunes.plist</i> which are in the<br />
<i>Home/Library/Preferences</i>-folder.</p>
<p> 2. On the<br />
iBook, use the <i>Finder/Network</i>-icon to connect to the server<br />
(iMacServer in my case) and browse to the iTunes-folder where you placed<br />
all the music (still, on the iBook in the Finder-window opened when you<br />
connect to iMacServer). Make an <i>Alias</i> of the two files and the<br />
directory in it (click on one of them once, go to the<br />
<i>File</i>-submenu of the Finder and choose <i>Make Alias</i>) which<br />
results in three new entries in the iTunes directory : <i>iTunes 4 Music<br />
Library alias</i>, <i>iTunes 4 Music Library.xml alias</i> and <i>iTunes<br />
4 Music Library alias</i>. Drag these 3 aliases to the<br />
<i>Home/Music/iTunes</i>-folder on the iBook and rename them by removing<br />
the <i>alias</i>-addendum.</p>
<p> 3. In the Finder-window on<br />
the iBook corresponding to the iMacServer browse to the<br />
<i>Home/Library/Preferences</i>-folder and drag the two files<br />
<i>com.apple.iTunes.eq.plist</i> and <i>com.apple.iTunes.plist</i> to<br />
the <i>Home/Library/Preferences</i>-folder of the iBook. Launch<br />
<i>iTunes</i> and it will give you access to the whole iTunes-collection<br />
of iMacServer! In all, the three aliases and the 2 copied files take up<br />
128 Kb&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/the-itunes-hack/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WarChalking</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/warchalking/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/warchalking/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2004 17:55:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[games]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[warwalking]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=104</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What then is all this WarWalking, WarDriving, WarChalking and so on? In particular, why the aggressive War-word in them ? From what I learned, the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/warchalk.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;" /><br />
  What then is all this <i>WarWalking</i>, <i>WarDriving</i>,<br />
<i>WarChalking</i> and so on? In particular, why the aggressive<br />
<b>War</b>-word in them ? From what I learned, the historical origin of<br />
these terms comes from the 1983 movie <b>&#8220;War Games&#8221;</b> in which a<br />
kid sets up his modem to dial numbers until it finds a computer to hack<br />
leading inevitably to the US-army in total panic. This hobby created the<br />
phrase <b>WarDialing</b>. In analogy, a person driving around in a car<br />
with a laptop in search for wireless networks is said to be<br />
<b>WarDriving</b>, if (s)he is on foot it is clearly <b>WarWalking</b>.<br />
Because of the aggressive nature of the War-subword some people have<br />
re-engineered an explanation :</p>
<p> <b>WAR = Wireless<br />
Access Reconnaissance</b></p>
<p> so let us hope this acronym<br />
will catch on. Now then, what is <b>WarChalking</b> ? It was invented by<br />
<a href="http://www.blackbeltjones.com/work/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Matt Jones</a> and the idea is that a WarWalker should write a symbol in<br />
chalk on the wall nearest to the discovered Access Point describing its<br />
nature (see picture on the left) : the first sign depicts an <b>open</b><br />
node, the next a <b>closed</b> one and the last one is a node with<br />
<b>WEP</b>-protection (btw. <b>WEP=Wired Equivalent Privacy</b>). A lot<br />
of people seem to take this fairly serious, there is even a webpage <a href="http://www.warchalking.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">warchalking.org</a> devoted to it on which you can<br />
find a lot more information. And as warchalking was originally British,<br />
there had to be also an <a href="http://www.warchalking.us/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">American site</a> containing among other things a not<br />
that active forum. Further, the <a href="http://www.wardriving.com/doc/Wardriving-HOWTO.txt" target="_blank" rel="noopener">unofficial HOW-TO </a> of WarDriving may be<br />
interesting. To me it all sounds as an excuse to buy a<br />
<i>GPS-receiver</i> and a<br />
<i>laptop</i>&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/warchalking/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WarWalking (3)</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/warwalking-3/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/warwalking-3/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2004 15:38:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[google]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[OSX]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[warwalking]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=102</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This time we turn to Ethereal, &#8216;sniffing the glue that holds the Internet together&#8217;. Here is the description they give : &#8220;Ethereal is a free&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/ethereal.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;" /><br />
  This time we turn to <a href="http://www.ethereal.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ethereal</a>, &#8216;sniffing the glue that holds the<br />
Internet together&#8217;. Here is the description they give : &#8220;Ethereal is a<br />
free network protocol analyzer for Unix and Windows. It allows you to<br />
examine data from a live network or from a capture file on disk. You can<br />
interactively browse the capture data, viewing summary and detail<br />
information for each packet. Ethereal has several powerful features,<br />
including a rich display filter language and the ability to view the<br />
reconstructed stream of a TCP session&#8221;. Whereas OSX is not included it<br />
<b>is</b> possible to get <i>Ethereal</i> running under OSX but it<br />
requires some work. To begin you need to have the <b>XTools</b><br />
installed (the extra CD shipped with 10.3) (btw. you probably needed<br />
already the XTools to get <i>Kismet</i> up and running). Secondly, you<br />
need to have <b>X11</b> in <b>Applications/Utilities</b>. This is not a<br />
standard option if you install 10.3 but with a custom install you can<br />
install X11. If you haven&#8217;t done this, no problem, you can download X11<br />
from the <a href="http://www.apple.com/downloads/macosx/apple/x11formacosx.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">apple-site</a> (43Mb! download). And finally you need<br />
to have <b>Fink</b> installed (see a <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php?p=95">previous<br />
post</a>). If you are set, open the <i>Terminal</i> and type</p>
<p> <b>sudo fink install ethereal-ssl</b></p>
<p> Fink will tell you that it needs some additional packages to<br />
install (12 in my case) and you agree to this with typing <b>Y</b>. Get<br />
yourself a coffee and a book or newspaper because the compilation<br />
process takes quite a while (in my case it took over one hour!). When it<br />
finally stops you hope to be done, so start up X11 and type </p>
<p> <b>sudo /sw/bin/ethereal</b></p>
<p> and it<br />
works! If you want to begin sniffing you have to click on<br />
<i>Capture/Start</i> and a pop-up window appears. Specify <b>en1</b> as<br />
Interface and click on <i>Ok</i>. If after some time you press<br />
<i>Stop</i> all the captured packages appear in the main window and you<br />
can start playing. We will see another time what exactly you can do with<br />
all this information&#8230;</p>
<p> The previous time that I<br />
tried to install Ethereal (on an iBook) I got an error message :<br />
<i>dyld: /sw/bin/ethereal can&#8217;t open library: /sw/lib/libdl.0.dylib (No<br />
such file or directory, errno = 2)</i>. Fortunately a simple Google gave<br />
me the following <a href="http://www.avantbard.com/blog/archives/000533.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">work-around</a>. So if you get into problems that will<br />
probably solve them. I also needed to type <b>xhost  </b> in X11 to<br />
allow su to use my window. But, none of these problems appeared right<br />
now so maybe they updated the package.</p>
<p> Moreover,<br />
<i>Ethereal</i> is very well documented both with an <a href="http://www.ethereal.com/ethereal.1.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">online manual-page</a> and a <a href="http://www.ethereal.com/docs/user-guide/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">User&#8217;s guide</a> (which you can also download as<br />
PDF-file : 454 pages! but only the first 100 or so are worth<br />
printing).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/warwalking-3/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WarWalking (2)</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/warwalking-2/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/warwalking-2/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2004 14:34:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[OSX]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[warwalking]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=101</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[MacStumbler and iStumbler are active scanners sending out probe messages to the basestations and can therefore be detected easily. Moreover, they are not able to&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/kismac.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;" /><br />
<i>MacStumbler</i> and <i>iStumbler</i> are active scanners sending out<br />
probe messages to the basestations and can therefore be detected easily.<br />
Moreover, they are not able to detect <i>closed</i> networks. So let us<br />
move up one step in the secrecy scale and get some <b>passive network<br />
scanners</b> running. The first one is <a href="http://www.binaervarianz.de/projekte/programmieren/kismac/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KisMAC</a> which instructs the Airport card to tune to<br />
a channel, listen a while, then tune to the next channel and so on. In<br />
this way <i>KisMAC</i> can detects networks without announcing its<br />
presence and can also find <i>closed</i> networks. More information can<br />
be found at the <a href="http://www.binaervarianz.de/projekte/programmieren/kismac/documentation.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KisMAC documentation</a> page.<br />
Installation is pretty straightforward : click on the <i>KisMAC<br />
installer</i> icon and after answering a few obvious questions you need<br />
to provide your Administer-login and password after which <i>KisMAC</i><br />
is installed in your <i>Applications</i>-folder so also copy it to your<br />
dock. The reason why it needs admin privileges to run is that the<br />
Airport card cannot perform passive monitoring. So it swaps to open<br />
source <b>Viha driver</b> for your Airport-driver on startup and<br />
reinstalls the Airport driver on exit (that is, is everything goes well,<br />
sometimes you seem to have lost your Airport connection afterwards but<br />
no harm is done which cannot be solved by either checking in your<br />
<b>SystemPreferences:Network</b> or by a restart. So do not worry if you<br />
see that your Airport icon (as well as all your usual wireless access<br />
such as Internet and Mail) vanishes. Before you can perform a scan, you<br />
have to go to the KisMAC-Preferences and choose under <b>Driver</b> a<br />
capturing device (in some versions of KisMAC you have to specify <b>Viha<br />
driver</b> if you are running an Airport card, in others you have to go<br />
for the option <b>Apple Airport Card,Passive mode</b>. If you press the<br />
<b>Scan</b> button you are again asked for admin-password to perform the<br />
driver-switch (the same happens if you Quit KisMAC). The program gives a<br />
wealth of information which can be quite useful if you want to find out<br />
about possible interference of your ABS with other wireless sources. We<br />
will come back to some of these features later, a rather scary one is<br />
the ability to log raw 802.11 frames to a dump which can then be fed to<br />
<b>Ethereal</b>.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/kismet.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;" />   Okay,<br />
let us go one step further and try to get <a href="http://www.kismetwireless.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kismet</a><br />
running. It seems to be an unwritten law in open source-software that<br />
the more potential harmful a program is, the more difficult it is to<br />
install, so installing <i>Kismet</i> is by no means trivial.<br />
Fortunately, <i>Kismet</i> is very well documented with a <a href="http://www.kismetwireless.net/documentation.shtml" target="_blank" rel="noopener">manual</a> and a <a href="http://www.kismetwireless.net/forum.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener">forum</a>. First, we need the <b>Viha Airport<br />
driver</b>, that is we need <a href="http://www.dopesquad.net/security/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Viha Wireless Tools 0.0.1a Binary Release</a>. Go in <i>Terminal</i> to the<br />
<i>Desktop-folder</i> where you will find the Folder <b>Viha-0.0.1a</b>.<br />
Then type</p>
<p> <b>mv Viha-0.0.1a/WiFi.framework/<br />
/Library/Frameworks/</b></p>
<p> Next, we get the latest<br />
version of Kismet, that is <a href="http://www.monolith81.de/wirelesslan/mirrors/?path=kismet/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">kismet-3.0.1.tar.gz</a> and get a <b>kismet-3.0.1</b><br />
folder on our Desktop. Use <i>Terminal</i> to go into this folder and<br />
type</p>
<p> <b>./configure &#8211;disable-pcap &#8211;enable-viha;<br />
make</b></p>
<p> and the following process may last for a<br />
while. If you finally get a prompt, type</p>
<p> <b>sudo make<br />
install</b></p>
<p> and the process will end with some<br />
warning messages : </p>
<p> <i>If you have not done so<br />
already, read the README file and the FAQ file.  Additional<br
/> documentation is in the docs/ directory.  You MUST edit<br />
/usr/local/etc/kismet.conf <br /> and configure Kismet for your<br />
system, or it will NOT run properly!<br /> Kismet has NOT been<br />
installed suid-root.  This means you will need to start <br /> it as<br />
root.  If you have no untrusted users on your system, it can be<br />
installed <br /> as suid-root via &#8216;make suidinstall&#8217;.  READ THE<br />
DOCUMENTATION BEFORE INSTALLING KISMET AS SUID-ROOT!&#8221;</i></p>
<p> Fine, so let us go to <b>/usr/local/etc</b> and change the<br />
following lines in <b>kismet.conf</b></p>
<p> <b>suiduser=lieven</b><br /> <b>source=viha,en1,Airport</b></p>
<p> (of course you have to replace <i>lieven</i> by your<br />
normal OSX login name). Further, in the file <b>kismet_ui.conf</b><br />
replace the last line by</p>
<p> <b>apm=false</b></p>
<p> Finally, you have to type in the Terminal</p>
<p> <b>export TERM=xterm-color</b></p>
<p> and you should<br />
be done. To launch Kismet, type as your usual user (the one you<br />
specified in the kismet.conf file) in the Terminal</p>
<p> <b>Kismet</b></p>
<p> and all will work. Again there is<br />
a switch of Airport to Viha driver (and if all works well also at the<br />
end). Often, the Airport card does not come up at the end in which case<br />
it is best to restart Kismet and Quit again (btw. you quit Kismet with<br />
capital Q). Then the Airport icon appears but it may be that you have to<br />
logon to your network again.</p>
<p> We wouldnt have done so<br />
much trouble if it were not that <i>Kismet</i> is a VERY powerfull<br />
application which can be used to Hack wireless networks. But if you<br />
think that <b>KisMAC</b> and <b>Kismet</b> are already scary, wait until<br />
next time when we deal with <b>Ethereal</b>&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/warwalking-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WarWalking (1)</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/warwalking-1/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/warwalking-1/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2004 14:29:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[OSX]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[warwalking]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=100</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What exactly is a \&#8217;WarDriver\&#8217;? WarDriver: One who locates and logs wireless access points while in motion ;[benign]. WarDriving was invented by Peter Shipley and&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/wardriver.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;" /><br />
What exactly is a \&#8217;WarDriver\&#8217;? WarDriver: One who locates and logs<br />
wireless access points while in motion ;[benign]. WarDriving was<br />
invented by Peter Shipley and now commonly practiced by hobbyists,<br />
hackers and security analysts worldwide. More information about this<br />
trend can be found at <a href="http://www.wardriving.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">wardriving.com</a>. Even if you are not into this<br />
sport, the following (innocent) software may be of use to obtain<br />
information about your wireless network. In a next message I\&#8217;ll discuss<br />
a few less innocent software tools. Probably the most popular <i>network<br />
scanner</i> for Mac OSX is <a href="http://www.macstumbler.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MacStumbler</a>. It detects nearby wireless networks,<br />
tells you the channels they use, whether they use <b>WEP</b><br />
(encryption), give their signal (and noise) strength, the name of the<br />
network and if you click on the <i>Details button</i> it gives you<br />
(among other things) the <b>MAC-address</b>. A similar tool is <a href="http://www.istumbler.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">iStumbler</a>. It<br />
gives roughly the same information : <b>SSID</b> (name). MAC-address,<br />
signal/noise, channel and whether it is encrypted. More information is<br />
available from the <a href="http://www.istumbler.net/manual.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">iStumbler manual</a>. In addition it presents a<br />
<b>signal graph</b> which is useful if you are trying to decide on which<br />
signal you will let your Airport-basestation broadcast. Using<br />
<i>iStumbler</i> i discovered that there was a recurrent noise at<br />
channel 5 every couple of minutes (don\&#8217;t ask what it was) but that on<br />
channel 1 the signal was not interrupted. </p>
<p> Both<br />
<i>MacStumbler</i> and <i>iStumbler</i> are <b>active</b> scanners<br />
meaning that they send out probe request to nearby access points. As a<br />
result they are not able to detect <b>closed</b> networks. To detect<br />
them you need far more intrusive <i>passive scanning</i> software, but<br />
that is for next time.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/warwalking-1/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
