<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Beauvallon &#8211; neverendingbooks</title>
	<atom:link href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tag/beauvallon/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 15:58:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.4</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Bourbaki = Bishops or Banditos?</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-bishops-or-banditos/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-bishops-or-banditos/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 15:58:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tBC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[banditos?]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Beauvallon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bishops]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bourbaki]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tbc]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tØp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Trench]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=11400</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In this series I&#8217;m trying to make sense of the inclusion of Nicolas Bourbaki in the storyline of Trench, the fifth studio album by American&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this series I&#8217;m trying to make sense of the inclusion of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolas_Bourbaki">Nicolas Bourbaki</a> in the storyline of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trench_(album)">Trench</a>, the fifth studio album by American musical duo <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twenty_One_Pilots">Twenty One Pilots</a> (or TØP).</p>
<p>That story is about the walled city of Dema, ruled by nine bishops dressed in red cloaks. They enforce their religion, called Vialism, on the inhabitants of Dema. The end-goal in Vialism is that you take your own life, having maximal impact (think: suicide bombers).</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://topmasterdoc.carrd.co/assets/images/image23.jpg?v=c02a4a30" width=100%><br />
</center></p>
<p>Outside the walls of Dema is the land of Trench, where a group of fighters (the Banditos) set up camp. They are dressed in grey trenchcoats adorned with yellow ribbons, and their goal is to help people escape from Dema, via its east side.</p>
<p>What on earth has the Bourbaki group to do with any of this?</p>
<p>We know from a <a href="https://twitter.com/tylerrjoseph/status/1030991703203897345">tweet by Tyler Joseph</a> that one Bourbaki-photograph (or at least a PhotoShopped version of it) played an important role in the creative process, as he used it as the background image on his Mac while producing the album.</p>
<p>It can also be seen, blurred in the background, in the opening seconds of his interview with Zane Lowe on Apple Music:</p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/s4CLo1gpHyQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>Here are the three versions: the original photo, overlayed with the tweet-image, and a screenshot from the interview:</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/af/Bourbaki_congress1938.png/440px-Bourbaki_congress1938.png" width=45%> <img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/BeauvallonTop.png" width=45%><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/BeavallonDesktop.png" width=45%><br />
</center></p>
<p>In the original photo, taken at the <a href="http://archives-bourbaki.ahp-numerique.fr/items/show/651#?c=0&#038;m=0&#038;s=0&#038;cv=0">1938 Dieulefit Bourbaki congress</a>, we see seven people, from left to right</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simone_Weil">Simone Weil</a> (not Bourbaki, sister of Andre Weil)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Pisot">Charles Pisot</a> (chrysalide, <a href="http://archives-bourbaki.ahp-numerique.fr/items/browse?advanced[0][element_id]=87&#038;advanced[0][type]=is+exactly&#038;advanced[0][terms]=Pisot%2C+Charles">Bourbaki member after WW2</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andr%C3%A9_Weil">Andre Weil</a>, partially hidden (Bourbaki founding member)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Dieudonn%C3%A9">Jean Dieudonne</a>, sitting (Bourbaki founding member)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claude_Chabauty">Claude Chabauty</a> (chrysalide, <a href="http://archives-bourbaki.ahp-numerique.fr/items/browse?advanced[0][element_id]=87&#038;advanced[0][type]=is+exactly&#038;advanced[0][terms]=Chabauty%2C+Claude">Bourbaki member during and after WW2</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Ehresmann">Charles Ehresmann</a> (Bourbaki founding member)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Delsarte">Jean Delsarte</a> (Bourbaki founding member)</li>
</ul>
<p>In the overlayed image an additional eight person, a bearded man, is PhotoShopped in the doorway, and in the screenshot we see that apart from this mystery man the empty chair in the lower left corner is replaced by a ninth person.</p>
<p>Common belief among the &#8216;clique&#8217; (TØP&#8217;s fanbase name) is that the nine people in the desktop image are the nine bishops of Dema, with the bearded man being Nico (the head-bishop), Andre Weil bishop Andre, and Simone Weil bishop Sacarver (the only known female bishop).</p>
<p>But who are these two additional persons?</p>
<p>In a remarkable tour de force, Reddit user &#8216;banditosleepers&#8217; was able to find the man sitting in the lower left corner (though he identified him wrongly)</p>
<blockquote class="reddit-embed-bq" style="height:316px" data-embed-height="316"><p>      <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/twentyonepilots/comments/m28f43/i_found_one_of_the_people_shopped_into_tylers/">I found one of the people shopped into Tyler&#8217;s desktop (2018)</a><br /> by      <a href="https://www.reddit.com/user/banditosleepers">u/banditosleepers</a> in      <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/twentyonepilots/">twentyonepilots</a>    </p></blockquote>
<p><script async="" src="https://embed.reddit.com/widgets.js" charset="UTF-8"></script></p>
<p>There&#8217;s this other famous pre-WW2 photo of a Bourbaki congress, this time the 1937 congress in <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/wheres-bourbakis-escorial">Chancay</a>:</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA2/chancay2.jpg" width=100%></p>
<p>Here we see, from left to right:</p>
<ul>
<li>Andre Weil</li>
<li>Simone Weil (standing)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henri_Cartan">Henri Cartan</a> (Bourbaki founding member)</li>
<li><a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Szolem_Mandelbrojt">Szolem Mandelbrojt</a> (Bourbaki founding member)</li>
<li><a href="">Claude Chevalley</a> (sitting on the bank, Bourbaki founding member)</li>
<li>Jean Delsarte (partially hidded)</li>
</ul>
<p>That is, the ninth person, sitting in the left lower corner of the screenshot is Szolem Mandelbrojt (and not Claude Chevalley, as claimed in the Reddit-post).</p>
<p>There&#8217;s another photo, taken at about the same moment, showing that also Jean Dieudonne (sitting on the bank in front next to Andre Weil) and Charles Ehresmann (sitting on the bank on the right, next to Jean Delsarte and Claude Chevalley) were present.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/chancay1937photo2.jpg" width=100%></p>
<p>Several people (myself included) have wasted too many hours trying to identify the bearded man in the doorway, starting from the assumption that he too might have some connection with Bourbaki (either the group or <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Denis_Bourbaki">the general</a>), without success.</p>
<p>There&#8217;s one problem with the &#8216;bearded man = Nico&#8217; hypothesis. Nico is supposed to be the tallest of the bishops, and bearded man&#8217;s head is level with Andre Weil&#8217;s head, who stand on the first step, so bearded man must at least be 15cm smaller than Andre, who was already rather short.</p>
<p>Here&#8217;s a theory.</p>
<p>The original Dieulefit 1938 photo is the first one on the Wikipedia page for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolas_Bourbaki">Nicolas Bourbaki</a>, and if you click on it you get a link to one of my own blogposts <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-and-the-miracle-of-silence">Bourbaki and the miracle of silence</a>.</p>
<p>In that post (from 2010) I found the exact location where that photo was taken: the <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%89cole_de_Beauvallon">Ecole de Beauvallon</a>, founded in 1929 by <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marguerite_Soubeyran">Marguerite Soubeyran</a> and Catherine Krafft, which was the first ‘modern’ boarding school in France for both boys and girls having behavioural problems. From 1936 on the school’s director was Simone Monnier.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA2/evidence1.jpg" width=100%></p>
<p>The lower picture is taken at the Ecole de Beauvallon in 1943, the woman in the middle is Marguerite Soubeyran.</p>
<p>From 1936 on, about 20 refugees from the Spanish civil war found a home at the school, and in the ‘pension’, next to the school. When WW2 started, about 1500 people were hidden from the German occupation in Dieulefit (having a total population of 3500) : Jewish children, intellectuals, artists, trade union leaders, many in the Ecole and the Pension. None were betrayed to the Germans, and this is called <a href="https://www.slate.fr/story/98797/dieulefit-occupation">Le miracle de silence à Dieulefit</a>.</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://www.rebelle-sante.com/wp-content/uploads/rs-222-rencontre-coline-3.jpg" width=50%><br />
</center></p>
<p>Given this historical context, there is only one possible way to include this Bourbaki-photo in the Trench-storyline: the Ecole de Beauvallon is the equivalent of the Bandito-camp, and the Bourbakis are Banditos (or at the very least, refugees having found a safe place in the camp).</p>
<p>In hindsight this was already given away by Tyler Joseph in that he gave the photo the color yellow, specifically Bandito-yellow 0xFCE300, which the bishops are unable to see (they see it as grey).</p>
<p>How does this help in identifying the bearded man in the doorway?</p>
<p>Standing in the doorway, he&#8217;s the one feeling at home there, gathering around him his guests or fellow fighters. My conjecture is that he is the leader of the bandito-camp, as seen at 2.12 in the movieclip of Levitate.</p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uv_1AKKKJnk" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>Granted, it is not a perfect match. I think &#8216;bearded man&#8217; is how Tyler Joseph envisioned the camp-leader, and included his picture in the &#8216;Trench Bible&#8217;, the 60 page booklet given to the movie-director, who did the casting some months later.</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/bearded2.jpg" width=40%> <img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/bearded1.jpg" width=40%><br />
</center></p>
<p>Next time we will try to find City of Dema, or at least what it should be if you take the inclusion of Bourbaki in the Trench storyline seriously.</p>
<p><strong>In this series:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-and-top-east-is-up">Bourbaki and TØP : East is up</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-bishops-or-banditos">Bourbaki = Bishops or Banditos?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/wheres-bourbakis-dema">Where’s Bourbaki’s Dema?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/weil-photos-used-in-dema-lore">Weil photos used in Dema-lore</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/dema2trench-and-repeat">Dema2Trench, AND REpeat</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/top-photoshop-mysteries">TØP PhotoShop mysteries</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/9-bourbaki-founding-members-really">9 Bourbaki founding members, really?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-and-dema-two-remarks">Bourbaki and Dema, two remarks</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/clancy-and-nancago">Clancy and Nancago</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-bishops-or-banditos/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bourbaki and the miracle of silence</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-and-the-miracle-of-silence/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-and-the-miracle-of-silence/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2010 19:49:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tBC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Beauvallon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bourbaki]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chabauty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Delsarte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dieudonne]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dieulefit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Weil]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[World War]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=3193</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The last pre-war Bourbaki congress, held in september 1938 in Dieulefit, is surrounded by mystery. Compared to previous meetings, fewer documents are preserved in the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The last pre-war Bourbaki congress, held in september 1938 in Dieulefit, is surrounded by mystery. Compared to previous meetings, fewer documents are preserved in the <a href="http://portail.mathdoc.fr/archives-bourbaki/">Bourbaki archives</a> and some sentences in the surviving notules have been made illegible. We will have to determine the exact location of the Dieulefit-meeting before we can understand why this had to be done. It&#8217;s Bourbaki&#8217;s own tiny contribution to &#8216;le miracle de silence&#8217;&#8230;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA2/Bourbaki1938.jpg" align=left style="margin-right:10px;"> First, the few facts we know about this Bourbaki congress, mostly from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/André_Weil">Andre Weil</a>&#8216;s autobiography <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Apprenticeship-Mathematician-Andre-Weil/dp/3764326506/">&#8216;The Apprenticeship of a Mathematician&#8217;</a>.</p>
<p>The meeting was held in <a href="http://www.drome-provence.com/villages/dieulefit.php">Dieulefit</a> in the Drome-Provencale region, sometime in september 1938 prior to the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Munich_Agreement">Munich Agreement</a> (more on this next time). We know that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Élie_Cartan">Elie Cartan</a> did accept Bourbaki&#8217;s invitation to join them and there is this one famous photograph of the meeting. From left to right : Simone Weil (accompanying Andre), Charles Pison, Andre Weil (hidden), Jean Dieudonne (sitting), Claude Chabauty, Charles Ehresmann, and Jean Delsarte.</p>
<p>Failing further written documentation, &#8216;all&#8217; we have to do in order to pinpoint the exact location of the meeting is to find a match between this photograph and some building in Dieulefit&#8230;</p>
<p>The crucial clue is provided by the couple of sentences, on the final page of the Bourbaki-archive document deldi_001 <a href="http://portail.mathdoc.fr/archives-bourbaki/PDF/deldi_001.pdf">Engagements de Dieulefit</a>, someone (Jean Delsarte?) has tried to make illegible (probably early on).</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA2/GeschrapteTekst.jpg"><br />
</center></p>
<p>Blowing the picture up, it isn&#8217;t too hard to guess that the header should read &#8216;Décision du 22 septembre 1938&#8217; and that the first sentence is &#8216;Le Bourbaki de 2e classe WEIL fera pour le 15 octobre&#8217;. The document is signed</p>
<p>Camp de Beauvallon, le 22.IX.38.<br />
L&#8217;adjudant de jour<br />
DIEUDONNE</p>
<p>Now we are getting somewhere. Beauvallon is the name of an hamlet of Dieulefit, situated approximately 2.5km to the east of the center.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA2/Dieulefit.jpg"></p>
<p>Beauvallon is rather famous for its <a href="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/École_de_Beauvallon">School</a>, founded in 1929 by <a href="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marguerite_Soubeyran">Marguerite Soubeyran</a> and <a href="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_Krafft">Catherine Krafft</a>, which was the first &#8216;modern&#8217; boarding school in France for both boys and girls having behavioral problems. From 1936 on the school&#8217;s director was <a href="http://www.lepost.fr/article/2008/09/03/1307302_simone-monnier-fondatrice-de-beauvallon.html">Simone Monnier</a>.</p>
<p>These three women were politically active and frequented several circles. Already in 1938 (at about the time of the Bourbaki congress) they knew the reality of the Nazi persecutions and planned to prepare their school to welcome, care for and protect refugees and Jewish children.</p>
<p>From 1936 on about 20 Spanish republican refugees found a home here and in the &#8216;pension&#8217; next to the school. When the war started, about 1500 people were hidden from the German occupation in Dieulefit (having a total population of 3500) : Jewish children, intellectuals, artists, trade union leaders, etc. etc. many in the Ecole and the Pension.</p>
<p>Because of the towns solidarity with the refugees, none were betrayed to the Germans, <a href="http://www.lepoint.fr/actualites-societe/miracle-a-dieulefit/920/0/229069">Le miracle de silence à Dieulefit</a>.<br />
It earned the three Ecole-women the title of &#8220;Juste&#8221; after the war. More on this period can be read <a href="http://www.clio-cr.clionautes.org/spip.php?article2993">here</a>.</p>
<p>But what does this have to do with Bourbaki? Well, we claim that the venue of the 1938 Bourbaki congress was the <a href="http://www.ajpn.org/sauvetage-ecole-de-Beauvallon-263.html">Ecole de Beauvallon</a> and they probably used Le Pension for their lodgings.</p>
<p>We have photographic evidence comparing the Bourbaki picture with a picture taken in 1943 at the Ecole (the woman in the middle is Marguerite Soubeyran). Compare the distance between door and window, the division of the windows and the ivy on the wall.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA2/evidence1.jpg"></p>
<p>Below two photographs of the entire school building : on the left, the school with &#8216;Le Pension&#8217; next to it around 1938 (the ivy clad wall with the Bourbaki-door is to the right) and on the right, the present <a href="http://pagesperso-orange.fr/lesamisdebeauvallon/pages/0.html">Ecole de Beauvallon</a> (this site also contains a lot of historical material). The ivy has gone, but the main features of the building are still intact, only the shape of the small roof above the Bourbaki-door has changed.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA2/evidence2.jpg"></p>
<p>During their stay, it is likely the Bourbakis became aware of the plans the school had would war break out. Probably, Jean Delsarte removed all explicit mention to the Ecole de Beauvallon from the archives upon their return. Bourbaki&#8217;s own small contribution to Dieulefit&#8217;s miracle of silence.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/bourbaki-and-the-miracle-of-silence/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
