<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Kontsevich &#8211; neverendingbooks</title>
	<atom:link href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tag/kontsevich/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 19:42:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Huawei and French mathematics</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/huawei-and-french-mathematics/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/huawei-and-french-mathematics/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 19:42:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[france]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[math]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Broue]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cartier]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Figalli]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Huawei]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kontsevich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lafforgue]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Schapira]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=9943</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Huawei, the Chinese telecom giant, appears to support (and divide) the French mathematical community. I was surprised to see that Laurent Lafforgue&#8217;s affiliation recently changed&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Huawei, the Chinese telecom giant, appears to support (and divide) the French mathematical community.</p>
<p>I was surprised to see that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laurent_Lafforgue">Laurent Lafforgue&#8217;s</a> affiliation recently changed from &#8216;IHES&#8217; to &#8216;Huawei&#8217;, for example <a href="https://utge.lakecomoschool.org/">here</a> as one of the organisers of the Lake Como conference on &#8216;Unifying themes in geometry&#8217;.</p>
<p>Judging from this short Huawei-clip (in French) he thoroughly enjoys his new position.</p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EqrNLuN5Bfk" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>Huawei <a href="https://inf.news/en/science/0b03792c7ee5879f723ea9ffaa608e60.html">claims</a> that &#8216;Three more winners of the highest mathematics award have now joined Huawei&#8217;:</p>
<p>&#8211; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maxim_Kontsevich">Maxim Kontsevich</a>, (IHES) Fields medal 1998</p>
<p>&#8211; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre-Louis_Lions">Pierre-Louis Lions</a> (College de France) Fields medal 1994</p>
<p>&#8211; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alessio_Figalli">Alessio Figalli</a> (ETH) Fields medal 2018</p>
<p>These news-stories seem to have been G-translated from the Chinese, resulting in misspellings and perhaps other inaccuracies. Maxim&#8217;s research field is described as &#8216;kink theory&#8217; (LoL).</p>
<p>Apart from luring away Fields medallist, Huawei set up last year the brand new <a href="https://www.huawei.com/fr/news/fr/2020/centre-lagrange">Huawei Lagrange Research Center</a> in the posh 7th arrondissement de Paris. (This &#8216;Lagrange Center&#8217; is different from the <a href="http://ilp.upmc.fr/">Lagrange Institute in Paris</a> devoted to astronomy and physics.)</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/LagrangeCenter.jpg" width=100% \><br />
</center></p>
<p>It aims to host about 30 researchers in mathematics and computer science, giving them the opportunity to live in the &#8216;unique eco-system of Paris, having the largest group of mathematicians in the world, as well as the best universities&#8217;.</p>
<p>Last May, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michel_Brou%C3%A9">Michel Broué</a> authored an open letter to the French mathematical community <a href="https://blogs.mediapart.fr/michel-broue/blog/180521/dans-un-hotel-particulier-du-7eme-arrondissement-de-paris">Dans un hotel particulier du 7eme arrondissement de Paris</a> (in French). A G-translation of the final part of this open letter:</p>
<p>&#8220;In the context of a very insufficient research and development effort in France, and bleak prospects for our young researchers, it is tempting to welcome the creation of the Lagrange center. We welcome the rise of Chinese mathematics to the highest level, and we are obviously in favour of scientific cooperation with our Chinese colleagues.</p>
<p>But in view of the role played by Huawei in the repression in Xinjiang and potentially everywhere in China, we call on mathematicians and computer scientists already engaged to withdraw from this project. We ask all researchers not to participate in the activities of this center, as we ourselves are committed to doing.&#8221;</p>
<p>Among the mathematicians signing the letter are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Cartier_(mathematician)">Pierre Cartier</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Schapira_(mathematician)">Pierre Schapira</a>.</p>
<p>To be continued.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/huawei-and-french-mathematics/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>best of 2008 (2) : big theorems</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/best-of-2008-2-big-theorems/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/best-of-2008-2-big-theorems/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2009 18:56:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blogging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[google]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kontsevich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Riemann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wordpress]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://matrix.cmi.ua.ac.be/?p=854</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A comment to Charles Siegel's 'big theorems'-series got me checking my stats.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA2/ChSiegelP.jpg" style="float:right;margin-left:10px;"><a href="http://www.math.upenn.edu/~siegelch/">Charles Siegel</a> of <a href="http://rigtriv.wordpress.com/author/rigtriv/">Rigorous Trivialities</a> ran a great series on <a href="http://wordpress.com/tag/big-theorems/">big theorems</a>.</p>
<p>The series started january 10th 2008 with a post on <a href="http://rigtriv.wordpress.com/2008/01/10/bezouts-theorem/">Bezout&#8217;s theorem</a>, followed by posts on Chow&#8217;s lemma, Serre duality, Riemann-Roch, Bertini, Nakayama&#8217;s lemma, Groebner bases, Hurwitz to end just before christmas with a post on <a href="http://rigtriv.wordpress.com/2008/12/23/kontsevichs-formula/">Kontsevich&#8217;s formula</a>.</p>
<p>Also at other blogs, 2008 was the year of series of long posts containing substantial pure mathematics.</p>
<p>Out of many, just two examples : Chris Schommer-Pries ran a three part series on TQFTs via planar algebras starting <a href="http://sbseminar.wordpress.com/2008/12/05/tqfts-via-planar-algebras/">here</a>, at the <a href="http://sbseminar.wordpress.com/">secret blogging seminar</a>.<br />
And, Peter Woit of <a href="http://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/">Not Even Wrong</a> has an ungoing series of posts called Notes on BRST, starting <a href="http://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=1076">here</a>. At the moment he is at episode <a href="http://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=1439">nine</a>.</p>
<p>It suffices to have a quick look at the length of any of these posts, to see that a great deal of work was put into these series (and numerous similar ones, elsewhere). Is this amount of time well spend? Or, should we focus on shorter, easier digestible math-posts?</p>
<p>What got me thinking was this merciless comment Charles got after a great series of posts leading up to Kontsevich&#8217;s formula :</p>
<p>&#8220;Perhaps you should make a New Years commitment to not be so obscurantist, like John Armstrong, and instead promote the public understanding of math!&#8221;</p>
<p>Well, if this doesn&#8217;t put you off blogging for a while, what will?</p>
<p>So, are we really writing the wrong sort of posts? Do math-blog readers only want short, flashy, easy reading posts these days? Or, is anyone out there taking notice of the hard work it takes to write such a technical post, let alone a series of them?</p>
<p>At first I was rather pessimistic about the probable answer to all these questions, but, fortunately we have <a href="http://www.google.com/analytics/">Google Analytics</a> to quantify things a bit.</p>
<p>Clearly I can only rely on the statistics for my own site, so I&#8217;ll treat the case of a recent post here : <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/mumfords-treasure-map.html">Mumford&#8217;s treasure map</a> which tried to explain the notion of a generic point and how one might depict an affine scheme.</p>
<p>Here&#8217;s some of the Google Analytics data :</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA2/GAMumford.jpg"><br />
</center></p>
<p>The yellow function gives the number of pageviews for that post, the value ranges between 0 and 600 (the number to the right of the picture). In total this post was viewed 2470 times, up till now.</p>
<p>The blue function tells the average time a visitor spend reading that post, the numbers range between 0 and 8 minutes (the times to the left of the picture). On average the time-on-page was 2.24 minutes, so in all people spend well over 92 hours reading this one post! This seems like a good return for the time it took me to write it&#8230;</p>
<p>Some other things can be learned from this data. Whereas the number of page-views has two peaks early on (one the day it was posted, the second one when Peter Woit <a href="http://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=1389">linked</a> to it) and is now steadily decreasing, the time-on-page for the later visitors is substantially longer than the early readers.</p>
<p>Some of this may be explained (see comment below) by returning visits. Here is a more detailed picture (orange = new visits, green=returning visits, blue=&#8217;total&#8217; whatever this means).</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA2/returningMumford.jpg"><br />
</center></p>
<p>All in all good news : there is indeed a market for longer technical math-posts and people (eventually) take time to read the post in detail.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/best-of-2008-2-big-theorems/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>best of 2008 (1) : wiskundemeisjes</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/best-of-2008-1-wiskundemeisjes/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/best-of-2008-1-wiskundemeisjes/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2009 11:54:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Galois]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kontsevich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Manin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marcolli]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wordpress]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://matrix.cmi.ua.ac.be/?p=823</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A feeble attempt to translate the Marcolli-post by the 'wiskundemeisjes'.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA2/wiskundemeisjesP.jpg" style="float:right;margin-left:10px;">Of course, excellent math-blogs exist in every language imaginable, but my linguistic limitations restrict me to the ones written in English, French, German and &#8230; Dutch. Here a few links to Dutch (or rather, Flemish) math-blogs, in order of proximity :<br />
Stijn Symens <a href="http://stijnsymens.wordpress.com/">blog</a>, Rudy Penne&#8217;s <a href="http://weetlogs.scilogs.be/index.php?blogId=11">wiskunde is sexy (math is sexy)</a>, Koen Vervloesem&#8217;s <a href="http://www.vervloesem.eu/qed/">QED</a>.</p>
<p>My favorite one is <a href="http://www.wiskundemeisjes.nl/">wiskundemeisjes</a> (&#8216;math-chicks&#8217; or &#8216;math-girls&#8217;), written by Ionica Smeets and Jeanine Daems, two reasearchers at Leiden University. Every month they have a post called &#8220;the favorite (living) mathematician of &#8230;&#8221; in which they ask someone to nominate and introduce his/her favorite colleague mathematician. Here some examples : <a href="http://www.wiskundemeisjes.nl/20061026/de-favoriete-nog-levende-wiskundige-van-5/">Roger Penrose chooses Michael Atiyah</a>, <a href="http://www.wiskundemeisjes.nl/20061130/de-favoriete-nog-levende-wiskunde-van5/">Robbert Dijkgraaf chooses Maxim Kontsevich</a>, <a href="http://www.wiskundemeisjes.nl/20071129/de-favoriete-nog-levende-wiskundige-van…-18/">Frans Oort chooses David Mumford</a>, <a href="http://www.wiskundemeisjes.nl/20071227/de-favoriete-nog-levende-wiskundige-van…-19/">Gunther Cornelissen chooses Yuri I. Manin</a>, <a href="http://www.wiskundemeisjes.nl/20081030/de-favoriete-nog-levende-wiskundige-van-27/">Hendrik Lenstra chooses Bjorn Poonen</a>, etc. the full list is <a href="http://www.wiskundemeisjes.nl/favoriete-wiskundigen/">here</a> or <a href="http://www.wiskundemeisjes.nl/category/favoriete-wiskundigen/">here</a>. This series deserves a wider audience. Perhaps Ionica and Jeanine might consider translating some of these posts?</p>
<p>I&#8217;m certain their English is far better than mine, so here&#8217;s a feeble attempt to translate the one post in their series they consider a complete failure (it isn&#8217;t even listed in the category). Two reasons for me to do so : it features Matilde Marcolli (one of my own favorite living mathematicians) and Matilde expresses here very clearly my own take on popular-math books/blogs.</p>
<p>The original post was written by Ionica and was called <a href="http://www.wiskundemeisjes.nl/20080716/weg-met-de-favoriete-wiskundige-van/">Weg met de &#8216;favoriete wiskundige van&#8230;&#8217;</a> :</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA2/MarcolliP.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;"> &#8220;This week I did spend much of my time at the Fifth European Mathematical Congress in Amsterdam. Several mathematicians suggested I should have a chat with <a href="http://www.math.fsu.edu/~marcolli/">Matilde Marcolli</a>, one of the plenary speakers. It seemed like a nice idea to ask her about her favorite (still living) mathematician, for our series.</p>
<p>Marcolli explained why she couldn&#8217;t answer this question : she has favorite mathematical ideas, but it doesn&#8217;t interest her one bit who discovered or proved them. And, there are mathematicians she likes, but that&#8217;s because she finds them interesting as human beings, independent of their mathematical achievements.</p>
<p>In addition, she thinks it&#8217;s a mistake to focus science too much on the persons. Scientific ideas should play the main role, not the scientists themselves. To her it is important to remember that many results are the combined effort of several people, that science doesn&#8217;t evolve around personalities and that scientific ideas are accessible to anyone.</p>
<p>Marcolli also dislikes the current trend in popular science writing: “I am completely unable to read popular-scientific books. As soon as they start telling anecdotes and stories, I throw away the book. I don’t care about their lives, I care about the real stuff.”</p>
<p>She&#8217;d love to read a popular science-book containing only ideas. She regrets that most of these books restrict to story-telling, but fail to disseminate the scientific ideas.&#8221;</p>
<p>Ionica then goes on to defend her own approach to science-popularization :</p>
<p>&#8220;&#8230; Probably, people will not know much about Galois-theory by reading about his turbulent life. Still, I can imagine people to become interested in &#8216;the real stuff&#8217; after reading his biography, and, in this manner they will read some mathematics they wouldn&#8217;t have known to exist otherwise. But, Marcolli got me thinking, for it is true that almost all popular science-books focus on anecdotes rather than science itself. Is this wrong? For instance, do you want to see more mathematics here? I&#8217;m curious to hear your opinion on this.&#8221;</p>
<p>Even though my own approach is somewhat different, Ionica and Jeanine you&#8217;re doing an excellent job: &#8220;houden zo!&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/best-of-2008-1-wiskundemeisjes/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>noncommutative F_un geometry (2)</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/noncommutative-f_un-geometry-2/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/noncommutative-f_un-geometry-2/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2008 12:14:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noncommutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arxiv]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[coalgebras]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Connes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dedekind]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[google]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Grothendieck]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kontsevich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[permutation representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[representations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=459</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We use Kontsevich's idea of thin varieties to define complexified varieties over F\_un.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/fun/index.php/towards-noncommutative-f_un-geometry.html">Last time</a> we tried to generalize the <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/fun/index.php/connes-consani-for-undergraduates-1.html">Connes-Consani</a> approach to commutative algebraic geometry over the field with one element $\mathbb{F}_1 $ to the noncommutative world by considering covariant functors</p>
<p>$N~:~\mathbf{groups} \rightarrow \mathbf{sets} $</p>
<p>which over $\mathbb{C} $ resp. $\mathbb{Z} $ become visible by a complex (resp. integral) algebra having suitable universal properties.</p>
<p>However, we didn&#8217;t specify what we meant by a complex noncommutative variety (resp. an integral noncommutative scheme). In particular, we claimed that the $\mathbb{F}_1 $-&#8216;points&#8217; associated to the functor</p>
<p>$D~:~\mathbf{groups} \rightarrow \mathbf{sets} \qquad G \mapsto G_2 \times G_3 $ (here $G_n $ denotes all elements of order $n $ of $G $)</p>
<p>were precisely the modular dessins d&#8217;enfants of Grothendieck, but didn&#8217;t give details. We&#8217;ll try to do this now.</p>
<p>For algebras over a field we follow the definition, due to <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/math/0606241">Kontsevich and Soibelman</a>, of so called &#8220;noncommutative <strong>thin</strong> schemes&#8221;. Actually, the <strong>thinness</strong>-condition is implicit in both Soule&#8217;s-approach as that of Connes and Consani : we do not consider R-points in general, but only those of rings R which are finite and flat over our basering (or field).</p>
<p>So, what is a <strong>noncommutative thin scheme</strong> anyway? Well, its a covariant functor (commuting with finite projective limits)</p>
<p>$\mathbb{X}~:~\mathbf{Alg}^{fd}_k \rightarrow \mathbf{sets} $</p>
<p>from finite-dimensional (possibly noncommutative) $k $-algebras to sets. Now, the usual dual-space operator gives an anti-equivalence of categories</p>
<p>$\mathbf{Alg}^{fd}_k \leftrightarrow \mathbf{Coalg}^{fd}_k \qquad A=C^* \leftrightarrow C=A^* $</p>
<p>so a thin scheme can also be viewed as a contra-variant functor (commuting with finite direct limits)</p>
<p>$\mathbb{X}~:~\mathbf{Coalg}^{fd}_k \rightarrow \mathbf{Sets} $</p>
<p>In particular, we are interested to associated to any {tex]k $-algebra $A $ its <strong>representation functor</strong> :</p>
<p>$\mathbf{rep}(A)~:~\mathbf{Coalg}^{fd}_k \rightarrow \mathbf{Sets} \qquad C \mapsto Alg_k(A,C^*) $</p>
<p>This may look strange at first sight, but $C^* $ is a finite dimensional algebra and any $n $-dimensional representation of $A $ is an algebra map $A \rightarrow M_n(k) $ and we take $C $ to be the dual coalgebra of this image.</p>
<p>Kontsevich and Soibelman proved that every noncommutative thin scheme $\mathbb{X} $ is representable by a $k $-coalgebra. That is, there exists a unique coalgebra $C_{\mathbb{X}} $ (which they call the coalgebra of &#8216;distributions&#8217; of $\mathbb{X} $) such that for every finite dimensional $k $-algebra $B $ we have</p>
<p>$\mathbb{X}(B) = Coalg_k(B^*,C_{\mathbb{X}}) $</p>
<p>In the case of interest to us, that is for the functor $\mathbf{rep}(A) $ the coalgebra of distributions is <strong>Kostant&#8217;s dual coalgebra</strong> $A^o $. This is the not the full linear dual of $A $ but contains only those linear functionals on $A $ which factor through a finite dimensional quotient.</p>
<p>So? You&#8217;ve exchanged an algebra $A $ for some coalgebra $A^o $, but where&#8217;s the geometry in all this? Well, let&#8217;s look at the commutative case. Suppose $A= \mathbb{C}[X] $ is the coordinate ring of a smooth affine variety $X $, then its dual coalgebra looks like</p>
<p>$\mathbb{C}[X]^o = \oplus_{x \in X} U(T_x(X)) $</p>
<p>the direct sum of all universal (co)algebras of tangent spaces at points $x \in X $. But how do we get the variety out of this? Well, any coalgebra has a <strong>coradical</strong> (being the sun of all simple subcoalgebras) and in the case just mentioned we have</p>
<p>$corad(\mathbb{C}[X]^o) = \oplus_{x \in X} \mathbb{C} e_x $</p>
<p>so every point corresponds to a unique simple component of the coradical. In the general case, the coradical of the dual coalgebra $A^o $ is the direct sum of all simple finite dimensional representations of $A $. That is, the direct summands of the coalgebra give us a noncommutative variety whose points are the simple representations, and the remainder of the coalgebra of distributions accounts for infinitesimal information on these points (as do the tangent spaces in the commutative case).</p>
<p>In fact, it was a surprise to me that one can describe the dual coalgebra quite explicitly, and that $A_{\infty} $-structures make their appearance quite naturally. See <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0805.2377">this paper</a> if you&#8217;re in for the details on this.</p>
<p>That settles the problem of what we mean by the noncommutative variety associated to a complex algebra. But what about the integral case? In the above, we used extensively the theory of Kostant-duality which works only for algebras over fields&#8230;</p>
<p>Well, not quite. In the case of $\mathbb{Z} $ (or more general, of Dedekind domains) one can repeat Kostant&#8217;s proof word for word provided one takes as the definition of the dual $\mathbb{Z} $-coalgebra<br />
of an algebra (which is $\mathbb{Z} $-torsion free)</p>
<p>$A^o = &#123; f~:~A \rightarrow \mathbb{Z}~:~A/Ker(f)~\text{is finitely generated and torsion free}~&#125; $</p>
<p>(over general rings there may be also variants of this duality, as in <a href="http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;id=u0slIpdBjYUC&amp;dq=Joyal+Street+Quantum+groups+current+algebra&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=web&amp;ots=YnWkAV4k9k&amp;sig=p9DpIEr7Ya4ssfjXlWWFDI3GndE&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ct=result">Street&#8217;s book an Quantum groups</a>). Probably lots of people have come up with this, but the only explicit reference I have is to the <a href="http://www.math.ua.ac.be/~lebruyn/LeBruyn1981a.pdf">first paper I&#8217;ve ever written</a>. So, also for algebras over $\mathbb{Z} $ we can define a suitable noncommutative integral scheme (the coradical approach accounts only for the maximal ideals rather than all primes, but somehow this is implicit in all approaches as we consider only <strong>thin</strong> schemes).</p>
<p>Fine! So, we can make sense of the noncommutative geometrical objects corresponding to the group-algebras $\mathbb{C} \Gamma $ and $\mathbb{Z} \Gamma $ where $\Gamma = PSL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $ is the modular group (the algebras corresponding to the $G \mapsto G_2 \times G_3 $-functor). But, what might be the points of the noncommutative scheme corresponding to $\mathbb{F}_1 \Gamma $???</p>
<p>Well, let&#8217;s continue the path cut out before. &#8220;Points&#8221; should correspond to finite dimensional &#8220;simple representations&#8221;. Hence, what are the finite dimensional simple $\mathbb{F}_1 $-representations of $\Gamma $? (Or, for that matter, of any group $G $)</p>
<p>Here we come back to <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/fun/index.php/f_un-and-group-representations.html">Javier&#8217;s post on this</a> : a finite dimensional $\mathbb{F}_1 $-vectorspace is a finite set. A $\Gamma $-representation on this set (of n-elements) is a group-morphism</p>
<p>$\Gamma \rightarrow GL_n(\mathbb{F}_1) = S_n $</p>
<p>hence it gives a permutation representation of $\Gamma $ on this set. But then, if finite dimensional $\mathbb{F}_1 $-representations of $\Gamma $ are the finite permutation representations, then the <strong>simple</strong> ones are the <strong>transitive</strong> permutation representations. That is, the points of the noncommutative scheme corresponding to $\mathbb{F}_1 \Gamma $ are the conjugacy classes of subgroups $H \subset \Gamma $ such that $\Gamma/H $ is finite. But these are exactly the modular dessins d&#8217;enfants introduced by Grothendieck as I explained a while back elsewhere (see for example <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/modular-quilts-and-cuboid-tree-diagrams.html">this post</a> and others in the same series).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/noncommutative-f_un-geometry-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>F_un with Manin</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/f_un-with-manin/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/f_un-with-manin/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2008 16:26:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[absolute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arxiv]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[coalgebras]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kontsevich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Manin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[non-commutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noncommutative]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=446</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Amidst all LHC-noise, Yuri I. Manin arXived today an interesting paper Cyclotomy and analytic geometry over $\mathbb{F}_1 $. The paper gives a nice survey of&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/manin.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;" hspace=10 > Amidst all LHC-noise, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yuri_Manin">Yuri I. Manin</a> arXived today an interesting paper <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0809.1564">Cyclotomy and analytic geometry over $\mathbb{F}_1 $</a>.</p>
<p>The paper gives a nice survey of the existent literature and focusses on the crucial role of roots of unity in the algebraic geometry over the non-existent field with one element $\mathbb{F}_1 $ (in French called &#8216;F-un&#8217;). I have tried to do a couple of <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/the-f_un-folklore.html">posts</a> on F-un some time ago but now realize, reading Manin&#8217;s paper, I may have given up way too soon&#8230;</p>
<p>At several places in the paper, Manin hints at a possible <strong>noncommutative geometry</strong> over $\mathbb{F}_1 $ :</p>
<blockquote><p>This is the appropriate place to stress that in a wider context of <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/math.AG/0509684">Toen-Vaqui &#8216;Au-dessous de Spec Z&#8217;</a>, or eventually in noncommutative $\mathbb{F}_1 $-geometry, teh spectrum of $\mathbb{F}_1 $ loses its privileged position as a final object of a geometric category. For example, in noncommutative geometry, or in an appropriate category of stacks, the quotient of this spectrum modulo the trivial action of a group must lie below this spectrum. </p>
<p>Soule&#8217;s algebras $\mathcal{A}_X $ are a very important element of the structure, in particular, because they form a bridge to Arakelov geometry. Soule uses concrete choices of them in order to produce &#8216;just right&#8217; supply of morphisms, without a priori constraining these choices formally. In this work, we use these algebras and their version also to pave a way to the analytic (and possibly non-commutative) geometry over $\mathbb{F}_1 $.</p></blockquote>
<p>Back when I was writing the first batch of F-un posts, I briefly contemplated the possibility of a noncommutative geometry over $\mathbb{F}_1 $, but quickly forgot about it because I thought it would be forced to reduce to commutative geometry.</p>
<p>Here is the quick argument : noncommutative geometry is really the study of coalgebras (see for example <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0805.2377">my paper</a> or if you prefer more trustworthy sources the <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/math/0606241v2">Kontsevich-Soibelman paper</a>). Now, unless I made a mistake, I think all coalgebras over $\mathbb{F}_1 $ must be co-commutative (even group-like), so reducing to commutative geometry.</p>
<p>Surely, I&#8217;m missing something&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/f_un-with-manin/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>what does the monster see?</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/what-does-the-monster-see/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/what-does-the-monster-see/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2008 18:12:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arxiv]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brauer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cuntz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hyperbolic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Klein]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kontsevich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[monster]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noncommutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[permutation representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quillen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[quivers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[representations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Riemann]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=440</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Monster is the largest of the 26 sporadic simple groups and has order 808 017 424 794 512 875 886 459 904 961 710&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monster_group">Monster</a> is the largest of the 26 sporadic simple groups and has order</p>
<p>808 017 424 794 512 875 886 459 904 961 710 757 005 754 368 000 000 000</p>
<p>= 2^46 3^20 5^9 7^6 11^2 13^3 17 19 23 29 31 41 47 59 71.</p>
<p>It is not so much the size of its order that makes it hard to do actual calculations in the monster, but rather the dimensions of its smallest non-trivial irreducible representations (196 883 for the smallest, 21 296 876 for the next one, and so on).</p>
<p>In characteristic two there is an irreducible representation of one dimension less (196 882) which appears to be of great use to obtain information. For example, Robert Wilson used it to prove that <a href="http://web.mat.bham.ac.uk/R.A.Wilson/pubs/MHurwitz.ps">The Monster is a Hurwitz group</a>. This means that the Monster is generated by two elements g and h satisfying the relations</p>
<p>$g^2 = h^3 = (gh)^7 = 1 $</p>
<p>Geometrically, this implies that the Monster is the automorphism group of a Riemann surface of genus g satisfying the Hurwitz bound 84(g-1)=#Monster. That is,</p>
<p>g=9619255057077534236743570297163223297687552000000001=42151199 * 293998543 * 776222682603828537142813968452830193</p>
<p>Or, in analogy with the <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/the-buckyball-curve.html">Klein quartic</a> which can be constructed from 24 heptagons in the tiling of the hyperbolic plane, there is a finite region of the hyperbolic plane, tiled with heptagons, from which we can construct this monster curve by gluing the boundary is a specific way so that we get a Riemann surface with exactly 9619255057077534236743570297163223297687552000000001 holes. This finite part of the hyperbolic tiling (consisting of #Monster/7 heptagons) we&#8217;ll call the <strong>empire of the monster</strong> and we&#8217;d love to describe it in more detail.</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/whatdoesmonstersee.jpg"><br />
</center></p>
<p>Look at the half-edges of all the heptagons in the empire (the picture above learns that every edge in cut in two by a blue geodesic). They are exactly #Monster such half-edges and they form a <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/the-best-rejected-proposal-ever.html">dessin d&#8217;enfant</a> for the monster-curve.</p>
<p>If we label these half-edges by the elements of the Monster, then multiplication by g in the monster interchanges the two half-edges making up a heptagonal edge in the empire and multiplication by h in the monster takes a half-edge to the one encountered first by going counter-clockwise in the vertex of the heptagonal tiling. Because g and h generated the Monster, the dessin of the empire is just a concrete realization of the monster.</p>
<p>Because g is of order two and h is of order three, the two permutations they determine on the dessin, gives a group epimorphism $C_2 \ast C_3 = PSL_2(\mathbb{Z}) \rightarrow \mathbb{M} $ from the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modular_group">modular group</a> $PSL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $ onto the Monster-group.</p>
<p>In noncommutative geometry, the group-algebra of the modular group $\mathbb{C} PSL_2 $ can be interpreted as the coordinate ring of a noncommutative manifold (because it is formally smooth in the sense of <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/math/9812158">Kontsevich-Rosenberg</a> or Cuntz-Quillen) and the group-algebra of the Monster $\mathbb{C} \mathbb{M} $ itself corresponds in this picture to a finite collection of &#8216;points&#8217; on the manifold. Using this geometric viewpoint we can now ask the question  <strong>What does the Monster see of the modular group?</strong></p>
<p>To make sense of this question, let us first consider the commutative equivalent : what does a point P see of a commutative variety X?</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/neighborhoods.jpg" ><br />
</center></p>
<p>Evaluation of polynomial functions in P gives us an algebra epimorphism $\mathbb{C}[X] \rightarrow \mathbb{C} $ from the coordinate ring of the variety $\mathbb{C}[X] $ onto $\mathbb{C} $ and the kernel of this map is the maximal ideal $\mathfrak{m}_P $ of<br />
 $\mathbb{C}[X] $ consisting of all functions vanishing in P.</p>
<p>Equivalently, we can view the point $P= \mathbf{spec}~\mathbb{C}[X]/\mathfrak{m}_P $ as the scheme corresponding to the quotient $\mathbb{C}[X]/\mathfrak{m}_P $. Call this the 0-th formal neighborhood of the point P.</p>
<p>This sounds pretty useless, but let us now consider higher-order formal neighborhoods. Call the affine scheme $\mathbf{spec}~\mathbb{C}[X]/\mathfrak{m}_P^{n+1} $ the n-th forml neighborhood of P, then the first neighborhood, that is with coordinate ring $\mathbb{C}[X]/\mathfrak{m}_P^2 $ gives us tangent-information. Alternatively, it gives the best linear approximation of functions near P.<br />
The second neighborhood $\mathbb{C}[X]/\mathfrak{m}_P^3 $ gives us the best quadratic approximation of function near P, etc. etc.</p>
<p>These successive quotients by powers of the maximal ideal $\mathfrak{m}_P $ form a system of algebra epimorphisms</p>
<p>$\ldots \frac{\mathbb{C}[X]}{\mathfrak{m}_P^{n+1}} \rightarrow \frac{\mathbb{C}[X]}{\mathfrak{m}_P^{n}} \rightarrow \ldots \ldots \rightarrow \frac{\mathbb{C}[X]}{\mathfrak{m}_P^{2}} \rightarrow \frac{\mathbb{C}[X]}{\mathfrak{m}_P} = \mathbb{C} $</p>
<p>and its inverse limit $\underset{\leftarrow}{lim}~\frac{\mathbb{C}[X]}{\mathfrak{m}_P^{n}} = \hat{\mathcal{O}}_{X,P} $ is the completion of the local ring in P and contains all the infinitesimal information (to any order) of the variety X in a neighborhood of P. That is, this completion $\hat{\mathcal{O}}_{X,P} $ contains <strong>all information that P can see of the variety X</strong>.</p>
<p>In case P is a smooth point of X, then X is a manifold in a neighborhood of P and then this completion<br />
$\hat{\mathcal{O}}_{X,P} $ is isomorphic to the algebra of formal power series $\mathbb{C}[[ x_1,x_2,\ldots,x_d ]] $ where the $x_i $ form a local system of coordinates for the manifold X near P.</p>
<p>Right, after this lengthy recollection, back to our question <strong>what does the monster see of the modular group?</strong> Well, we have an algebra epimorphism</p>
<p>$\pi~:~\mathbb{C} PSL_2(\mathbb{Z}) \rightarrow \mathbb{C} \mathbb{M} $</p>
<p>and in analogy with the commutative case, all information the Monster can gain from the modular group is contained in the $\mathfrak{m} $-adic completion</p>
<p>$\widehat{\mathbb{C} PSL_2(\mathbb{Z})}_{\mathfrak{m}} = \underset{\leftarrow}{lim}~\frac{\mathbb{C} PSL_2(\mathbb{Z})}{\mathfrak{m}^n} $</p>
<p>where $\mathfrak{m} $ is the kernel of the epimorphism $\pi $ sending the two free generators of the modular group $PSL_2(\mathbb{Z}) = C_2 \ast C_3 $ to the permutations g and h determined by the dessin of the pentagonal tiling of the Monster&#8217;s empire.</p>
<p>As it is a hopeless task to determine the Monster-empire explicitly, it seems even more hopeless to determine the kernel $\mathfrak{m} $ let alone the completed algebra&#8230; But, (surprise) we can compute $\widehat{\mathbb{C} PSL_2(\mathbb{Z})}_{\mathfrak{m}} $ as explicitly as in the commutative case we have $\hat{\mathcal{O}}_{X,P} \simeq \mathbb{C}[[ x_1,x_2,\ldots,x_d ]] $ for a point P on a manifold X.</p>
<p>Here the details : the quotient $\mathfrak{m}/\mathfrak{m}^2 $ has a natural structure of $\mathbb{C} \mathbb{M} $-bimodule. The group-algebra of the monster is a semi-simple algebra, that is, a direct sum of full matrix-algebras of sizes corresponding to the dimensions of the irreducible monster-representations. That is,</p>
<p>$\mathbb{C} \mathbb{M} \simeq \mathbb{C} \oplus M_{196883}(\mathbb{C}) \oplus M_{21296876}(\mathbb{C}) \oplus \ldots \ldots \oplus M_{258823477531055064045234375}(\mathbb{C}) $</p>
<p>with exactly 194 components (the number of irreducible Monster-representations). For any $\mathbb{C} \mathbb{M} $-bimodule $M $ one can form the tensor-algebra</p>
<p>$T_{\mathbb{C} \mathbb{M}}(M) = \mathbb{C} \mathbb{M} \oplus M \oplus (M \otimes_{\mathbb{C} \mathbb{M}} M) \oplus (M \otimes_{\mathbb{C} \mathbb{M}} M \otimes_{\mathbb{C} \mathbb{M}} M) \oplus \ldots \ldots $</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/cuntz.jpg"><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/Quillen.jpg"><br />
</center></p>
<p>and applying the formal neighborhood theorem for formally smooth algebras (such as $\mathbb{C} PSL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $) due to <a href="http://wwwmath.uni-muenster.de/u/cuntz/cuntz.html">Joachim Cuntz</a> (left) and <a href="http://www-groups.dcs.st-and.ac.uk/~history/Biographies/Quillen.html">Daniel Quillen</a> (right) we have an isomorphism of algebras</p>
<p>$\widehat{\mathbb{C} PSL_2(\mathbb{Z})}_{\mathfrak{m}} \simeq \widehat{T_{\mathbb{C} \mathbb{M}}(\mathfrak{m}/\mathfrak{m}^2)} $</p>
<p>where the right-hand side is the completion of the tensor-algebra (at the unique graded maximal ideal) of the $\mathbb{C} \mathbb{M} $-bimodule $\mathfrak{m}/\mathfrak{m}^2 $, so we&#8217;d better describe this bimodule explicitly.</p>
<p>Okay, so what&#8217;s a bimodule over a semisimple algebra of the form $S=M_{n_1}(\mathbb{C}) \oplus \ldots \oplus M_{n_k}(\mathbb{C}) $? Well,  a <strong>simple</strong> S-bimodule must be either (1) a factor $M_{n_i}(\mathbb{C}) $ with all other factors acting trivially or (2) the full space of rectangular matrices $M_{n_i \times n_j}(\mathbb{C}) $ with the factor $M_{n_i}(\mathbb{C}) $ acting on the left, $M_{n_j}(\mathbb{C}) $ acting on the right and all other factors acting trivially.</p>
<p>That is, any S-bimodule can be represented by a quiver (that is a directed graph) on k vertices (the number of matrix components) with a loop in vertex i corresponding to each simple factor of type (1) and a directed arrow from i to j corresponding to every simple factor of type (2).</p>
<p>That is, for the Monster, the bimodule $\mathfrak{m}/\mathfrak{m}^2 $ is represented by a quiver on 194 vertices and now we only have to determine how many loops and arrows there are at or between vertices.</p>
<p>Using Morita equivalences and standard representation theory of quivers it isn&#8217;t exactly rocket science to determine that the number of arrows between the vertices corresponding to the irreducible Monster-representations $S_i $ and $S_j $ is equal to</p>
<p>$dim_{\mathbb{C}}~Ext^1_{\mathbb{C} PSL_2(\mathbb{Z})}(S_i,S_j)-\delta_{ij} $</p>
<p>Now, I&#8217;ve been wasting a lot of time already here explaining what representations of the modular group have to do with quivers (see for example <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/why-nag-2.html">here</a> or some other posts in the same series) and for quiver-representations we all know how to compute Ext-dimensions in terms of the Euler-form applied to the dimension vectors.</p>
<p>Right, so for every Monster-irreducible $S_i $ we have to determine the corresponding dimension-vector $~(a_1,a_2;b_1,b_2,b_3) $ for the quiver</p>
<p>$\xymatrix{ &amp; &amp; &amp; &amp;<br />
\vtx{b_1} \\ \vtx{a_1} \ar[rrrru]^(.3){B_{11}} \ar[rrrrd]^(.3){B_{21}}<br />
\ar[rrrrddd]_(.2){B_{31}} &amp; &amp; &amp; &amp; \\ &amp; &amp; &amp; &amp; \vtx{b_2} \\ \vtx{a_2}<br />
\ar[rrrruuu]_(.7){B_{12}} \ar[rrrru]_(.7){B_{22}}<br />
\ar[rrrrd]_(.7){B_{23}} &amp; &amp; &amp; &amp; \\ &amp; &amp; &amp; &amp; \vtx{b_3}} $</p>
<p>Now the dimensions $a_i $ are the dimensions of the +/-1 eigenspaces for the order 2 element g in the representation and the $b_i $ are the dimensions of the eigenspaces for the order 3 element h. So, we have to determine to which conjugacy classes g and h belong, and from Wilson&#8217;s paper mentioned above these are classes 2B and 3B in standard <a href="http://brauer.maths.qmul.ac.uk/Atlas/v3/spor/M/">Atlas notation</a>.</p>
<p>So, for each of the 194 irreducible Monster-representations we look up the character values at 2B and 3B (see below for the first batch of those) and these together with the dimensions determine the dimension vector $~(a_1,a_2;b_1,b_2,b_3) $.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/seemonsterchars.jpg"></p>
<p>For example take the 196883-dimensional irreducible. Its 2B-character is 275 and the 3B-character is 53. So we are looking for a dimension vector such that $a_1+a_2=196883, a_1-275=a_2 $ and $b_1+b_2+b_3=196883, b_1-53=b_2=b_3 $ giving us for that representation the dimension vector of the quiver above $~(98579,98304,65663,65610,65610) $.</p>
<p>Okay, so for each of the 194 irreducibles $S_i $ we have determined a dimension vector $~(a_1(i),a_2(i);b_1(i),b_2(i),b_3(i)) $, then standard quiver-representation theory asserts that the number of loops in the vertex corresponding to $S_i $ is equal to</p>
<p>$dim(S_i)^2 + 1 &#8211; a_1(i)^2-a_2(i)^2-b_1(i)^2-b_2(i)^2-b_3(i)^2 $</p>
<p>and that the number of arrows from vertex $S_i $ to vertex $S_j $ is equal to</p>
<p>$dim(S_i)dim(S_j) &#8211; a_1(i)a_1(j)-a_2(i)a_2(j)-b_1(i)b_1(j)-b_2(i)b_2(j)-b_3(i)b_3(j) $</p>
<p>This data then determines completely the $\mathbb{C} \mathbb{M} $-bimodule $\mathfrak{m}/\mathfrak{m}^2 $ and hence the structure of the completion $\widehat{\mathbb{C} PSL_2}_{\mathfrak{m}} $ containing all information the Monster can gain from the modular group.</p>
<p>But then, one doesn&#8217;t have to go for the full regular representation of the Monster. Any faithful permutation representation will do, so we might as well go for the one of minimal dimension.</p>
<p>That one is known to correspond to the largest maximal subgroup of the Monster which is known to be a two-fold extension $2.\mathbb{B} $ of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baby_Monster_group">Baby-Monster</a>. The corresponding permutation representation is of dimension 97239461142009186000 and decomposes into Monster-irreducibles</p>
<p>$S_1 \oplus S_2 \oplus S_4 \oplus S_5 \oplus S_9 \oplus S_{14} \oplus S_{21} \oplus S_{34} \oplus S_{35} $</p>
<p>(in standard Atlas-ordering) and hence repeating the arguments above we get a quiver on just 9 vertices! The actual numbers of loops and arrows (I forgot to mention this, but the quivers obtained are actually symmetric) obtained were found after laborious computations mentioned in <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/monstrous-frustrations.html">this post</a> and the details I&#8217;ll make avalable <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/monsterquiver2.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>Anyone who can spot a relation between the numbers obtained and any other part of mathematics will obtain quantities of genuine (ie. non-Inbev) Belgian beer&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/what-does-the-monster-see/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>recap and outlook</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/recap-and-outlook/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/recap-and-outlook/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 May 2007 08:08:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Grothendieck]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[groups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kontsevich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mathieu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noncommutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[permutation representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[profinite]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[quivers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[representations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Riemann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[simples]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=297</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[After a lengthy spring-break, let us continue with our course on noncommutative geometry and $SL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $-representations. Last time, we have explained Grothendiecks mantra that all&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After a lengthy spring-break, let us continue with our course on noncommutative geometry and $SL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $-representations. Last time, we have explained Grothendiecks mantra that <strong>all algebraic curves defined over number fields are contained in the profinite compactification<br />
$\widehat{SL&#95;2(\mathbb{Z})} = \underset{\leftarrow}{lim}~SL&#95;2(\mathbb{Z})/N $ of the modular group $SL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $ and in the knowledge of a certain subgroup G of its group of outer automorphisms</strong>. In particular we have seen that many curves defined over the algebraic numbers $\overline{\mathbb{Q}} $ correspond to permutation representations of $SL&#95;2(\mathbb{Z}) $. The profinite compactification $\widehat{SL&#95;2}=\widehat{SL_2(\mathbb{Z})} $ is a continuous group, so it makes sense to consider its <strong>continuous</strong> n-dimensional representations $\mathbf{rep}&#95;n^c~\widehat{SL&#95;2} $ Such representations are known to have a finite image in $GL&#95;n(\mathbb{C}) $ and therefore we get an embedding $\mathbf{rep}&#95;n^c~\widehat{SL&#95;2} \hookrightarrow \mathbf{rep}&#95;n^{ss}~SL&#95;n(\mathbb{C}) $ into all n-dimensional (semi-simple) representations of $SL&#95;2(\mathbb{Z}) $. We consider such semi-simple points as <strong>classical objects</strong> as they are determined by &#8211; curves defined over $\overline{Q} $ &#8211; representations of (sporadic) finite groups &#8211; modlart data of fusion rings in RCTF &#8211; etc&#8230; To get a feel for the distinction between these continuous representations of the cofinite completion and all representations, consider the case of $\hat{\mathbb{Z}} = \underset{\leftarrow}{lim}~\mathbb{Z}/n \mathbb{Z} $. Its one-dimensional continuous representations are determined by roots of unity, whereas all one-dimensional (necessarily simple) representations of $\mathbb{Z}=C&#95;{\infty} $ are determined by all elements of $\mathbb{C} $. Hence, the image of $\mathbf{rep}&#95;1^c~\hat{\mathbb{Z}} \hookrightarrow \mathbf{rep}&#95;1~C&#95;{\infty} $ is contained in the unit circle</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/unitcircle.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>and though these points are very special there are enough of them (technically, they form a Zariski dense subset of all representations). Our aim will be twofold : (1) when viewing a classical object as a representation of $SL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $ we can define its <strong>modular content</strong> (which will be the noncommutative tangent space in this classical point to the noncommutative manifold of $SL&#95;2(\mathbb{Z}) $). In this way we will associate noncommutative gadgets to our classical object (such as orders in central simple algebras, infinite dimensional Lie algebras, noncommutative potentials etc. etc.) which give us new tools to study these objects. (2) conversely, as we control the tangentspaces in these special points, they will allow us to determine other $SL&#95;2(\mathbb{Z}) $-representations and as we vary over all classical objects, we hope to get ALL finite dimensional modular representations. I agree this may all sound rather vague, so let me give one example we will work out in full detail later on. <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/?p=297">Remember</a> that one can reconstruct the sporadic simple Mathieu group $M_{24} $ from the dessin d&#8217;enfant</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/mathieuZvonkin.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<dl>
<dt>This</dt>
<dt>dessin determines a 24-dimensional permutation representation (of</dt>
<dt>$M&#95;{24} $ as well of $SL&#95;2(\mathbb{Z}) $) which</dt>
<dt>decomposes as the direct sum of the trivial representation and a simple</dt>
<dt>23-dimensional representation. We will see that the noncommutative</dt>
<dt>tangent space in a semi-simple representation of</dt>
<dt>$SL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $ is determined by a <strong>quiver</strong> (that is, an</dt>
<dt>oriented graph) on as many vertices as there are non-isomorphic simple</dt>
<dt>components. In this special case we get the quiver on two points</dt>
<dt>$\xymatrix{\vtx{} \ar@/^2ex/[rr] &amp; &amp; \vtx{} \ar@/^2ex/[ll]</dt>
<dt>\ar@{=>}@(ur,dr)^{96} } $ with just one arrow in each direction</dt>
<dt>between the vertices and 96 loops in the second vertex. To the</dt>
<dt>experienced tangent space-reader this picture (and in particular that</dt>
<dt>there is a unique cycle between the two vertices) tells the remarkable</dt>
<dt>fact that there is **a distinguished one-parameter family of</dt>
<dt>24-dimensional simple modular representations degenerating to the</dt>
<dt>permutation representation of the largest Mathieu-group**. Phrased</dt>
<dt>differently, there is a specific noncommutative modular Riemann surface</dt>
<dt>associated to $M_{24} $, which is a new object (at least as far</dt>
<dt>as I&#8217;m aware) associated to this most remarkable of sporadic groups.</dt>
<dt>Conversely, from the matrix-representation of the 24-dimensional</dt>
<dt>permutation representation of $M_{24} $ we obtain representants</dt>
<dt>of all of this one-parameter family of simple</dt>
<dt>$SL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $-representations to which we can then perform</dt>
<dt>noncommutative flow-tricks to get a Zariski dense set of all</dt>
<dt>24-dimensional simples lying in the same component. (Btw. there are</dt>
<dt>also such noncommutative Riemann surfaces associated to the other</dt>
<dt>sporadic Mathieu groups, though not to the other sporadics&#8230;) So this</dt>
<dt>is what we will be doing in the upcoming posts (10) : explain what a</dt>
<dt>noncommutative tangent space is and what it has to do with quivers (11)</dt>
<dd>what is the noncommutative manifold of $SL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $? and what is its connection with the Kontsevich-Soibelman coalgebra? (12)</dd>
<dd>is there a noncommutative compactification of $SL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $? (and other arithmetical groups) (13) : how does one calculate the noncommutative curves associated to the Mathieu groups? (14) : whatever comes next&#8230; (if anything).</dd>
</dl>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/recap-and-outlook/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>noncommutative geometry : a medieval science?</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/noncommutative-geometry-a-medieval-science/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/noncommutative-geometry-a-medieval-science/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2007 09:29:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arxiv]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Connes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kontsevich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marcolli]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noncommutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[representations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=203</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[According to a science article in the New York Times, archeologists have discovered &#8220;signs of advanced math&#8221; in medieval mosaics. An example of a quasi-crystalline&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>According to a science article in the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/27/science/27math.html?_r=1&amp;oref=slogin">New York Times</a>, archeologists have discovered &#8220;signs of advanced math&#8221; in medieval mosaics. An example of a quasi-crystalline Penrose pattern was found at the Darb-i Imam shrine in Isfahan, Iran.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/penrose.jpg" /></p>
<p>&#8220;A new study shows that the Islamic pattern-making process, far more intricate than the laying of one‚Äôs bathroom floor, appears to have involved an advanced math of quasi crystals, which was not understood by modern scientists until three decades ago.  Two years ago, Peter J. Lu, a doctoral student in physics at Harvard University, was transfixed by the geometric pattern on a wall in Uzbekistan. It reminded him of what mathematicians call quasi-crystalline designs. These were demonstrated in the early 1970s by Roger Penrose, a mathematician and cosmologist at the University of Oxford.  Mr. Lu set about examining pictures of other tile mosaics from Afghanistan, Iran, Iraq and Turkey, working with Paul J. Steinhardt, a Princeton cosmologist who is an authority on quasi crystals and had been Mr. Lu&#8217;s undergraduate adviser. &#8221;</p>
<p>Penrose tilings are one of the motivating examples of Alain Connes&#8217; <a href="ftp://ftp.alainconnes.org/book94bigpdf.pdf">book</a> as there is a $C^* $-algebra associated to it. In fact, the algebra is AF ( a limit of semi-simple finite dimensional algebras) so is even a formally smooth algebra in Kontsevichian noncommutative geometry (it is remarkable how quickly one gets used to silly terminology&#8230;). However, the Penrose algebra is simple, so rather useless from the point of view of finite dimensional representations&#8230; Still, Connesian noncommutative geometry may be a recent incarnation of the medieval Tehran program (pun intended).  Thanks to <a href="http://easwaran.livejournal.com/431416.html">easwaran</a> for the link (via Technorati).</p>
<p>Added, March 1 : I haven&#8217;t looked at the Connes-Marcolli paper <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/abs/math.QA/0601054">A walk in the noncommutative garden</a> for a while but now that I do, I see that they mentioned the above already at the end of their section on Tilings (page 32). They also include clearer pictures.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/ConnesMarcolli1.jpg" /><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/ConnesMarcolli2.jpg" /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/noncommutative-geometry-a-medieval-science/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>noncommutative bookmarks</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/noncommutative-bookmarks/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/noncommutative-bookmarks/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2007 09:17:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[anabelian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Connes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[differential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kontsevich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noncommutative]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=202</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[At last, some excitement about noncommutative geometry in the blogosphere. From what I deduce from reading the first posts, Arup Pal set up a new&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At<br />
last, some excitement about noncommutative geometry in the blogosphere.
</p>
</p>
<p>From what I deduce from reading the first posts, <a href="http://www.isid.ac.in/~arup/">Arup Pal</a> set up a new blog<br />
called <a href="http://noncommutativegeometry.blogspot.com/">Noncommutative<br />
Geometry</a> and subsequently handed it over to <a href="http://www.math.uwo.ca/~masoud/cv/">Masoud Khalkhali</a> who then<br />
got Alain Connes to post on it who, in turn, is asking people to submit<br />
posts, such as todays post by <a href="http://www.math.ohio-state.edu/~goss/">David Goss</a>. </p>
<p>Somehow, most people refer to the Noncommutative Geometry blog as<br />
&#8220;Alain Connes&#8217; blog&#8221; (for example  <a href="http://doctorgero.livejournal.com/32369.html">Doctor Gero</a>, <a href="http://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=526">Not Even<br />
Wrong</a>, <a href="http://golem.ph.utexas.edu/category/2007/02/how_to_write_mathematics_badly.html">the n-category cafe</a> and<br />
possibly many others). </p>
<p>David Corfield <a href="http://golem.ph.utexas.edu/category/2007/02/noncommutative_geometry_blog.html">over at the n-category cafe</a> stops<br />
short of suggesting to rename (by analogy) NeverEndingBooks into<br />
Kontsevich&#8217;s blog</p>
<blockquote><p>A new blog Noncommutative Geometry<br />
has begun, which appears to be of the Connesian variety. (Connes himself<br />
has already commented there.) We mentioned a couple of weeks ago that<br />
there are different flavours of noncommutative geometry. The<br />
Kontsevichian variety, nongeometry, finds its blog voice in Lieven Le<br />
Bruyn‚Äôs NeverEndingBooks. It would be interesting to see some<br />
interaction.</p></blockquote>
<p>I don&#8217;t think I will opt for a dialectic<br />
response to the <a href="http://noncommutativegeometry.blogspot.com/index.html">Noncommutative Geometry Blog</a>, although I realize this would result<br />
in more enjoyable reading for some of you&#8230;</p>
<p>For starters,<br />
I&#8217;ve signed up to another flagship of noncommutative<br />
_differential_ geometry : <a href="http://www.noncommutativegeometry.net/">noncommutativegeometry.net</a>, though it is unclear to me what action (if any) is<br />
going on over there.</p>
<p>Further, I plan to move my talks at the <a href="http://www.math.ua.ac.be/algebra/seminar.php">master class<br />
noncommutative geometry</a> to the virtual lecture room of this blog,<br />
hoping to get the desired interaction. We&#8217;ll start later this week and<br />
the pace will be pretty easy going.  A tentative title might be<br />
&#8220;Anabelian versus Noncommutative Geometry&#8221;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/noncommutative-bookmarks/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>2006 paper nominees</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/2006-paper-nominees/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/2006-paper-nominees/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2006 08:42:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Calabi-Yau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Galois]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Grothendieck]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kontsevich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[moduli]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[non-commutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noncommutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Riemann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[superpotential]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=227</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here are my nominees for the 2006 paper of the year award in mathematics &#38; mathematical physics : in math.RA : math.RA/0606241 : Notes on&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here are<br />
my nominees for the 2006 paper of the year award in mathematics &amp;<br />
mathematical physics :    <strong>in math.RA : math.RA/0606241</strong><br />
: <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/abs/math.RA/0606241">Notes on A-infinity<br />
algebras, A-infinity categories and non-commutative geometry. I</a> by<br />
<a href="http://www.arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Kontsevich_M/0/1/0/all/0/1"><br />
Maxim Kontsevich</a> and <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/find/math/1/au:+Soibelman_Y/0/1/0/all/0/1"><br />
Yan Soibelman</a>. Here is the abstract :   </p>
<blockquote><p> We develop<br />
geometric approach to A-infinity algebras and A-infinity categories<br />
based on the notion of formal scheme in the category of graded vector<br />
spaces. Geometric approach clarifies several questions, e.g. the notion<br />
of homological unit or A-infinity structure on A-infinity functors. We<br />
discuss Hochschild complexes of A-infinity algebras from geometric point<br />
of view. The paper contains homological versions of the notions of<br />
properness and smoothness of projective varieties as well as the<br />
non-commutative version of Hodge-to-de Rham degeneration conjecture. We<br />
also discuss a generalization of Deligne&#8217;s conjecture which includes<br />
both Hochschild chains and cochains. We conclude the paper with the<br />
description of an action of the PROP of singular chains of the<br />
topological PROP of 2-dimensional surfaces on the Hochschild chain<br />
complex of an A-infinity algebra with the scalar product (this action is<br />
more or less equivalent to the structure of 2-dimensional Topological<br />
Field Theory associated with an &#8220;abstract&#8221; Calabi-Yau<br />
manifold). </p></blockquote>
<p>   <strong>why ?</strong> : Because this paper<br />
probably gives the correct geometric object associated to a<br />
non-commutative algebra (a huge coalgebra) and consequently the right<br />
definition of a map between noncommutative affine schemes. In a <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/2006/09/11/coalgebras-and-non-geometry-3/">previous post </a> (and its predecessors) I&#8217;ve<br />
tried to explain how this links up with my own interpretation and since<br />
then I&#8217;ve thought more about this, but that will have to wait for<br />
another time.    <strong>in hep-th : hep-th/0611082</strong> : <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/abs/hep-th/0611082">Children&#8217;s Drawings From<br />
Seiberg-Witten Curves</a> by  Sujay K. Ashok, Freddy Cachazo, Eleonora<br />
Dell&#8217;Aquila. Here is the abstract :   </p>
<blockquote><p> We consider N=2<br />
supersymmetric gauge theories perturbed by tree level superpotential<br />
terms near isolated singular points in the Coulomb moduli space. We<br />
identify the Seiberg-Witten curve at these points with polynomial<br />
equations used to construct what Grothendieck called &#8220;dessins<br />
d&#8217;enfants&#8221; or &#8220;children&#8217;s drawings&#8221; on the Riemann<br />
sphere. From a mathematical point of view, the dessins are important<br />
because the absolute Galois group Gal(\bar{Q}/Q) acts faithfully on<br />
them. We argue that the relation between the dessins and Seiberg-Witten<br />
theory is useful because gauge theory criteria used to distinguish<br />
branches of N=1 vacua can lead to mathematical invariants that help to<br />
distinguish dessins belonging to different Galois orbits. For instance,<br />
we show that the confinement index defined in hep-th/0301006 is a Galois<br />
invariant. We further make some conjectures on the relation between<br />
Grothendieck&#8217;s programme of classifying dessins into Galois orbits and<br />
the physics problem of classifying phases of N=1 gauge theories.
</p></blockquote>
<p>   <strong>why ?</strong> : Because this paper gives the<br />
best introduction I&#8217;ve seen to Grothendieck&#8217;s dessins d&#8217;enfants<br />
(slightly overdoing it by giving a crash course on elementary Galois<br />
theory in appendix A) and kept me thinking about dessins and their<br />
Galois invariants ever since (again, I&#8217;ll come back to this later). </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/2006-paper-nominees/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
