<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>differential &#8211; neverendingbooks</title>
	<atom:link href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tag/differential/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2008 17:17:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.4</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Arnold’s trinities</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/arnolds-trinities/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/arnolds-trinities/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2008 17:17:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[groups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[math]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[number theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[brain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[differential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Galois]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hexagonal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hyperbolic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Klein]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Manin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mathieu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[monster]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[symmetry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wordpress]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=430</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Referring to the triple of exceptional Galois groups $L_2(5),L_2(7),L_2(11) $ and its connection to the Platonic solids I wrote : &#8220;It sure seems that surprises&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="http://www.fields.utoronto.ca/programs/scientific/96-97/arnold/arnold.jpg" hspace=10 style="float:left;margin-right:10px;" >Referring to the triple of exceptional Galois groups $L_2(5),L_2(7),L_2(11) $ and its connection to the Platonic solids I <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/galois-last-letter.html">wrote</a> : &#8220;It sure seems that surprises often come in triples…&#8221;. Briefly I considered replacing triples by trinities, but then, I didnt want to sound too mystic&#8230;</p>
<p>David Corfield of the <a href="http://golem.ph.utexas.edu/category/2008/06/the_mathematical_sublime.html">n-category cafe</a> and <a href="http://dialinf.wordpress.com/2008/06/11/the-sublime/">a dialogue on infinity</a> (and perhaps other blogs I&#8217;m unaware of) pointed me to the paper <a href="http://www.pdmi.ras.ru/~arnsem/Arnold/arnlect2.ps.gz">Symplectization, complexification and mathematical trinities</a> by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vladimir_Arnold">Vladimir I. Arnold</a>. (Update : <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/ArnoldTrinities.pdf">here</a> is a PDF-conversion of the paper)</p>
<p>The paper is a write-up of the second in a series of three lectures Arnold gave in june 1997 at the meeting in the <a href="http://www.fields.utoronto.ca/">Fields Institute</a> dedicated to his 60th birthday. The goal of that lecture was to explain some mathematical dreams he had.</p>
<blockquote><p>The next dream I want to present is an even more fantastic set of theorems and conjectures. Here I also have no theory and actually the ideas form a kind of religion rather than mathematics.<br />
The key observation is that in mathematics one encounters many trinities. I shall present a list of examples. The main dream (or conjecture) is that all these trinities are united by some rectangular &#8220;commutative diagrams&#8221;.<br />
I mean the existence of some &#8220;functorial&#8221; constructions connecting different trinities. The knowledge of the existence of these diagrams provides some new conjectures which might turn to be true theorems.
</p></blockquote>
<p>Follows a list of 12 trinities, many taken from Arnold&#8217;s field of expertise being differential geometry. I&#8217;ll restrict to the more algebraically inclined ones.</p>
<p><strong>1 :</strong> &#8220;The first trinity everyone knows is&#8221;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="http://matrix.cmi.ua.ac.be/DATA3/trinity3.jpg"></p>
<p>where $\mathbb{H} $ are the Hamiltonian <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quaternion">quaternions</a>. The trinity on the left may be natural to differential geometers who see real and complex and hyper-Kaehler manifolds as distinct but related beasts, but I&#8217;m willing to bet that most algebraists would settle for the trinity on the right where $\mathbb{O} $ are the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octonion">octonions</a>.</p>
<p><strong>2 :</strong> The next trinity is that of the exceptional Lie algebras <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E6_(mathematics)">E6</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E7_(mathematics)">E7</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E8_(mathematics)">E8</a>.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="http://matrix.cmi.ua.ac.be/DATA3/trinity4.jpg"></p>
<p>with corresponding Dynkin-Coxeter diagrams</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="http://matrix.cmi.ua.ac.be/DATA3/dynkins.jpg"></p>
<p>Arnold has this to say about the apparent ubiquity of Dynkin diagrams in mathematics.</p>
<blockquote><p>Manin told me once that the reason why we always encounter this list in many different mathematical classifications is its presence in the hardware of our brain (which is thus unable to discover a more complicated scheme). <br />
I still hope there exists a better reason that once should be discovered.</p></blockquote>
<p>Amen to that. I&#8217;m quite hopeful human evolution will overcome the limitations of Manin&#8217;s brain&#8230;</p>
<p><strong>3 :</strong> Next comes the Platonic trinity of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetrahedron">tetrahedron</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cube">cube</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dodecahedron">dodecahedron</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="http://matrix.cmi.ua.ac.be/DATA3/trinity5.jpg"></p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/f/fc/Tetrahedron.svg/240px-Tetrahedron.svg.png" width=200> <img decoding="async" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a5/Hexahedron.svg/240px-Hexahedron.svg.png" width=200><img decoding="async" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/66/POV-Ray-Dodecahedron.svg/240px-POV-Ray-Dodecahedron.svg.png" width=200><br />
</center></p>
<p>Clearly one can argue against this trinity as follows : a tetrahedron is a bunch of triangles such that there are exactly 3 of them meeting in each vertex, a cube is a bunch of squares, again 3 meeting in every vertex, a dodecahedron is a bunch of pentagons 3 meeting in every vertex&#8230; and we can continue the pattern. What should be a bunch a hexagons such that in each vertex exactly 3 of them meet? Well, only one possibility : it must be the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hexagonal_tiling">hexagonal tiling</a> (on the left below). And in normal Euclidian space we cannot have a bunch of septagons such that three of them meet in every vertex, but in hyperbolic geometry this is still possible and leads to the <a href="http://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/klein.html">Klein quartic</a> (on the right). Check out this wonderful post by John Baez for more on this.</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="http://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/KleinDualInsideOut.gif" width=300><br />
</center></p>
<p><strong>4 :</strong> The trinity of the rotation symmetry groups of the three Platonics</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="http://matrix.cmi.ua.ac.be/DATA3/trinity6.jpg"></p>
<p>where $A_n $ is the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alternating_group">alternating group</a> on n letters and $S_n $ is the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symmetric_group">symmetric group</a>.</p>
<p>Clearly, any rotation of a Platonic solid takes vertices to vertices, edges to edges and faces to faces. For the tetrahedron we can easily see the 4 of the group $A_4 $, say the 4 vertices. But what is the 4 of $S_4 $ in the case of a cube? Well, a cube has 4 body-diagonals and they are permuted under the rotational symmetries. The most difficult case is to see the $5 $ of $A_5 $ in the dodecahedron. Well, here&#8217;s the solution to this riddle</p>
<p><center><br />
<img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/cubedode.jpg"><br />
</center></p>
<p>there are exactly 5 inscribed cubes in a dodecahedron and they are permuted by the rotations in the same way as $A_5 $.</p>
<p><strong>7 :</strong> The seventh trinity involves complex polynomials in one variable</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="http://matrix.cmi.ua.ac.be/DATA3/trinity7.jpg"></p>
<p>the Laurant polynomials and the <strong>modular polynomials</strong> (that is, rational functions with three poles at 0,1 and $\infty $.</p>
<p><strong>8 :</strong> The eight one is another beauty</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="http://matrix.cmi.ua.ac.be/DATA3/trinity8.jpg"></p>
<p>Here &#8216;numbers&#8217; are the ordinary complex numbers $\mathbb{C} $, the &#8216;trigonometric numbers&#8217; are the quantum version of those (aka q-numbers) which is a one-parameter deformation and finally, the &#8216;elliptic numbers&#8217; are a two-dimensional deformation. If you ever encountered a Sklyanin algebra this will sound familiar.</p>
<p>This trinity is based on a paper of Turaev and Frenkel and I must come back to it some time&#8230;</p>
<p>The paper has some other nice trinities (such as those among Whitney, Chern and Pontryagin classes) but as I cannot add anything sensible to it, let us include a few more algebraic trinities. The first one attributed by Arnold to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_McKay_(mathematics)">John McKay</a></p>
<p><strong>13 :</strong> A trinity parallel to the exceptional Lie algebra one is</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="http://matrix.cmi.ua.ac.be/DATA3/trinity9.jpg"></p>
<p>between the 27 straight lines on a cubic surface, the 28 bitangents on a quartic plane curve and the 120 tritangent planes of a canonic sextic curve of genus 4.</p>
<p><strong>14 :</strong> The exceptional Galois groups</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="http://matrix.cmi.ua.ac.be/DATA3/trinity10.jpg"></p>
<p>explained <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/galois-last-letter.html">last time</a>.</p>
<p><strong>15 :</strong> The associated curves with these groups as symmetry groups (as in the previous post)</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="http://matrix.cmi.ua.ac.be/DATA3/trinity11.jpg"></p>
<p>where the ? refers to the mysterious genus 70 curve. I&#8217;ll check with one of the authors whether there is still an embargo on the content of this paper and if not come back to it in full detail.</p>
<p><strong>16 :</strong> The three generations of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sporadic_group">sporadic groups</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="http://matrix.cmi.ua.ac.be/DATA3/trinity12.jpg"></p>
<p><strong>Do you have other trinities you&#8217;d like to worship?</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/arnolds-trinities/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Quiver-superpotentials</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/quiver-superpotentials/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/quiver-superpotentials/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2008 12:47:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arxiv]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[braid group]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Calabi-Yau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dedekind]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[differential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ginzburg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[groups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hyperbolic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[M-geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mathieu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[necklace]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noncommutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[permutation representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Procesi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[quivers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[representations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[superpotential]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/index.php/quiver-superpotentials.html</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It&#8217;s been a while, so let&#8217;s include a recap : a (transitive) permutation representation of the modular group $\Gamma = PSL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $ is determined by&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s been a while, so let&#8217;s include a recap : a (transitive) permutation representation of the modular group $\Gamma = PSL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $ is determined by the conjugacy class of a cofinite subgroup $\Lambda \subset \Gamma $, or equivalently, to a dessin d&#8217;enfant. We have introduced a <strong>quiver</strong> (aka an oriented graph) which comes from a triangulation of the compactification of $\mathbb{H} / \Lambda $ where $\mathbb{H} $ is the hyperbolic upper half-plane. This quiver is independent of the chosen embedding of the dessin in the Dedeking tessellation. (For more on these terms and constructions, please consult the series <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/the-dedekind-tessellation.html">Modular subgroups</a> and <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/monsieur-mathieu.html">Dessins d&#8217;enfants</a>).</p>
<p>Why are quivers useful? To start, any quiver $Q $ defines a noncommutative algebra, the <strong>path algebra</strong> $\mathbb{C} Q $, which has as a $\mathbb{C} $-basis all oriented paths in the quiver and multiplication is induced by concatenation of paths (when possible, or zero otherwise). Usually, it is quite hard to make actual computations in noncommutative algebras, but in the case of path algebras you can just <strong>see</strong> what happens.</p>
<p>Moreover, we can also <strong>see</strong> the finite dimensional representations of this algebra $\mathbb{C} Q $. Up to isomorphism they are all of the following form : at each vertex $v_i $ of the quiver one places a finite dimensional vectorspace $\mathbb{C}^{d_i} $ and any arrow in the quiver<br />
[tex]\xymatrix{\vtx{v_i} \ar[r]^a &amp; \vtx{v_j}}[/tex] determines a linear map between these vertex spaces, that is, to $a $ corresponds a matrix in $M_{d_j \times d_i}(\mathbb{C}) $. These matrices determine how the paths of length one act on the representation, longer paths act via multiplcation of matrices along the oriented path.</p>
<p>A <strong>necklace</strong> in the quiver is a closed oriented path in the quiver <strong>up to cyclic permutation</strong> of the arrows making up the cycle. That is, we are free to choose the start (and end) point of the cycle. For example, in the one-cycle quiver</p>
<p>[tex]\xymatrix{\vtx{} \ar[rr]^a &amp; &amp; \vtx{} \ar[ld]^b \\ &amp; \vtx{} \ar[lu]^c &amp;}[/tex]</p>
<p>the basic necklace can be represented as $abc $ or $bca $ or $cab $. How does a necklace act on a representation? Well, the matrix-multiplication of the matrices corresponding to the arrows gives a square matrix in each of the vertices in the cycle. Though the dimensions of this matrix may vary from vertex to vertex, what does not change (and hence is a property of the necklace rather than of the particular choice of cycle) is the <strong>trace</strong> of this matrix. That is, necklaces give complex-valued functions on representations of $\mathbb{C} Q $ and by a result of <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/m-geometry-3.html">Artin and Procesi</a> there are enough of them to distinguish isoclasses of (semi)simple representations! That is, linear combinations a necklaces (aka <strong>super-potentials</strong>) can be viewed, after taking traces, as complex-valued functions on all representations (similar to character-functions).</p>
<p>In physics, one views these functions as potentials and it then interested in the points (representations) where this function is extremal (minimal) : the <strong>vacua</strong>. Clearly, this does not make much sense in the complex-case but is relevant when we look at the real-case (where we look at skew-Hermitian matrices rather than all matrices). A motivating example (the <strong>Yang-Mills potential</strong>) is given in Example 2.3.2 of Victor Ginzburg&#8217;s paper <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/math/0612139">Calabi-Yau algebras</a>.</p>
<p>Let $\Phi $ be a super-potential (again, a linear combination of necklaces) then our commutative intuition tells us that extrema correspond to zeroes of all partial differentials $\frac{\partial \Phi}{\partial a} $ where $a $ runs over all coordinates (in our case, the arrows of the quiver). One can make sense of differentials of necklaces (and super-potentials) as follows : the partial differential with respect to an arrow $a $ occurring in a term of $\Phi $ is defined to be the <strong>path</strong> in the quiver one obtains by removing all 1-occurrences of $a $ in the necklaces (defining $\Phi $) and rearranging terms to get a maximal broken necklace (using the cyclic property of necklaces). An example, for the cyclic quiver above let us take as super-potential $abcabc $ (2 cyclic turns), then for example</p>
<p>$\frac{\partial \Phi}{\partial b} = cabca+cabca = 2 cabca $</p>
<p>(the first term corresponds to the first occurrence of $b $, the second to the second). Okay, but then the vacua-representations will be the representations of the quotient-algebra (which I like to call the <strong>vacualgebra</strong>)</p>
<p>$\mathcal{U}(Q,\Phi) = \frac{\mathbb{C} Q}{(\partial \Phi/\partial a, \forall a)} $</p>
<p>which in &#8216;physical relevant settings&#8217; (whatever that means&#8230;) turn out to be <strong>Calabi-Yau algebras</strong>.</p>
<p>But, let us return to the case of subgroups of the modular group and their quivers. Do we have a natural <strong>super-potential</strong> in this case? Well yes, the quiver encoded a triangulation of the compactification of $\mathbb{H}/\Lambda $ and if we choose an orientation it turns out that all &#8216;black&#8217; triangles (with respect to the Dedekind tessellation) have their arrow-sides defining a necklace, whereas for the &#8216;white&#8217; triangles the <strong>reverse</strong> orientation makes the arrow-sides into a necklace. Hence, it makes sense to look at the <strong>cubic</strong> superpotential $\Phi $ being the sum over all triangle-sides-necklaces with a +1-coefficient for the black triangles and a -1-coefficient for the white ones. Let&#8217;s consider an index three example from a previous post</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/quiver3.jpg" style="float:left;margin-right:10px;" ><br />
[tex]\xymatrix{&amp; &amp; \rho \ar[lld]_d \ar[ld]^f \ar[rd]^e &amp; \\<br />
i \ar[rrd]_a &amp; i+1 \ar[rd]^b &amp; &amp; \omega \ar[ld]^c \\<br />
&amp; &amp; 0 \ar[uu]^h \ar@/^/[uu]^g \ar@/_/[uu]_i &amp;}[/tex]</p>
<p>In this case the super-potential coming from the triangulation is</p>
<p>$\Phi = -aid+agd-cge+che-bhf+bif $</p>
<p>and therefore we have a noncommutative algebra $\mathcal{U}(Q,\Phi) $ associated to this index 3 subgroup. Contrary to what I believed at the start of this series, the algebras one obtains in this way from dessins d&#8217;enfants are <strong>far from being Calabi-Yau</strong> (in whatever definition). For example, using a GAP-program written by <a href="http://www.win.ua.ac.be/~rbockl/research/">Raf Bocklandt</a> Ive checked that the growth rate of the above algebra is similar to that of $\mathbb{C}[x] $, so in this case $\mathcal{U}(Q,\Phi) $ can be viewed as a noncommutative curve (with singularities).</p>
<p>However, this is not the case for all such algebras. For example, the vacualgebra associated to the second index three subgroup (whose fundamental domain and quiver were depicted at the end of <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/the-modular-group-and-superpotentials-2.html">this post</a>) has growth rate similar to that of $\mathbb{C} \langle x,y \rangle $&#8230;</p>
<p>I have an outlandish conjecture about the growth-behavior of all algebras $\mathcal{U}(Q,\Phi) $ coming from dessins d&#8217;enfants : <strong>the algebra sees what the monodromy representation of the dessin sees of the modular group (or of the third braid group)</strong>.<br />
I can make this more precise, but perhaps it is wiser to calculate one or two further examples&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/quiver-superpotentials/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Vacation reading</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/vacation-reading/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/vacation-reading/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2007 15:23:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[differential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Galois]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[representations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Riemann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[symmetry]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=30</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Im in the process of writing/revising/extending the course notes for next year and will therefore pack more math-books than normal. These are for a 3rd&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Im in the process of writing/revising/extending the course notes for next year and will therefore pack more math-books than normal.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/reader/0521423538/ref=sib_dp_pt/202-4088950-4861437#reader-link"><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/Kirwan.gif"></a> <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/reader/0521658179/ref=sib_dp_pt/202-4088950-4861437#reader-link"><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/McKeanMoll.gif"></a> <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/reader/052145901X/ref=sib_dp_pt/202-4088950-4861437#reader-link"><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/Moreno.gif"></a></p>
<p>These are for a 3rd year Bachelor course on Algebraic Geometry and a 1st year Master course on Algebraic and Differential Geometry. The bachelor course was based this year partly on Miles Reid&#8217;s <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Undergraduate-Algebraic-Geometry-Mathematical-Society/dp/0521356628">Undergraduate Algebraic Geometry</a> and partly on David Mumford&#8217;s <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Red-Book-Varieties-Schemes-Mathematics/dp/354063293X/">Red Book</a>, but this turned out to be too heavy going. Next year I&#8217;ll be happy if they know enough on algebraic curves. The backbone of these two courses will be Fulton&#8217;s old but excellent <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Algebraic-Curves-Introduction-Geometry-Advanced/dp/0201510103/">Algebraic curves</a>. It&#8217;s self contained (unlike Hartshorne&#8217;s book that assumes a prior course on commutative algebra), contains a lot of exercises and goes on to the Brill-Noether proof of Riemann-Roch. Still, Id like to extend it with the introductory chapter and the chapters on Riemann surfaces from <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Complex-Algebraic-Mathematical-Society-Student/dp/0521423538/">Complex Algebraic Curves</a> by Frances Kirwan, a bit on elliptic and modular functions from <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Elliptic-Curves-Function-Geometry-Arithmetic/dp/0521658179/">Elliptic curves</a> by Henry McKean and Victor Moll and the adelic proof of Riemann-Roch and applications of it to the construction of algebraic codes from <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Algebraic-Curves-Over-Finite-Fields/dp/052145901X/">Algebraic curves over finite fields</a> by Carlos Moreno. If time allows Id love to include also the chapter on <a href="http://kea-monad.blogspot.com/2007/07/riemann-rocks.html">zeta functions</a> but I fear this will be difficult.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/reader/0691124922/ref=sib_dp_pt/202-4088950-4861437#reader-link"><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/AshGross.gif"></a> <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/reader/0123392519/ref=sib_dp_pt/202-4088950-4861437#reader-link"><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/Hellegouarch.gif"></a> <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/reader/0471062618/ref=sib_dp_pt/202-4088950-4861437#reader-link"><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/VanderPoorten.gif"></a></p>
<p>These are to spice up a 2nd year Bachelor course on Representations of Finite Groups with a tiny bit of Galois representations, both as motivation and to wet their appetite for elliptic curves and algebraic geometry. Ive received <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Fearless-Symmetry-Exposing-Patterns-Numbers/dp/0691124922/">Fearless Symmetry</a> by Avner Ash and Robert Gross only yesterday and find it hard to stop reading. It attempts to explain Galois representations and generalized reciprocity laws to a general audience and from what I read so far, they really do a terrific job. Another excellent elementary introduction to elliptic curves and Galois representations is in <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Invitation-Mathematics-Fermat-Wiles-Yves-Hellegouarch/dp/0123392519/">Invitation to the Mathematics of Fermat-Wiles</a> by Yves Hellegouarch. On a gossipy note, the appendix &#8220;The origin of the elliptic approach to Fermat&#8217;s last theorem&#8221; is fun reading. Finally, Ill also take <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Fermats-Canadian-Mathematical-Monographs-Advanced/dp/0471062618/">Introduction to Fermat&#8217;s Last Theorem</a> by Alf van der Poorten along simply because I love his writing style.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/reader/1846140129/ref=sib_dp_pt/202-4088950-4861437#reader-link"><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/OShea.gif"></a> <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/reader/0465082319/ref=sib_dp_pt/202-4088950-4861437#reader-link"><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/Stewart.gif"></a> <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/reader/0883850303/ref=sib_dp_pt/202-4088950-4861437#reader-link"><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/Conwaysensual.gif"></a></p>
<p>These are included just for fun. <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Poincare-Conjecture-Search-Shape-Universe/dp/1846140129/">The Poincare Conjecture</a> by Donal O&#8217;Shea because I know far too little about it, <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Letters-Young-Mathematician-Art-Mentoring/dp/0465082327/">Letters to a Young Mathematician</a> by Ian Stewart because I like the concept of the book and finally <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Sensual-Quadratic-Carus-Mathematical-Monographs/dp/0883850303/">The sensual (quadratic) form</a> by John Conway because I need to have at all times at least one Conway-book nearby.</p>
<p><span id="more-30"></span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/vacation-reading/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>neverendingbooks-geometry (2)</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/neverendingbooks-geometry-2/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/neverendingbooks-geometry-2/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2007 12:32:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Azumaya]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brauer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brauer-Severi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[differential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Galois]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Grothendieck]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jacobian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[moduli]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[necklace]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noncommutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[representations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[topology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/?p=6</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here pdf-files of older NeverEndingBooks-posts on geometry. For more recent posts go here. Seen this quiver? Necklaces (again) B for bricks A for aggregates From&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here pdf-files of older NeverEndingBooks-posts on geometry. For more recent posts <a href="index.php?p=5">go here</a>.</p>
<p><span id="more-12052"></span></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/53.pdf">Seen this quiver?</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/282.pdf">Necklaces (again)</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/281.pdf">B for bricks</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/52.pdf">A for aggregates</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/51.pdf">From Galois to NOG</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/50.pdf">Jacobian update 2</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/256.pdf">Jacobian update</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/265.pdf">Congrats Carolyn!</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/48.pdf">Double Poisson algebras</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/44.pdf">Hyper-resolutions</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/43.pdf">Smooth Brauer-Severis</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/42.pdf">Brauer-Severi varieties</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/41.pdf">Curvatures</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/74.pdf">Differential forms</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/40.pdf">Cotangent bundles</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/39.pdf">Moduli spaces</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/37.pdf">Representation spaces</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/36.pdf">Quiver representations</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/35.pdf">Algebraic vs. differential NOG</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/34.pdf">Path algebras</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/241.pdf">Nog course outline</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/33.pdf">The Azumaya locus does determine the order</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/246.pdf">Differential geometry</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/240.pdf">The one quiver for GL(2,Z)</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/138.pdf">The necklace Lie bialgebra</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/137.pdf">More noncommutative manifolds</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/135.pdf">Points and lines</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/125.pdf">Projects in noncommutative geometry</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/118.pdf">Noncommutative geometry 2</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/115.pdf">Noncommutative geometry 1</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/113.pdf">A noncommutative Grothendieck topology</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/116.pdf">Connected component coalgebra</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/100.pdf">NOG master class update</a></p>
<p><a href="NEBPDFS/93.pdf">NOG master class</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/neverendingbooks-geometry-2/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>the Manin-Marcolli cave</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/the-manin-marcolli-cave/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/the-manin-marcolli-cave/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2007 11:29:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arxiv]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[differential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Manin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marcolli]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[modular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[non-commutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noncommutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[topology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=208</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Yesterday, Yuri Manin and Matilde Marcolli arXived their paper Modular shadows and the Levy-Mellin infinity-adic transform which is a follow-up of their previous paper Continued&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yuri_Manin">Yuri Manin</a> and <a href="http://www.math.fsu.edu/~marcolli/">Matilde Marcolli</a> arXived their paper<br />
<a href="http://www.arxiv.org/abs/math.NT/0703718">Modular shadows and the Levy-Mellin infinity-adic transform</a> which is a<br />
follow-up of their previous paper <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/abs/math.NT/0102006">Continued fractions, modular symbols, and non-commutative geometry</a>.<br />
  They motivate the title of the recent paper by :</p>
<blockquote><p> In<br />
[MaMar2](http://www.arxiv.org/abs/hep-th/0201036), these and similar<br />
results were put in connection with the so called  &#8220;holography&#8221;<br />
principle in modern theoretical physics. According to this principle,<br />
quantum field theory on a space may be faithfully reflected by an<br />
appropriate theory  on the boundary of this space. When this boundary,<br />
rather than the interior, is  interpreted as our observable<br />
space‚Äìtime, one can proclaim that the ancient Plato&#8217;s  cave metaphor<br />
is resuscitated in this sophisticated guise. This metaphor motivated<br />
the title of the present paper.  </p></blockquote>
<p>Here&#8217;s a layout of<br />
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allegory_of_the_cave">Plato&#8217;s cave</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/platocave.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<blockquote><p>
Imagine prisoners, who have been chained since childhood deep inside an<br />
cave: not only are their limbs immobilized by the chains; their heads<br />
are chained as well, so that their gaze is fixed on a wall.<br /> Behind<br />
the prisoners is an enormous fire, and between the fire and the<br />
prisoners is a raised walkway, along which statues of various animals,<br />
plants, and other things are carried by people. The statues cast shadows<br />
on the wall, and the prisoners watch these shadows. When one of the<br />
statue-carriers speaks, an echo against the wall causes the prisoners to<br />
believe that the words come from the shadows. <br /> The prisoners<br />
engage in what appears to us to be a game: naming the shapes as they<br />
come by. This, however, is the only reality that they know, even though<br />
they are seeing merely shadows of images. They are thus conditioned to<br />
judge the quality of one another by their skill in quickly naming the<br />
shapes and dislike those who begin to play poorly. <br /> Suppose a<br />
prisoner is released and compelled to stand up and turn around. At that<br />
moment his eyes will be blinded by the firelight, and the shapes passing<br />
will appear less real than their shadows. </p></blockquote>
<p>Right, now how<br />
does the <strong>Manin-Marcolli cave</strong> look? My best guess is : like this<br />
picture, taken from <a href="http://www.math.harvard.edu/~ctm/gallery/">Curt McMullen&#8217;s Gallery</a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/maninmarcollicave.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>Imagine<br />
this as the top view of a spherical cave. M&amp;M are imprisoned in the<br />
cave, their heads chained preventing them from looking up and see the<br />
ceiling (where $PSL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $ (or a cofinite subgroup of<br />
it) is acting on the upper-half plane via<br />
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M√∂bius_transformation">Moebius-transformations</a> ). All they can see is the circular exit of the<br />
cave. They want to understand the complex picture going on over their<br />
heads from the only things they can observe, that is the action of<br />
(subgroups of) the modular group on the cave-exit<br />
$\mathbb{P}^1(\mathbb{R}) $.  Now, the part of it consisting<br />
of orbits of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cusps">cusps</a><br />
$\mathbb{P}^1(\mathbb{Q}) $ has a nice algebraic geometric<br />
description, but orbits of irrational points cannot be handled by<br />
algebraic geometry as the action of $PSL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $ is<br />
highly non-discrete as illustrated by another picture from McMullen&#8217;s<br />
gallery</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/actionreals.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>depicting the ill behaved topology of the action on the bottom real<br />
axis. Still, noncommutative _differential_ geometry is pretty good at<br />
handling such ill behaved quotient spaces and it turns out that as a<br />
noncommutative space, this quotient<br />
$\mathbb{P}^1(\mathbb{R})/PSL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $ is rich enough<br />
to recover many important aspects of the classical theory of modular<br />
curves.  Hence, they reverse the usual NCG-picture of interpreting<br />
commutative objects as shadows of noncommutative ones. They study the<br />
_noncommutative shadow_<br />
$\mathbb{P}^1(\mathbb{R})/PSL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $ of a classical<br />
commutative object, the quotient of the action of the modular group (or<br />
a cofinite subgroup of it) on the upper half-plane.</p>
<p>In our<br />
noncommutative geometry course we have already<br />
seen this noncommutative shadow in action (though at a very basic<br />
level). Remember that we first described the group-structure of the<br />
modular group $PSL_2(\mathbb{Z}) = C_2 \ast C_3 $ via the<br />
classical method of groups acting on trees. In particular, we<br />
considered the tree</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA/actionmoebius.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<p>and<br />
calculated the stabilizers of the end points of its fundamental domain<br />
(the thick circular edge). But<br />
later we were able to give a<br />
much shorter proof (due to Roger Alperin) by looking only at the action<br />
of $PSL_2(\mathbb{Z}) $ on the irrational real numbers (the<br />
noncommutative shadow).  Needless to say that the results obtained by<br />
Manin and Marcolli from staring at their noncommutative shadow are a lot<br />
more intriguing&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/the-manin-marcolli-cave/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>noncommutative bookmarks</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/noncommutative-bookmarks/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/noncommutative-bookmarks/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2007 09:17:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[anabelian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Connes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[differential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kontsevich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noncommutative]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=202</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[At last, some excitement about noncommutative geometry in the blogosphere. From what I deduce from reading the first posts, Arup Pal set up a new&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At<br />
last, some excitement about noncommutative geometry in the blogosphere.
</p>
</p>
<p>From what I deduce from reading the first posts, <a href="http://www.isid.ac.in/~arup/">Arup Pal</a> set up a new blog<br />
called <a href="http://noncommutativegeometry.blogspot.com/">Noncommutative<br />
Geometry</a> and subsequently handed it over to <a href="http://www.math.uwo.ca/~masoud/cv/">Masoud Khalkhali</a> who then<br />
got Alain Connes to post on it who, in turn, is asking people to submit<br />
posts, such as todays post by <a href="http://www.math.ohio-state.edu/~goss/">David Goss</a>. </p>
<p>Somehow, most people refer to the Noncommutative Geometry blog as<br />
&#8220;Alain Connes&#8217; blog&#8221; (for example  <a href="http://doctorgero.livejournal.com/32369.html">Doctor Gero</a>, <a href="http://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=526">Not Even<br />
Wrong</a>, <a href="http://golem.ph.utexas.edu/category/2007/02/how_to_write_mathematics_badly.html">the n-category cafe</a> and<br />
possibly many others). </p>
<p>David Corfield <a href="http://golem.ph.utexas.edu/category/2007/02/noncommutative_geometry_blog.html">over at the n-category cafe</a> stops<br />
short of suggesting to rename (by analogy) NeverEndingBooks into<br />
Kontsevich&#8217;s blog</p>
<blockquote><p>A new blog Noncommutative Geometry<br />
has begun, which appears to be of the Connesian variety. (Connes himself<br />
has already commented there.) We mentioned a couple of weeks ago that<br />
there are different flavours of noncommutative geometry. The<br />
Kontsevichian variety, nongeometry, finds its blog voice in Lieven Le<br />
Bruyn‚Äôs NeverEndingBooks. It would be interesting to see some<br />
interaction.</p></blockquote>
<p>I don&#8217;t think I will opt for a dialectic<br />
response to the <a href="http://noncommutativegeometry.blogspot.com/index.html">Noncommutative Geometry Blog</a>, although I realize this would result<br />
in more enjoyable reading for some of you&#8230;</p>
<p>For starters,<br />
I&#8217;ve signed up to another flagship of noncommutative<br />
_differential_ geometry : <a href="http://www.noncommutativegeometry.net/">noncommutativegeometry.net</a>, though it is unclear to me what action (if any) is<br />
going on over there.</p>
<p>Further, I plan to move my talks at the <a href="http://www.math.ua.ac.be/algebra/seminar.php">master class<br />
noncommutative geometry</a> to the virtual lecture room of this blog,<br />
hoping to get the desired interaction. We&#8217;ll start later this week and<br />
the pace will be pretty easy going.  A tentative title might be<br />
&#8220;Anabelian versus Noncommutative Geometry&#8221;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/noncommutative-bookmarks/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>non-geometry</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/non-geometry/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/non-geometry/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2006 12:44:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[coalgebras]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Connes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cuntz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[differential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ginzburg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kontsevich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[non-commutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noncommutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quillen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[quivers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[representations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[simples]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=247</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here&#8217;s an appeal to the few people working in Cuntz-Quillen-Kontsevich-whoever noncommutative geometry (the one where smooth affine varieties correspond to quasi-free or formally smooth algebras)&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here&#8217;s<br />
an appeal to the few people working in Cuntz-Quillen-Kontsevich-whoever<br />
noncommutative geometry (the one where smooth affine varieties<br />
correspond to quasi-free or formally smooth algebras) : let&#8217;s rename our<br />
topic and call it <strong>non-geometry</strong>. I didn&#8217;t come up with<br />
this term, I heard in from Maxim Kontsevich in a talk he gave a couple<br />
of years ago in Antwerp. There are some good reasons for this name<br />
change.</p>
<p>The term _non-commutative geometry_ is already taken by<br />
much more popular subjects such as _Connes-style noncommutative<br />
differential geometry_ and _Artin-style noncommutative algebraic<br />
geometry_. Renaming our topic we no longer have to include footnotes<br />
(such as the one in the recent <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/abs/math.RA/0606241">Kontsevich-Soibelman<br />
paper</a>) :</p>
<blockquote><p>  We use &#8220;formal&#8221; non-commutative geometry<br />
in tensor categories, which is different from  the non-commutative<br />
geometry in the sense of Alain Connes.  </p></blockquote>
<p>or to make a<br />
distinction between _noncommutative geometry in the small_ (which is<br />
Artin-style) and _noncommutative geometry in the large_ (which in<br />
non-geometry) as in the <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/abs/math.AG/0506603">Ginzburg notes</a>. </p>
<p>Besides, the stress in _non-commutative geometry_ (both in Connes-<br />
and Artin-style) in on _commutative_. Connes-style might also be called<br />
&#8216;K-theory of $C^*$-algebras&#8217; and they use the topological<br />
information of K-theoretic terms in the commutative case as guidance to<br />
speak about geometrical terms in the nocommutative case. Similarly,<br />
Artin-style might be called &#8216;graded homological algebra&#8217; and they<br />
use Serre&#8217;s homological interpretation of commutative geometry to define<br />
similar concepts for noncommutative algebras. Hence, non-commutative<br />
geometry is that sort of non-geometry which is almost<br />
commutative&#8230;</p>
<p>But the main point of naming our subject<br />
non-geometry is to remind us not to rely too heavily on our<br />
(commutative) geometric intuition. For example, we would expect a<br />
manifold to have a fixed dimension. One way to define the dimension is<br />
as the trancendence degree of the functionfield. However, from the work<br />
of Paul Cohn (I learned about it through Aidan Schofield) we know that<br />
quasi-free algebras usually do&#8217;nt have a specific function ring of<br />
fractions, rather they have infinitely many good candidates for it and<br />
these candidates may look pretty unrelated. So, at best we can define a<br />
_local dimension_ of a noncommutative manifold at a point, say given by<br />
a simple representation. It follows from the Cunz-Quillen tubular<br />
neighborhood result that the local ring in such a point is of the<br />
form</p>
<p>$M_n(\mathbb{C} \langle \langle z_1,\ldots,z_m \rangle<br />
\rangle) $</p>
<p>(this s a noncommutative version of the classical fact<br />
than the local ring in a point of a d-dimensional manifold is formal<br />
power series $\mathbb{C} [[ z_1,\ldots,z_d ]] $) but in non-geometry both<br />
m (the _local_ dimension) and n (the dimension of the simple<br />
representation) vary from point to point. Still, one can attach to the<br />
quasi-free algebra A a finite amount of data (in fact, a _finite_ quiver<br />
and dimension vector) containing enough information to compute the (n,m)<br />
couples for _all_ simple points (follows from the <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/abs/math.RA/0304196">one quiver to rule them<br />
all paper</a> or see <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/abs/math.RA/0406618">this</a> for more<br />
details). </p>
<p>In fact, one can even extend this to points<br />
corresponding to semi-simple representations in which case one has to<br />
replace the matrix-ring above by a ring Morita equivalent to the<br />
completion of the path algebra of a finite quiver, the _local quiver_ at<br />
the point (which can also be computer from the one-quiver of A. The<br />
local coalgebras of distributions at such points of<br />
Kontsevich&amp;Soibelman are just the dual coalgebras of these local<br />
algebras (in <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/abs/math.RA/0606241">math.RA/0606241</a> they<br />
merely deal with the n=1 case but no doubt the general case will appear<br />
in the second part of their paper).</p>
<p>The case of the semi-simple<br />
point illustrates another major difference between commutative geometry<br />
and non-geometry, whereas commutative simples only have self-extensions<br />
(so the distribution coalgebra is just the direct sum of all the local<br />
distributions) noncommutative simples usually have plenty of<br />
non-isomorphic simples with which they have extensions, so to get at the<br />
global distribution coalgebra of A one cannot simply add the locals but<br />
have to embed them in more involved coalgebras.</p>
<p>The way to do it<br />
is somewhat concealed in <a href="http://www.math.ua.ac.be/~lebruyn/paper/lebruyn2002d.pdf">the<br />
third version of my neverending book</a> (the version that most people<br />
found incomprehensible). Here is the idea : construct a huge uncountable<br />
quiver by taking as its vertices the isomorphism classes of all simple<br />
A-representations and with as many arrows between the simple vertices S<br />
and T as the dimension of the ext-group between these simples (and<br />
again, these dimensions follow from the knowledge of the one-quiver of<br />
A). Then, the global coalgebra of distributions of A is the limit over<br />
all cotensor coalgebras corresponding to finite subquivers). Maybe I&#8217;ll<br />
revamp this old material in connection with the Kontsevich&amp;Soibelman<br />
paper(s) for the mini-course I&#8217;m supposed to give in september.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/non-geometry/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>citeUlike</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/citeulike/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/citeulike/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2006 14:09:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arxiv]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[differential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noncommutative]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=164</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thanks to Andrei Sobolevskii for his comment pointing me to a wonderful initiative : CiteULike. What is CiteULike? CiteULike is a free service to help&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanks<br />
to Andrei Sobolevskii for his comment<br />
pointing me to a wonderful initiative : <a href="http://www.citeulike.org/">CiteULike</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p> What is CiteULike?<br />  CiteULike is a<br />
free service to help academics to share, store, and organise the<br />
academic papers they are reading. When you see a paper on the web that<br />
interests you, you can click one button and have it added to your<br />
personal library. CiteULike automatically extracts the citation details,<br />
so there&#8217;s no need to type them in yourself. It all works from<br />
within your web browser. There&#8217;s no need to install any special<br />
software.<br />  Because your library is stored on the server, you<br />
can access it from any computer. You can share you library with others,<br />
and find out who is reading the same papers as you. In turn, this can<br />
help you discover literature which is relevant to your field but you may<br />
not have known about.<br />  When it comes to writing up your<br />
results in a paper, you can export your library to either BibTeX or<br />
Endnote to build it in to your bibliography. CiteULike has a flexible<br />
filing system, so you actually stand a chance of being able to find that<br />
article that you stored a few months ago when you need<br />
it. </p></blockquote>
<p>   If all this seems too abstract, <a href="http://savageminds.org/2005/06/27/tutorial-how-to-use-citeulike-with-anthrosource/#more-122">here is an excellent practical<br />
introduction</a> (also suggested by Andrei). This text focusses on<br />
articles from AnthroSource but if you&#8217;re a mathematician, do the<br />
same things when you are at the abstract page of a paper on the <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/">arXiv</a> or a paper description from <a href="http://www.ams.org/mathscinet">MathSciNet</a>. The really nice<br />
thing is that you virtually have to do no typing at all (apart from the<br />
tags you want to add to classify the paper where you want it or, if you<br />
want, to add a note about the paper).     Another exciting feature<br />
is that you can upload your personal copy of the paper. A typical<br />
situation : most of us can get the PDF-file of a published paper at work<br />
(because the university has a contract with the publisher) but not at<br />
home, on the road or on vacation. So, while at work, download the PDF,<br />
upload it as your personal copy to citeUlike and you can read that paper<br />
wherever you have internet access!    But there is more : you can<br />
export the BibTeX-data of your whole library and use it in your next<br />
paper, every library has its separate RSS-feed so you can feed it to a<br />
news-aggregator (or to bloglines) to find out whether someone with<br />
similar interests added a new paper to his/her library, you can create<br />
Groups that is collections of Libraries of people interested in the same<br />
topic, so that others can help you finding stuff of value (and again,<br />
such Group-libraries have there own RSS-feed so&#8230;.), all libraries<br />
have all tags used by the Library-owner in a graphical format, the<br />
larger the tag-text the more it is used in the Library, so just by<br />
looking at the right-sidebar you get a good idea what the person&#8217;s<br />
interests are, etc. etc. etc.    I&#8217;m just two days into<br />
citeUlike and there will be tons of features I still have to discover<br />
and I&#8217;ll report on this later. At the moment I just added a few<br />
papers to my Library but I will extend this drasticly in the weeks<br />
ahead. If you want to check on my progress here is <a href="http://www.citeulike.org/user/lieven">lieven&#8217;s Library</a><br />
or the citeIlike link in the header of this blog (between the<br />
&#8216;about me&#8217; and the &#8217;search&#8217; link) and I hope<br />
that many of you will add similar buttons on your homepages.<br />
Finally, if you are interested in Noncommutative algebraic and/or<br />
differential geometry, I&#8217;ve set up a Group-Library <a href="http://www.citeulike.org/group/NoncommutativeGeometry"><br />
NoncommutativeGeometry</a>. At the moment it&#8217;s just identical to<br />
my own Library, but please register to citeUlike, set up your own<br />
Library and if you&#8217;re into NOG join this group!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/citeulike/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>nostalgia</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/nostalgia/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/nostalgia/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2005 18:29:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[apple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[arxiv]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Connes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[differential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[non-commutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tiger]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=272</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Unlike the cooler people out there, I haven&#8217;t received my _pre-ordered_ copy (via AppleStore) of Tiger yet. Partly my own fault because I couldn&#8217;t resist&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Unlike the<br />
<a href="http://www.rousette.org.uk/blog/archives/2005/05/04/shiny-tiger-things/">cooler people</a> out there, I haven&#8217;t received my<br />
_pre-ordered_ copy (via AppleStore) of <a href="http://www.apple.com/macosx/">Tiger</a> yet. Partly my own fault<br />
because I couldn&#8217;t resist the temptation to bundle up with a<br />
personalized <a href="http://www.apple.com/ipodphoto/">iPod Photo</a>!<br />
The good news is that it buys me more time to follow the <a href="http://www.macdevcenter.com/pub/a/mac/2005/04/26/tiger.html"><br />
housecleaning tips</a>. First, my idea was to make a <a href="http://www.bombich.com/software/ccc.html">CarbonCopyClooner</a>&#8211;<br />
image of my iBook and put it on the _iMac_ upstairs which I<br />
rarely use these days, do a <a href="http://www.macdevcenter.com/pub/a/mac/2005/04/29/tiger.html">clean<br />
Tiger install</a> on the iBook and gradually copy over the essential<br />
programs and files I need (and only those!). But reading the<br />
macdev-article, I think it is better to keep my iBook running Panther<br />
and experiment with Tiger on the redundant iMac. (Btw. unless you want<br />
to have a copy of my Mac-installation there will be hardly a point<br />
checking this blog the next couple of weeks as I intend to write down<br />
all details of the Panther/Tiger switch here.)  </p>
<p>Last week-end I<br />
started a _Paper-rescue_ operation, that is, to find among the<br />
multiple copies of books/papers/courses, the ones that contain all the<br />
required material to re-TeX them and unfortunately my _archive_<br />
is in a bad state. There is hardly a source-file left of a paper prior<br />
to 1999 when I started putting all my papers on the <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/">arXiv</a>. </p>
<p>On the other hand, I do<br />
have saved most of my undergraduate courses. Most of them were still<br />
using postscript-crap like _epsfig_ etc. so I had to convert all<br />
the graphics to PDFs (merely using <a href="http://www.apple.com/macosx/features/pdf/">Preview</a> ) and<br />
modify the epsfig-command to _includegraphics_. So far, I<br />
converted all my undergraduate _differential geometry_ courses<br />
from 1998 to this year and made them available in a uniform<br />
screen-friendly viewing format at <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/toolkit/pdfdir.php?dir=%2FTheLibrary%2Fundergraduate%2F">TheLibrary/undergraduate</a>.</p>
<p>There are two<br />
ways to read the changes in these courses over the years. (1) as a shift<br />
from _differential_ geometry to more _algebraic_ geometry<br />
and (2) as a shift towards realism wrt.the level of our undegraduate<br />
students. In <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/toolkit/pdffile.php?pdf=%2FTheLibrary%2Fundergraduate%2Fdiff1998.pdf">1998</a> I was still thinking<br />
that I could teach them an easy way into Connes non-commutative standard<br />
model but didn&#8217;t go further than the Lie group sections (maybe one day<br />
I&#8217;ll rewrite this course as a graduate course when I ever get<br />
reinterested in the Connes&#8217; approach). In <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/toolkit/pdffile.php?pdf=%2FTheLibrary%2Fundergraduate%2Fdiff1999.pdf">1999</a> I had the illusion that<br />
it might be a good idea to introduce manifolds-by-examples coming from<br />
operads! In <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/toolkit/pdffile.php?pdf=%2FTheLibrary%2Fundergraduate%2Fdiff2000.pdf">2000</a> I gave in to the fact<br />
that most of the students which had to follow this course were applied<br />
mathematicians so perhaps it was a good idea to introduce them to<br />
dynamical systems (quod non!). The <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/toolkit/pdffile.php?pdf=%2FTheLibrary%2Fundergraduate%2Fdiff2001.pdf">2001</a> course is probably the<br />
most realistic one while still doing standard differential geometry. In<br />
<a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/toolkit/pdffile.php?pdf=%2FTheLibrary%2Fundergraduate%2Fdiff2002.pdf">2002</a> I used the conifold<br />
singularity and conifold transitions (deformations and blow-ups) as<br />
motivation but it was clear that the students did have difficulties with<br />
the blow-up part as they didn&#8217;t have enough experience in<br />
_algebraic_ geometry. So the <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/toolkit/pdffile.php?pdf=%2FTheLibrary%2Fundergraduate%2Fdiff2004.pdf">last two years</a> I&#8217;m giving an<br />
introduction to algebraic geometry culminating in blow-ups and some<br />
non-commutative geometry.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/nostalgia/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>pdfsync</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/pdfsync/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/pdfsync/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2005 09:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[differential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[geometry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LaTeX]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[non-commutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[quivers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Riemann]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=302</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I expect to be writing a lot in the coming months. To start, after having given the course once I noticed that I included a&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I<br />
expect to be writing a lot in the coming months. To start, after having<br />
given the course once I noticed that I included a lot of new material<br />
during the talks (mainly concerning the component coalgebra and some<br />
extras on non-commutative differential forms and symplectic forms) so<br />
I\&#8217;d better update the Granada notes<br />
soon as they will also be the basis of the master course I\&#8217;ll start<br />
next week. Besides, I have to revise the <a href="http://www.arxiv.org/abs/math.RA/0406618">Qurves and<br />
Quivers</a>-paper and to start drafting the new bachelor courses for<br />
next academic year (a course on representation theory of finite groups,<br />
another on Riemann surfaces and an upgrade of the geometry-101 course).
 </p>
<p>So, I\&#8217;d better try to optimize my LaTeX-workflow and learn<br />
something about the <a href="http://itexmac.sourceforge.net/pdfsync.html">pdfsync package</a>.<br />
Here is what it is supposed to do :  </p>
<blockquote>
<p>pdfsync is<br />
an acronym for synchronization between a pdf file and the TeX or so<br />
source file used in the production process. As TeX system is not a<br />
WYSIWYG editor, you cannot modify the output directly, instead, you must<br />
edit a source file then run the production process. The pdfsync helps<br />
you finding what part of the output corresponds to what line of the<br />
source file, and conversely what line of the source file corresponds to<br />
a location of a given page in the ouput. This feature is achieved with<br />
the help of an auxiliary file: foo.pdfsync corresponding to a foo.pdf.
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>All you have to do is to put the pdfsync.sty file<br />
in the directory _~/Library/texmf/tex/latex/pdfsync.sty_ and to<br />
include the pdfsync-package in the preamble of the LaTeX-document. Under<br />
my default iTex-front-end <a href="http://www.uoregon.edu/~koch/texshop/texshop.html">TeXShop</a> it<br />
works well to go from a spot in the PDF-file to the corresponding place<br />
in the source-code, but in the other direction it only shows the<br />
appropriate page rather than indicate the precise place with a red dot<br />
as it does in the alternative front-end <a href="http://itexmac.sourceforge.net/">iTeXMac</a>.  </p>
<p>A major<br />
drawback for me is that pdfsync doesn\&#8217;t live in harmony with my<br />
favorite package for drawing commutative diagrams <a href="http://ftp.ktug.or.kr/tex-archive/nonfree/macros/generic/diagrams/
taylor/">diagrams.sty</a>. For example, the 75 pages of the current<br />
version of the Granada notes become blown-up to 96 pages because each<br />
commutative diagram explodes to nearly page size! So I will also have to<br />
translate everything to <a href="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/TeXdoc/xypic/xyguide-html/">xymatrix</a>&#038;#<br />
8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/pdfsync/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
