<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>WikiLeaks &#8211; neverendingbooks</title>
	<atom:link href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tag/wikileaks/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 May 2011 11:30:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>If Bourbaki=WikiLeaks then Weil=Assange</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/if-bourbakiwikileaks-then-weilassange/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/if-bourbakiwikileaks-then-weilassange/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2011 11:30:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bourbaki]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chevalley]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[de Possel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[groups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Weil]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WikiLeaks]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=5144</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In an interview with readers of the Guardian, December 3rd 2010, Julian Assange made a somewhat surprising comparison between WikiLeaks and Bourbaki, sorry, The Bourbaki&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/WeilAssange.jpg"></p>
<p>In an interview with readers of the <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/blog/2010/dec/03/julian-assange-wikileaks">Guardian, December 3rd 2010</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julian_Assange">Julian Assange</a>  made a somewhat surprising comparison between <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WikiLeaks">WikiLeaks</a> and Bourbaki, sorry, The Bourbaki (sic) :</p>
<p>&#8220;I originally tried hard for the organisation to have no face, because I wanted egos to play no part in our activities. <strong>This followed the tradition of the French anonymous pure mathematians, who wrote under the collective allonym, &#8220;The Bourbaki&#8221;.</strong>  However this quickly led to tremendous distracting curiosity about who and random individuals claiming to represent us. In the end, someone must be responsible to the public and only a leadership that is willing to be publicly courageous can genuinely suggest that sources take risks for the greater good. In that process, I have become the lightening rod. I get undue attacks on every aspect of my life, but then I also get undue credit as some kind of balancing force.&#8221;</p>
<p>Analogies are never perfect, but perhaps Assange should have taken it a bit further and studied the history of the pre-war Bourbakistas in order to avoid problems that led to the eventual split-up.</p>
<p>Clearly, if Bourbaki=WikiLeaks, then Assange plays the role of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/André_Weil">Andre Weil</a>. Both of them charismatic leaders, convincing the group around them that for the job at hand to succeed, it is best to work as a collective so that individual  contributions cannot be traced.</p>
<p>At first this works well. Both groups make progress and gain importance, also to the outside world. But then, internal problems surface, questioning  the commitment of &#8216;the leader&#8217; to the original project.</p>
<p>In the case of the Bourbakis, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claude_Chevalley">Claude Chevalley</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/René_de_Possel">Rene de Possel</a> dropped that bombshell at the second Chancay-meeting in 1937 with a 2 page pamphlet <a href="http://portail.mathdoc.fr/archives-bourbaki/PDF/delms_008.pdf">7 theses de Chancay</a>.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/7thesesChancay.jpg"></p>
<p>&#8220;Criticism on the state of affairs :</p>
<ul>
<li>in general, a certain aging of Bourbaki, which manifests itself in a tendency to neglect internal lively opposition in favor of pursuing visible external succes ((failed) completion of versions, artificial agreement among members of the group).  </li>
<li>in particular, often the working method appears to be that of suffocating any objections in official meetings (via interruptions, not listening, etc. etc.). This tendency didn&#8217;t exist at the <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/where-is-the-royal-poldavian-academy.html">Besse meeting</a>, began to manifest itself at the <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/wheres-bourbakis-escorial.html">Escorial-meeting</a>  and got even worse here at Chancay. Bourbaki-members don&#8217;t pay attention to discussions and the principle of unanimous decision-making is replaced in reality by majority rule.&#8221;  </li>
</ul>
<p>Sounds familiar? Perhaps stretching the analogy a bit one might say that Claude Chevalley&#8217;s and Rene de Possel&#8217;s role within Bourbaki is similar to that of respectively <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birgitta_Jónsdóttir">Birgitta Jónsdóttir</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Domscheit-Berg">Daniel Domscheit-Berg</a> within WikiLeaks.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/BourbakiWikileaks.jpg"></p>
<p>This criticism will be neglected and at the following Bourbaki-meeting in <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/bourbaki-and-the-miracle-of-silence.html">Dieulefit</a> (neither Chevalley nor de Possel were present) hardly any work gets done, largely due to the fact that Andre Weil is more concerned about his personal safety and escapes during the meeting for a couple of days to Switserland, fearing an imminent invasion.</p>
<p>After the Dieulefit-meeting, even though Bourbaki&#8217;s fame is spreading, work on the manuscripts is halted because all members are reserve-officers in the French army and have to prepare for war.</p>
<p>Except for Andre Weil, who&#8217;s touring the world with a clear &#8220;Bourbaki, c&#8217;est moi!&#8221; message, handing out Bourbaki name-cards or invitations to <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/index.php/the-wedding-invitation-that-nearly-killed-andre-weil.html">Betti Bourbaki&#8217;s wedding</a>&#8230; That Andre and Eveline Weil are traveling as Mr. and Mrs. Bourbaki is perhaps best illustrated by the thank-you note, left on their journey through Finland.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/WeilEvelineBourbaki.jpg"></p>
<p>If it were not for the fact that the other members had more pressing matters to deal with, Weil&#8217;s attitude would have resulted in more people dropping out of the group, or continuing the work under another name, a bit like what happens to WikiLeaks and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenLeaks">OpenLeaks</a> today.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/if-bourbakiwikileaks-then-weilassange/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WikiLeaks’ collateral damage : web-anarchy?</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/wikileaks-collateral-damage-web-anarchy/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/wikileaks-collateral-damage-web-anarchy/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 18:44:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[web]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blogging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WikiLeaks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wordpress]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=3658</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[NeB&#8217;s web-stats are orders of magnitude out of normal behavior, something must be going on&#8230; Spam filter : normally between 10 and 20 spam-comments are&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>NeB&#8217;s web-stats are orders of magnitude out of normal behavior, something must be going on&#8230;</p>
<ul>
<li>Spam filter : normally between 10 and 20 spam-comments are trapped. They are removed automatically every 14 days so I only look at them when someone complains a valid comment didn&#8217;t get through. This moment, there are <strong>1007</strong> spam-comments held (already 1020 by the time I post this).</li>
<li>Akismet-plugin : for those who don&#8217;t run a blog, <a href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/akismet/">Akismet</a> is an extremely useful WordPress-plugin getting rid of most spam-comments (before entering the spam-filter). I must admit I don&#8217;t check Akismet-stats regularly but today the message reads : &#8216;Akismet has protected your site from 104,145 spam comments already&#8217; (which is about 10% of all visits&#8230;).</li>
<li>Mail-notifications : this week my email-account is bombarded with spam-comments to approve. Usually there are 1 to 2 such comments a week, now about 20 a day. Part of the problem was that the Akismet-servers were obstructed earlier this week, but the problem persists.</li>
<li>Today&#8217;s stats show more than 4000 hits, 500 uniques. About 3 times average.</li>
</ul>
<p>Do we all really need to get caught in the cross-fire between WikiLeaks- and government-hackers?</p>
<p>I have no intention to post my take on WikiLeaks, simply because it won&#8217;t be original. As to Assange&#8217;s problems with justice : until further evidence comes to light I&#8217;m with <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/naomi-wolf/interpol-the-worlds-datin_b_793033.html">Naomi Wolf</a> on this  (thanks <a href="http://pseudomonad.blogspot.com/2010/12/future.html">Kea</a> for the link).</p>
<p>If NeB goes off-line for a while, you know why&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/wikileaks-collateral-damage-web-anarchy/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
