<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Duncan &#8211; neverendingbooks</title>
	<atom:link href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tag/duncan/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 14:01:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Extending McKay&#8217;s E8 graph?</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/extending-mckays-e8-graph/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/extending-mckays-e8-graph/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 14:01:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[groups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[representations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Duncan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[E8]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[McKay]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=7837</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If you take two Fischer involutions in the monster (elements of conjugacy class 2A) and multiply them, the resulting element surprisingly belongs to one of&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you take two Fischer involutions in the monster (elements of conjugacy class 2A) and multiply them, the resulting element surprisingly belongs to one of just 9 conjugacy classes:</p>
<p>1A,2A,2B,3A,3C,4A,4B,5A or 6A</p>
<p>The orders of these elements are exactly the dimensions of the fundamental root for the extended $E_8$ Dynkin diagram.</p>
<p>This is the content of <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/e8-from-moonshine-groups">John McKay&#8217;s E(8)-observation</a> : there should be a precise relation between the nodes of the extended Dynkin diagram and these 9 conjugacy classes in such a way that the order of the class corresponds to the component of the fundamental root. More precisely, one conjectures the following correspondence:</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/e8monster.png"></p>
<p>John Duncan found such a connection by considering carefully the corresponding moonshine groups and their inter-relation. For more on this, look at the old post <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/e8-from-moonshine-groups">E8 from moonshine groups</a>. The extended Dynkin diagram with these moonshine groups as vertices is:</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/Duncan1.png"></p>
<p>Duncan does this by assigning numbers to moonshine groups: the <em>dimension</em> is the order of the corresponding monster element and the <em>valency</em> is one more than the copies of $C_2$ generated by the Atkin-Lehner involutions in the moonshine group.</p>
<p>One might ask whether there is a graph on all 171 moonshine groups, compatible with the valencies of every vertex.</p>
<p>Now, even for the 9 groups in McKay&#8217;s question, the valencies do not determine the graph uniquely and Duncan proceeds with an ad hoc condition on the edges.</p>
<p>There is a partition on the 9 groups by the property whether or not the index of the intersection with $\Gamma_0(2)$ is at most two. Then Duncan declares that there cannot be an edge between two groups belonging to the same class.</p>
<p>His motivation for this property comes from classical McKay-correspondence for the binary icosahedral group (where the vertices correspond to simple representations $S$, and the edges from $S$ to factors of $S \otimes V_2$, where $V_2$ is the restriction of the standard $2$-dimensional simple for $SU(2)$).</p>
<p>Of the $9$ simples there are only $4$ faithful ones, $5$ come from simples of $A_5$. Because $\Gamma_0(2)$ is a subgroup of the modular group of index 2, he then views $\Gamma_0(2)$ as similar to the subgroup $A_5$ in the binary icosahedral group, and declares a moonshine group to be <em>faithful</em> if its index in the intersection with $\Gamma_0(2)$ is at most two.</p>
<p>One might ask whether there is another, more natural, definition for having an edge (or multiple ones) between <em>arbitrary</em> moonshine groups.</p>
<p>And, what is the full graph on the 171 groups?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/extending-mckays-e8-graph/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>a non-commutative Jack Daniels problem</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/a-non-commutative-jack-daniels-problem/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/a-non-commutative-jack-daniels-problem/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2018 13:56:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[groups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[math]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[noncommutative]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Borcherds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Duncan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jack Daniels]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Norton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ogg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ono]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pizer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Plazas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ricard]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tits]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=7776</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[At a seminar at the College de France in 1975, Tits wrote down the order of the monster group \[ \# \mathbb{M} = 2^{46}.3^{20}.5^9.7^6.11^2.13^3.17·19·23·29·31·41·47·59·71 \]&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/jackdanielsMoonshine.jpg"></p>
<p>At a seminar at the College de France in 1975, Tits wrote down the order of the monster group</p>
<p>\[<br />
\# \mathbb{M} = 2^{46}.3^{20}.5^9.7^6.11^2.13^3.17·19·23·29·31·41·47·59·71 \]</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Ogg">Andrew Ogg</a>, who attended the talk, noticed that the prime divisors are precisely the primes $p$ for which the characteristic $p$ super-singular $j$-invariants are all defined over $\mathbb{F}_p$.</p>
<p>Here&#8217;s Ogg&#8217;s paper on this: <a href="http://www.numdam.org/article/SDPP_1974-1975__16_1_A4_0.pdf">Automorphismes de courbes modulaires</a>,  Séminaire Delange-Pisot-Poitou. Théorie des nombres, tome 16, no 1 (1974-1975).</p>
<p>Ogg offered a bottle of Jack Daniels for an explanation of this coincidence.</p>
<p>Even <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Borcherds">Richard Borcherds</a> didn&#8217;t claim the bottle of Jack Daniels, though his proof of the monstrous moonshine conjecture is believed to be the best explanation, at present.</p>
<p>A few years ago, John Duncan and Ken Ono posted a paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1411.5354">&#8220;The Jack Daniels Problem&#8221;</a>, in which they prove that monstrous moonshine implies that if $p$ is not one of Ogg&#8217;s primes it cannot be a divisor of $\# \mathbb{M}$. However, the other implication remains mysterious.</p>
<p>Duncan and Ono say:</p>
<p>&#8220;This discussion does not prove that every $p ∈ \text{Ogg}$ divides $\# \mathbb{M}$. It merely explains how the first principles of moonshine suggest this implication. Monstrous moonshine is the proof. Does this then provide a completely satisfactory solution to Ogg’s problem? Maybe or maybe not. Perhaps someone will one day furnish a map from the characteristic $p$ supersingular $j$-invariants to elements of order $p$ where the group structure of $\mathbb{M}$ is apparent.&#8221;</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t know whether they claimed the bottle, anyway.</p>
<p>But then, what is the <strong>non-commutative Jack Daniels Problem</strong>?</p>
<p>A footnote on the first page of Conway and Norton&#8217;s &#8216;Monstrous Moonshine&#8217; paper says:</p>
<p>&#8220;Very recently, A. Pizer has shown these primes are the only ones that satisfy a certain conjecture of Hecke from 1936 relating modular forms of weight $2$ to quaternion algebra theta-series.&#8221;</p>
<p>Pizer&#8217;s paper is <a href="https://msp.org/pjm/1978/79-2/pjm-v79-n2-p16-s.pdf">&#8220;A note on a conjecture of Hecke&#8221;</a>.</p>
<p>Maybe there&#8217;s a connection between monstrous moonshine and the arithmetic of integral quaternion algebras. Some hints:</p>
<p>The <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/the-big-picture-is-non-commutative">commutation relations in the Big Picture</a> are reminiscent of the <a href="http://www.m-hikari.com/imf/imf-2012/41-44-2012/perngIMF41-44-2012.pdf">meta-commutation relations for Hurwitz quaternions</a>, originally due to Conway in his booklet on Quaternions and Octonions.</p>
<p>The fact that the $p$-tree in the Big Picture has valency $p+1$ comes from the fact that the Brauer-Severi of $M_2(\mathbb{F}_p)$ is $\mathbb{P}^1_{\mathbb{F}_p}$. In fact, the Big Picture should be related to the Brauer-Severi scheme of $M_2(\mathbb{Z})$.</p>
<p>Then, there&#8217;s Jorge Plazas claiming that Connes-Marcolli&#8217;s $GL_2$-system <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/nc-geometry-and-moonshine">might be related to moonshine</a>.</p>
<p>One of the first things I&#8217;ll do when I return is to run to the library and get our copy of Shimura&#8217;s &#8216;Introduction to the arithmetic theory of automorphic functions&#8217;.</p>
<p>Btw. the bottle in the title image is not a Jack Daniels but the remains of a bottle of Ricard, because I&#8217;m still in the French mountains.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/a-non-commutative-jack-daniels-problem/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
