<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Yoneda &#8211; neverendingbooks</title>
	<atom:link href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/tag/yoneda/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2022 18:53:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Le Guide Bourbaki : Murol(s)</title>
		<link>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/le-guide-bourbaki-murols/</link>
					<comments>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/le-guide-bourbaki-murols/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lieven]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2022 18:53:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[france]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tBC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Besse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Iyanaga]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lang]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MacLane]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Murol]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Serre]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yoneda]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.neverendingbooks.org/?p=10703</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The preparations for the unique Bourbaki-congress in Murols, start already in La Tribu 32 (fall 1953). On page 3: &#8220;Summer 54: To suit Phileas Chevalley,&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The preparations for the unique Bourbaki-congress in Murols, start already in La Tribu 32 (fall 1953). On page 3:</p>
<p>&#8220;Summer 54: To suit Phileas Chevalley, Sammy Fogg and eventual Mexicans and Colombians, this Congress will be held from August 17 to 30. Samuel will look for a hotel in Auvergne, but everyone is asked to also prospect the hotels in his region.&#8221;</p>
<p>One should recall that the ICM 1954 was held in Amsterdam from September 2nd-9th. It was convenient for Chevalley and Eilenberg (who were in the US) and for possible more foreigners to have Bourbaki&#8217;s summer congress just before the ICM.</p>
<p>(Of course, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phileas_Fogg">Phileas Fogg</a> is the main character in Jules Verne&#8217;s Around the World in 80 days.)</p>
<p>A lot of people attended the Murols-meeting (La Tribu 34, &#8216;Congres super-oecumenique du frigidaire et des revetements troues&#8217;).</p>
<p>Apart from the regular crowd (Cartan, Chevalley, Delsarte, Dieudonne, Dixmier, Godement, Koszul, Sammy (=Eilenberg), Samuel, Schwartz, Serre and Weil), there was a guinea-pig (Serge Lang), an &#8216;efficiency expert&#8217; (Saunders MacLane), two &#8216;foreign visitors&#8217; (Hochschild and John Tate) and two &#8216;honorable foreign visitors&#8217; (Iyanaga and Kosaku Yosida).</p>
<p>Probably because of this, extremely detailed travel instructions were given in La Tribu 33 (page 2):</p>
<p>&#8220;Next congress: will be held at the Hotel des Pins, in Murols (Puy-de-Dome) from August 17 to 30.<br />
There is at least one night train departing from Paris, going to Clermont or Issoire, followed by a bus-ride to Murols; details will be given as soon as we know the summer schedules.<br />
For motorized people not coming from the South by the N.9, nor from the West by the N.89: go to Clermont-Ferrand, leave it by the N.9 (route d&#8217;Issoire), turn right about 17 kms further (after the village of Veyre) to take the N.678 towards Champeix; in Champeix take (on the right) the N.496 (direction of St-Nectaire, Murols and Mont-Dore).<br />
For those coming from the South by the N.9: turn left at Issoire to take the N.496 towards Campais, St-Nectaire, Murols. For those coming from the West by the N.89: leave it a little before Lequeille to take (on the right) the N.122, turn left 2 km further to take the N.496 towards Mont-Dore, the Chambon lake and Murols (road continuing towards Champeix and Issoire).&#8221;</p>
<p>If you follow this route on the map, you&#8217;ll know that the congress was not held in <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murols">Murols</a> (departement de l&#8217;Aveyron), but in <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murol">Murol</a> (departement du Puy-de-Dome).</p>
<p>This time we do not have to search long for the place of venue as <a href="https://www.hoteldespins-murol.com/fr/">Hotel des Pins a Murol</a> is still in operation.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.hoteldespins-murol.com/media/filer_public_thumbnails/filer_public/7a/9f/7a9f74d8-c5c6-442e-98cb-bb3fa4123a19/hotel-des-pins-79.jpg__1920x1080_q85_crop_subsampling-2_upscale.jpg" width=100% ></p>
<p>Note the terras on the first floor, and the impressive line of trees in front of the hotel.</p>
<p>At first I felt frustrated as I couldn&#8217;t figure out where this well-known photograph of the Murol-meeting was taken.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://d2r55xnwy6nx47.cloudfront.net/uploads/2020/11/Boubaki-2000_balcony.jpg" width=100% ></p>
<p>From left to right, Godement, Dieudonne, Weil, MacLane, and a smug looking Serre (he knew he would be awarded a Fields medal in a few days time).</p>
<p>Today it is impossible to have this view from the hotel-terras because of the trees in front. Still, the picture was taken from the terras, and the imposing building in the background is the late <a href="http://abandoned-france.org/history-murol-abandoned-hotel.php">Turing Hotel in Murol</a>.</p>
<p>Here&#8217;s a picture of it with the Hotel des Pins in the background.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="http://abandoned-france.org/gallery/albums/Murol_Abandoned_Hotel/07.jpg" width=100% ></p>
<p>We&#8217;ve encountered the Murol-congress before on this blog when trying to piece together <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/le-lemme-de-la-gare-du-nord">the history of the Yoneda lemma</a> (Iyanaga was Yoneda&#8217;s Ph.D. advisor, and probably on his advice MacLane met with Yoneda in the Gare du Nord to hear about his lemma).</p>
<p>On MacLane&#8217;s role as &#8216;efficiency expert&#8217; we have this in La Tribu 34:</p>
<p>&#8220;Frightened by the disorder of the discussions, some members had brought a world-renowned efficiency expert from Chicago. This one, armed with a hammer, tried hard and with good humor,  but without much result. He quickly realized that it was useless, and turned, successfully this time, to photography.&#8221;</p>
<p>As we&#8217;ve seen in <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/le-guide-bourbaki-amboise">Amboise</a> and <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/le-guide-bourbaki-pelvoux">Pelvoux</a>, Bourbaki likes to have His summer venues close to places of great sentimental value.</p>
<p>Murol is very close to Besse-et-Saint Anastaise, the place of the very <a href="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/where-is-the-royal-poldavian-academy">first Bourbaki-meeting in 1935</a>.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/DATA3/murols23.jpg" width=100% ></p>
<p>As always, this asks for a little pilgrimage. From La Tribu 34 (page 2):</p>
<p>&#8220;Despite the incessant rain, Bourbaki was attracted by the waters, and went to explore lots of Auvergnian lakes. Besse and its Lac Pavin were naturally entitled to a pilgrimage. Courageous founding-fathers and lower-members, braving the rain and fog, rushed across to the lake of Guery where their dripping pants aroused the suspicions of a bar maid, and beat the motorized elements there by several lengths. Others swam and rowed. Even the Japanese were entitled to their lake.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://lievenlebruyn.github.io/neverendingbooks/le-guide-bourbaki-murols/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
